Mayank Aggarwal: Hey everyone, very good morning. So, let us begin in just some time, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Funding, let me quickly just set things up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Gita project clone is still not working. I fixed the same, I think people were able to check that out. So, let me… Anyways, I will be fixing it up, I think, today or tomorrow, so it should be fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Good evening, so just give me a couple of minutes, and then we will start.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just a minute…
Mayank Aggarwal: Great, everyone. So, before I start, let me know if anyone has any doubts, because I think we have covered lots of doubt, I hope all of your revising.
Mayank Aggarwal: Today, as I promised, it will be a little bit more practical side.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, yeah, let me provide you with everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Also, if anyone can let me know in the GitHub what error you are facing, because there is a Windows to Mac, some issues with the file thing, so I will quickly fix that.
Mayank Aggarwal: When will we do an end-to-end project after MCP? I think I've told that multiple times. First, master these things, don't worry on the project, like, of course we will do it, but yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great. So, I think we can begin, everyone. Let's quickly start.
Mayank Aggarwal: I actually have a few things messed up. This is not, I think, using VS Code in here.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, Ricky, I will just… From here only.
Mayank Aggarwal: Also, because I have added everything, Go back one.
Mayank Aggarwal: True.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, I don't think too.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, so…
Mayank Aggarwal: Great. Yes, so when we… just one minute, let me fix that GitHub issue as well. Not sure why people are facing it, let me check that. Yes, so I think people are suggesting that GitHub is working, request everyone to do the same. Let's now start, and let me tell you what is the agenda and everything for today.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me share my screen, everyone. I hope all of you are able to see the screen.
Mayank Aggarwal: Shared. Are you able to see the screen, everyone?
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, first thing… Before I move forward, it's discussed on the agenda and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Git, as people are saying, is working, so Git seems to be working, everyone, that's kind of done.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will anyways check and fix the scene. Like, I think there was a few issues here and there, but you will have to give me a little bit of time. But hopefully, I think from this weekend onward, it will be fixed, because I… hopefully, I'm not traveling a lot after this weekend.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then, after that, everyone, today's agenda, we will understand about integrating Desai word.
Mayank Aggarwal: To Claude.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which we kind of stopped yesterday.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then, everyone, we will be understanding how to use… MCP in a… Proper.
Mayank Aggarwal: project, so I have created Time Tracker.
Mayank Aggarwal: as a project, where we will be having… I think I was discussing that with someone in the Q&A last, yesterday. So yes, I thought of, doing the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: After that, I will also be showcasing you around how to use Community servers.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pomdi servers, etc.
Mayank Aggarwal: And in the same, we plan to also have HTTP servers.
Mayank Aggarwal: And host them up.
Mayank Aggarwal: As well. So, hosting them not onto our own machine, but hosting them up onto somewhere on the cloud, so that people can use it.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will be using this, something known as MCP Cloud.
Mayank Aggarwal: fast MCP logo, I guess. So it has been named to, I think, Horizon or something, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is something which we will be using, built it with FastMCP, run it on Hoizen, so they are actually suggesting the same. Good thing is that it is free after, for the very first case, one developer, 200 MCP servers, 1 hour retention.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it can be connected with…
Mayank Aggarwal: Cloud, code, GitHub, and Kulkar, and everything, okay? So that's the idea. Let me quickly see…
Mayank Aggarwal: What all were the different, different… Switch me open yesterday.
Mayank Aggarwal: And most probably, then everyone, by the next class, we will jump back to Langchain after understanding about clients, and just the architectural changes in the latest version of MCP. So that is also required. Though it does not have any issues in the
Mayank Aggarwal: Way we are using it.
Mayank Aggarwal: But still, of course, the same will be required, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, close view of the things.
Mayank Aggarwal: Meanwhile, if anyone has any doubt, let me know in the chat, so that we can…
Mayank Aggarwal: Quickly clear it out, and we can start, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Also, please, another two days longer plan so people do not make noise. Amit people will always make noise, okay? So, not an issue.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool.
Mayank Aggarwal: Any coupons? Yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me try. Can we deploy MCP somewhere in Azure? We can deploy it anywhere, I don't have Azure as of now handy, so yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Sampling and KPC in MCP, did we talk about it? Kpc we have talked about. This last are a few other things which we have to talk about. Pings, error, timeout, canceling, progress notification. So, yeah. How long will be today's class? 3 hours only, I don't want to keep you more than that.
Mayank Aggarwal: We can complete it in the next one, that should not be a problem, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Can we get an idea how it is done in any other cloud? Yes. We… when will we do that, it will be very much clear, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Great.
Mayank Aggarwal: So again, I hope everything is clear. We have been mastering and almost near mastering MCP completely, everyone, so humble request.
Mayank Aggarwal: For any doubts, please ask me in the chat so I can clear it out.
Mayank Aggarwal: Else, let us start.
Mayank Aggarwal: And yes, I think we should be good.
Mayank Aggarwal: When would we jump back to Langchain? Next Saturday or Sunday? Next Saturday, I think it will happen, because I will show you that, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Chetal.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, we will be creating a…
Mayank Aggarwal: project in today's class. Want to make sure that my chat… yes, Ashish, I'm getting the chat, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's start, everyone, let me close a few things up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Shetty?
Mayank Aggarwal: Lots and lots of things are open on my machine, so that is something which I have to just handle.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great. So, let us begin, everyone. Just give me one last minute, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: slow this I can keep open.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just one last minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me share my screen and have your chat and everything properly.
Mayank Aggarwal: this course versus FDE.
Mayank Aggarwal: Whatever you are learning in here should be helpful in the FTE as well, okay? Do we have to clone any repo for today's project? I will give that, don't worry. Okay, so once the time will be right, I will provide you with all the code and everything. So, with that, let's begin, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, first thing, I hope all of you remember that how we actually created an MCP server yesterday. So, quickly, let me help you revise that.
Mayank Aggarwal: That's cool.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP jami is closed because that is not needed.
Mayank Aggarwal: Will you share coupon now or later? I will have to check if I'm able to create them. If I am able to create them, I will share them. Else, I will create them later on in next class. Okay? Cool. So, yes, I hope everyone… you were able to understand how we created the dummy kind of a server, and how we were able to
Mayank Aggarwal: check if it is running properly or not. Anyone has any issues in that? I hope the code is also pinged in, so you must have all tried it out.
Mayank Aggarwal: Right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Any issues, anyone, in this?
Mayank Aggarwal: Anything which is not clear?
Mayank Aggarwal: Just one more quick thing. Just a second, everyone, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Beat.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, so I think it should be fine. Sorry for the mix-up. I was closing lots of things.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, everyone, let's continue our discussion, and in the last part, we saw that how we are able to create our own recipe box past MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: And of course, the same was working. We checked the same out by using the MCP inspector as well. And one thing to note here, even though in the future parts we will be learning that how exactly we can
Mayank Aggarwal: Like, right now, we will also be integrating it with our own
Mayank Aggarwal: Cloud desktop, so that is the very next step. But always, it's a good idea to check against if our server is working or not, so whatever MCP server we have created. If it is working or not.
Mayank Aggarwal: Via here directly. So, in here, we are able to see that, yes, it is working. We are able to get all the right, complete tools. Similarly, we have the prompts, okay? So, we actually are having complete prompt as well. We have the resources as well, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, that is, of course, not always a good approach. That is the reason MCP Inspector exists.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, once we have got the same working, everyone, next obvious step is to make sure that we can integrate
Mayank Aggarwal: Ar…
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP server, which we have created, into Cloud Code. Sorry, Cloud Code, or Cloud, or for that matter now, any of the ChatGPT cursor, or any client, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: which is running on our local, so as of now, I'm going to show you by running it, integrating it in Cloud Code, and that is where
Mayank Aggarwal: this understanding becomes important, so if I get Claude everyone, Let me quickly get Claude.
Mayank Aggarwal: When we talk about Cloud, and when we talk about adding MCP servers to Cloud, so for people who have Claude Desktop installed, you will see Cloud Desktop something like this. In here, you can actually go on connectors.
Mayank Aggarwal: And by default, there are lots and lots of connectors which we can directly use. So you will notice here, everyone, that how we are having
Mayank Aggarwal: lots of connectors which are based on the MCP protocol only. So, these are the official ones. If you click on Add.
Mayank Aggarwal: it actually is asking you to give the MCP server URL and the name. So, yes, if you are having your MCP server hosted, you can give it here. And for that matter, actually, it will work anywhere. We saw in MCP jam as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, MCP Jam, everyone connects with similar applications like Claude, ChatGPT, etc, and then you can add your MCPs exactly there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Coming back, there are actually two ways of
Mayank Aggarwal: Majorly integrating your MCP servers in cloud.
Mayank Aggarwal: One is, by default, by default, the connectors, everyone. So, one, of course, is the connectors by default.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where what happened, you add those connectors, everyone, right into the, complete your own
Mayank Aggarwal: overall claud. And once your cloud starts, it makes sure that it hits and gets the tools list, so the same approach is follows then. It will get the tool list, when you're calling the same, it will hit the same as well. We saw it via the…
Mayank Aggarwal: initial file which I had, so I made sure
Mayank Aggarwal: that in this MCP log, which was actually given by Claude.
Mayank Aggarwal: we were able to see the same, like, how Claude is hitting the server, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: And, of course, Claude is a client, and in that way, other clients are there. So now, everyone, what I will do, first, I will stop this up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear everything up.
Mayank Aggarwal: And pay attention what exactly are the steps. Just one more thing before I move forward, I will just make the name as Recipe Box.
Mayank Aggarwal: updated.
Mayank Aggarwal: The reason is that
Mayank Aggarwal: And I can add a description as well. The reason is that I think I added recipe box before as well, so I want to have that distinction.
Mayank Aggarwal: And once we will be able to add it into Claude Everyone, then easily we will be able to see that all these tools which we are having, we will be able to use them and, of course, further also, make sure that everything is working fine. So the command now which we have to run, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can we integrate the MCP server to Cloud CLI? If not, why? We can integrate it anywhere. Cloud CLI also works, not a problem.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Amlam?
Mayank Aggarwal: Amland, sorry. Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Open code, anything works, any client works, for that matter.
Mayank Aggarwal: Kindly update the dictionary as well, otherwise it will not work with your dictionary.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which dictionary are you talking about?
Mayank Aggarwal: It is fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: Fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: I think it will work.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I will make sure that I'm giving the command in the end, so that all of you will also have it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Command is UV.
Mayank Aggarwal: Run. Fast. MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: install.
Mayank Aggarwal: Claude Desktop, which is nothing but my client.
Mayank Aggarwal: Recipe, box, fast MCP, be bye.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, again, we can use this MCP server with our client. We know the architecture now, just that, up till now, we were seeing many things via MCP inspector, etc. Now, we are making sure that we use the same
Mayank Aggarwal: Directly.
Mayank Aggarwal: Once we do this, everyone, it is getting the description might be wrong, so I think we should have less AI-coded things.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me just… Coldest one.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, k terminal.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear everything up, and now let me run this command.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it is saying, successfully installed recipe box updated in Claude Desktop, so let me quickly explain what exactly I meant. So, when everyone is connectors, okay, which I think all of us have been using, so if I click on Claude.
Mayank Aggarwal: we have different, different connectors, we can discover and add them, okay? And over time, we will try to make sure that we are able to get R directly as well here. So, I showed that how, if you go on Langchain, so, for example.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you go on Langchain, and search for its MCP, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: You are easily able to just
Mayank Aggarwal: copy the MCP server, okay, so MCP server is HTTP-based.
Mayank Aggarwal: And just add the same inherent clock. So I can just do Langchain.
Mayank Aggarwal: And added, something which we have done. On that note, everyone, just one more thing to take away here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Is that…
Mayank Aggarwal: Of course, we can create our own MCP server, and we will be making them more, better, and everything from future, in the future parts. But one thing to note is that
Mayank Aggarwal: your overall, cloud, or any client for that matter, like, your code as well. So tomorrow, well, we will be…
Mayank Aggarwal: creating, let's say, client. So, as of now, we have created server. Similarly, of course, we can create client as well. So, if you search Fast MCP client.
Mayank Aggarwal: There is a way through which you can create client as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Similarly, Langchain, everyone, which is, again, for creating agents and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: In here as well, if you go on the Langchain documentation.
Mayank Aggarwal: Here, as well, we have an MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP adapter, okay? It is built on fast MCP, which handles transport inference, protocol negotiation, connection management, and authentication.
Mayank Aggarwal: And here, as well, we actually create a MCP adapter where we can add and have client, basically, and other overall MCP servers. So the takeaway is that we can
Mayank Aggarwal: Connect.
Mayank Aggarwal: 2?
Mayank Aggarwal: Third Party or global MCP servers.
Mayank Aggarwal: And connect them to our code.
Mayank Aggarwal: Via?
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP client.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, in this, everyone, if we notice, if you search for just MCP servers.
Mayank Aggarwal: you will find that how we have different, different websites, where we have all of these multiple servers present, okay? So, for every day-to-day application which we might be using, there are MCP servers which we can directly connect to. All we have to do is just, let's say, Google MCP server, go to Google MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: And see that, okay, all of this is what it provides, and how you can easily just use it as well. So, let's take some easy one. Maybe the…
Mayank Aggarwal: What we can take up here, let me take…
Mayank Aggarwal: Maybe Fire Crawl MCP, so let's take this one, everyone. It is having these tools. It is all what we can do with this.
Mayank Aggarwal: And if you go on the documentation side, when to use this server and installation see.
Mayank Aggarwal: Connect to the remote hosted server with no setup. So just copy this.
Mayank Aggarwal: And, of course, you can paste the same. If I go back.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's say add.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pasting it, and say fire crawl.
Mayank Aggarwal: And you are just good with adding the symbol, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Next, everyone, is where you want to add your locally hosted servers. So, next is… Where we have the…
Mayank Aggarwal: configuration file.
Mayank Aggarwal: And in this as well, we can actually add
Mayank Aggarwal: our servers. So, add our own MCP servers, which are running locally.
Mayank Aggarwal: Or, normally, To add via.
Mayank Aggarwal: code slash config.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, this is majorly the two ways, everyone, in which Claude normally supports, and for that matter, I guess ChatGPT, Cursor, all of them supports, how we will be adding the MCPs, or MCP servers, to the Cloud, so that we can use the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, first, everyone is you having the local servers. Okay, and you can have the overall, this, your…
Mayank Aggarwal: Global or Mobile… mobile servers as well, which can be connected via connectors.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope this thing is clear, anyone has any doubt in this?
Mayank Aggarwal: And just to clear out one thing, it is not that when we are using the config file.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can just add the local servers? No, all the servers can actually be added. Rather, in the backend, Claude is maintaining those config files when you are adding them into the same. So, this server which I was adding for FireCrawl, I could have added that into the configuration file as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Suhani, I hope that is clear now. Does it need some security certificate or thumbtail to connect from our custom domain? Like, each individual organization has own servers? So, Bala normal authentication, we can add it, we should add, rather, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: In real world, once we test.
Mayank Aggarwal: the MCP locally, we will host them on a server, right? I hope configuration file is for local testing or HTTP available server as well. So, again, normally, configuration file is the main or default way, just that Claude now provides you with the
Mayank Aggarwal: connectors directly as well. Ideally, in the backend, configuration file is maintained, so that is the whole idea, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: What difference between two approaches? I will show you guys that. Just in a bit, I will showcase that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Like, why I'm talking about the same. Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Then how will Claude decide which MCP tool needs to use for input prompt? So, okay, let me make it clear so that all of you will be actually a lot, overall clear with that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, the reason, everyone, I was actually discussing about this complete two ways of adding MCPs in Claude is that when we ran this command up, so when we ran this command, and we saw that how recipe box has been added in Claude desktop.
Mayank Aggarwal: you will not be finding it in here. So if I search for, say, recipe?
Mayank Aggarwal: recipe?
Mayank Aggarwal: box. Of course, we will not find them in connectors. Connectors are just an easy way for laymen and everyone to quickly add their connectors. Similarly, of course, via this ad, as of now, we cannot add that. So, even if I go on this, your connectors, that is where everyone we have to go on this developer, if you will see.
Mayank Aggarwal: There is this developer thing which we have to open in our application.
Mayank Aggarwal: And in here, everyone, we have this config. So, local MCP server, add and manage MCP servers that you are working on, and now we can go on edit configuration.
Mayank Aggarwal: Once you go on Edit Configuration, everyone, what will happen is that
Mayank Aggarwal: it will showcase the position of this file, cloud desktopconfig.json. So, very, very important. This is actually that config file which I was talking about. And in this file, everyone, actually, your servers are added. So, if I showcase the same to you.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me just try to open the same up in our VS Code, maybe. So let me try to showcase by opening in VS Code.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that I can explain it to you as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Although we will have to make sure that we are not moving it, okay, so that thing is very, very important.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me just quickly try to have a copy.
Mayank Aggarwal: of this.
Mayank Aggarwal: and paste it into our DS code.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, paste this.
Mayank Aggarwal: And yeah, see, MCP servers, demo file system wiretapped, so this is actually a server which I have wiretapped, so that I can see the MCP logs and everything. So, this actually is this file, which I will showcase in a bit.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, similarly, recipe box, which I added earlier only, and there is recipe box updated, everyone, which has added. So, what happened is that when Claude Desktop starts.
Mayank Aggarwal: it makes sure that all the servers which are mentioned inside this particular thing, it run those servers. So you will see UV run.
Mayank Aggarwal: with fast MCP run and exact file. And if you think about this, I also run this command here, uvrun, fast
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP?
Mayank Aggarwal: And I can just give recipe box, fast MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: And now, okay, I think the command is UV run.
Mayank Aggarwal: recipe… or UV fast MCP run.
Mayank Aggarwal: Recipe box, pass MCP. So, always get confused in this. Let me quickly get this index, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Chang GPT…
Mayank Aggarwal: Right? Syntax.
Mayank Aggarwal: Run the same. Let's see.
Mayank Aggarwal: UV run fast MCP then. Okay, my bad.
Mayank Aggarwal: You read on Fast MCP run, or you read on Python.
Mayank Aggarwal: Teja. Sorry, my writing. Cool.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I could just clear it up, write the right command.
Mayank Aggarwal: And see, my server actually got started, if you will notice, everyone, fast MCP 4.0.3, and now my server is actually running up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Starting MCP server, recipe box updated with transport STDIO, and in a way, your cloud also will be starting up these servers, because again.
Mayank Aggarwal: Claude client will be connecting to the connecting with the server which it is running. And yes, that is how we can have it. Now, if we go back to Claude, everyone, what I will do is, I will first make sure that I go to the
Mayank Aggarwal: connectors.
Mayank Aggarwal: In this, we will see this recipe box, most probably, but not the recipe box updated. So I'm seeing recipe box, but actually, recipe box updated is not visible, and there is a very, very…
Mayank Aggarwal: Not issue, there is a reason for that. The reason is that, if you go here, everyone, you will notice that how the command is running by UV, and after that, it is having the complete things.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, normally what happens, instead of UV, we have to provide the complete path of UV, like, where exactly the UV is installed in my machine. So, the same is pretty simple as well, everyone. What you can do, you can just execute the shell command.
Mayank Aggarwal: which UV?
Mayank Aggarwal: And it gives you the complete path of the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: like, what I've done is, in here, if I open another terminal, everyone, so let me just delete this.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I open another terminal, just, I could ask which UV?
Mayank Aggarwal: And it is OPTHOMEWINUV. Where exactly it is installed? Like, you can just actually ask which Python
Mayank Aggarwal: And inside this particular thing, it will tell that, hey, this is the Python I'm using. And we can ask for other cases as well. I can deactivate my environment every month, pay attention, clear everything, and now I can ask which UV. And see, it is saying that UV is via Opt Homebrew. I will just go ahead and change it here.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that now my config actually knows where exactly my UV is present, and then run the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope this thing is clear, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope this thing is clear.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anyone has any doubt? What is the command you use first type to add recipe box MCP to Cloud Desktop?
Mayank Aggarwal: This is Devomar.
Mayank Aggarwal: You will run fast MCP, install Cloud Desktop, this MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: Here?
Mayank Aggarwal: Why UV command here? Because we have created a server that it will be starting off with a UV command. You can have via pip or anything else as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: But how for SCP Bocket is not showing?
Mayank Aggarwal: It is above it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nini, so, again, I will make it clear. I made it recipe box updated. Recipe box, I actually fixed this up, right? So, recipe box, I fixed the same up.
Mayank Aggarwal: gear?
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, our server is recipe box updated.
Mayank Aggarwal: Could you please tell how to config MCP in Cloud terminal also? We don't have Claude Desktop configured on JSON.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, again, same things. You will find… you will be able to find in the cloud terminal this thing. Why do we need UV? UV command. Because we are running it via UV, you can run it via pip install or docker, or anything. Not a problem.
Mayank Aggarwal: So UV is used to run the file, right? I'm just using UV to run the file. Because I added it via UV, it is being done by like that. Otherwise, it can be pip install or python 3 run as well. So this server, if you will notice, it is Python 3.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm just running the file, nothing else.
Mayank Aggarwal: For me, I'm just running the file. UV helps in running the file as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: For connectors, we have enable or disable option, but… Through config, how?
Mayank Aggarwal: through config, you remove this. If you have to disable the same, you just remove it or commit this. Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Venki, I think the error is very self-explanatory. You don't have Cloud Desktop installed, so you will have to install the Cloud Desktop, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Where to find this JSON config? Is it auto-created? We only have to replace the pass, or do we have to create it? Okay, please listen, everyone, not sure. I have generally taken this very slow. I will explain it again. Please focus.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just give me a smiley face or a sad face.
Mayank Aggarwal: Are you clear that there are two ways of connecting MCP servers? One via connectors, one via config file?
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope this is clear.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? One via connectors, one via config file.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then, after that, Mayank went to Connectors and showcased that how we are having different, different connectors for everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can discover and see your day-to-day applications.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope that makes sense.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anyone has any doubt in this?
Mayank Aggarwal: Should be clear, we are using Claude, and again, the same thing holds in Claude normally as well. If you go on Claude web, I'm not going to open it right now.
Mayank Aggarwal: After that, everyone, I showcase to you that how you can go to this, let's say, MCP servers.
Mayank Aggarwal: awesome MCP servers, or any other website.
Mayank Aggarwal: And… Just select an MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: And there, the steps will be present. So, how to add it?
Mayank Aggarwal: Copy the same, and you can add it like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: under Add and Custom.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope this thing is also clear.
Mayank Aggarwal: And in future, we will make our MCP server available like this, okay? In future, we will make it available like that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Wanted to know if I don't have Cloud desktop subscription, can I use ChatGPT for free? Cloud Co-work can work too. You can use ChatGPT, should not be a problem. I think ChatGPT has a simple same commands, so…
Mayank Aggarwal: If you just… just go to ChatGPT or Claude and ask that, hey, I have ChatGPT, and what is the command for the same?
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can easily connect your locally running system with that, not a problem at all.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool?
Mayank Aggarwal: Till now, I hope everything is clear.
Mayank Aggarwal: Next, after that, everyone, I told you that how we have a config file as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: We have a config file as well. Let me make it a little bit easier for all of you. We have to go on Developer.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, so just give me a minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, we have to go on Developer.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then we have to click on Edit Config.
Mayank Aggarwal: And this will take us to…
Mayank Aggarwal: Claude.
Mayank Aggarwal: Desktop.
Mayank Aggarwal: config.
Mayank Aggarwal: JSON.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me copy this.
Mayank Aggarwal: the copy button.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, so I think this should be more than clear. I hope this image helps you, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Why do we need it to add in config file? In real time when users install MCP? Then still our code needs to have a code where it will update config to run user machine, because if you want to have your local MCP server, you need to add it in config file. In connectors, it will, of course, not show up, and that is why in the developer side, they have given the same
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah?
Mayank Aggarwal: However, chat GPT, it can mean settings, etc. Everyone, I think you can easily do that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Should not be a problem. Right now, there is no URL, right? It is saying add and manage MCP servers that you are working on. Edit config.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear, everyone?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, majorly, any of the local, any of the servers which are running, or which you want to start when Claude starts, you can do that with here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope now it is done, everyone. Steps are revised.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Yashranda, I'm not going to ask about context management, let's keep it afterwards. Of course, when the server starts, it will have context and everything, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Any other doubt? What is UV.log? Again, Jyoti told you in the starting, so that should be fine. Plugin, please cover. Totally unrelated question. Why will I leave MCP and cover plugin out of the sudden?
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Good. Can I get a smiley faces now, everyone?
Mayank Aggarwal: When you click on Edit Config, it will open the location of your config file on your machine. In Windows, it will be, I think, present somewhere on app data somewhere. On Mac, it is present on Library, Application Support, Cloud, desktop.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool.
Mayank Aggarwal: And this is the cloud config file.
Mayank Aggarwal: Please start fresh new project on MCP, please don't include an existing code. Murthy, again, not sure that this is… we wrote this project yesterday.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? Suggest C line, open code, continue dev, those, maybe we can easily add it up, not a problem.
Mayank Aggarwal: U.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, a ton.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, again, what I have done, everyone, I've just added this screenshot as well, and many of you might have also remember, because I remember showcasing the same to you, if you actually remember, when we did
Mayank Aggarwal: or when we were working on VS Code.
Mayank Aggarwal: In this as well, if you want to add server everyone, it asks you. So, command SDIO, run a local command that implements MCP protocol.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want, in here as well, you can list the servers.
Mayank Aggarwal: And you will see that how we are having different, different MCP servers, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: So…
Mayank Aggarwal: In the same as well, when you… let's say that if I have to add a server here, so what I'm doing is Command-Shift-P,
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP add server.
Mayank Aggarwal: command STDIO, run a local command that implements the MCP server. Let me say UV run MCP rent.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I could actually add this, recipe box underscore fast MCP dot py.
Mayank Aggarwal: And if I press enter, I can say recipe box.
Mayank Aggarwal: updated MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: And let me make it on this workspace. See? It actually kind of tries to create the same kind of a thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: And now what it is doing, everyone, is that it has created a VS Code MCP JSON.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is saying that, hey, there is a server.
Mayank Aggarwal: you can restart the server, and it is throwing error because I guess I have messed this up, so ideally, I should have get the complete
Mayank Aggarwal: copy path. I should have given the complete path here, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pasted the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: And let me restart it.
Mayank Aggarwal: See?
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, so it is still giving an error. It is saying it discovered 3 tools, so it seems like it has worked.
Mayank Aggarwal: But yes, this is how, actually, when your, this thing will start, it is able to get this. Three tools and everything, it is able to get each and everything. So this is how, when you are having any of the VS Code cursor, or all these things, you just tell them that, hey.
Mayank Aggarwal: When you are starting up, Start this command, uv run fast MCP run with this particular case.
Mayank Aggarwal: your MCP server will start locally, and your client can connect to that, so that is what is happening here as well. Same thing Claude does. In the Claude, if you will notice, this is exactly the command or the code which is running.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, opt home review bin UV, I've given the exact UV path. Run, fast MCP, fast MCP run, this complete file exact thing. So that now, when my Cloud will start, it will start off with this complete thing. So, I specifically, in the previous part, showed you that how we add in
Mayank Aggarwal: VS Code as well, so just to revise the steps, Command-Shift-P. You can add server, everyone. Command-STDIO, run local, command and implement MCP protocol.
Mayank Aggarwal: And you can have npm package, pip package, any of that. The whole idea is very simple, that when you will be adding a server.
Mayank Aggarwal: If it starts up locally, that is on STDIO, you just have to give the exact file or anything which has to be ran.
Mayank Aggarwal: And in that ways, we can quickly just add another and different, different servers as well. So, that is how it gets started. Now, if you will run here, warm-up server is also starting uvrun python server.py, and it is getting started here.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope the same is now clear, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope the same is now clear.
Mayank Aggarwal: Server which we will host on GCP will be connected via config or connectors.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ideally, if you have hosted them, you can do it via… directly via connector, so you can just add onto that. If you will see now, there is a button of adding the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, if you go on connectors, there is an add button. So, hosted thing, you can start from here. Locally, which you are running, for the developer's part, you have to start from here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Via?
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope this is good, everyone. Let's move forward.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, everyone, with this thing clear, let's now try to make sure that our server, the one which is actually,
Mayank Aggarwal: this recipe box updated. Now, also make sure that I have deliberately named this recipe box updated, because earlier I was trying it out, and I had this recipe box, so it is already added. So, either I could remove it, I could make sure that I am removing this MCP box, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me remove it like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? So the same is removed.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now I can save the file.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can make sure that I'm extracting the file and dropping it safely.
Mayank Aggarwal: Going back.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now I will make sure that I override the same. I could have done the changes directly in here.
Mayank Aggarwal: But let me just… So, let me do one thing, let me keep both.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, let me say this one is the backup, so that we don't face any issues, by any chance.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, it already exists. One minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: or old, and now I can just remove the copy from here. So, just safe steps to do that. Now, this one will be the file which my Cloud desktop will run, will read.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just to understand everyone, I have removed Recipe Box from here. I have installed just recipe box updated.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now…
Mayank Aggarwal: The reason it was not showing up earlier, because this UV was not right, so now I have made sure that I have done this UV thing as well. When my Cloud desktop will start, it will run the same as well, so easily, we will be able to see the same up.
Mayank Aggarwal: And yeah, let me restart the Claude, everyone. So what I will do, quickly, I will kill Claude.
Mayank Aggarwal: And now I will start Claude again.
Mayank Aggarwal: See? So, Claude is killed, and Claude is started.
Mayank Aggarwal: Plus?
Mayank Aggarwal: Connectors?
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me see Manage Connectors.
Mayank Aggarwal: And let me search if… yeah. So, recipe box updated is there, everyone. It is having the list recipes, get recipe and search recipe.
Mayank Aggarwal: Claude, by default, just work on tools, but of course, it will be able to access your resources and everything. Now, when Claude did start it, everyone, so the moment Claude started.
Mayank Aggarwal: It actually… now, I can go on Developer and show you, there is recipe box updated.
Mayank Aggarwal: Command?
Mayank Aggarwal: This, and we have the logs as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, we have the…
Mayank Aggarwal: complete, complete logs as well. So when I click on View Logs, everyone, something like this got started. See?
Mayank Aggarwal: This is having, I'm gonna zoom it in.
Mayank Aggarwal: So this, actually, in the backend, started my MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope this is clear, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: How about in the backend, Claude started at the same time, because it is a client.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: I will quickly help you to revise it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Little bit… not complex, but let's do it step by step.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, as we can see, like, it has been started in here, everyone. So, to quickly help you revise, let's go back to the whiteboard, because there are lots of steps.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will specifically talk about if we are having a local STDIO server.
Mayank Aggarwal: We make sure that we provide
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me make it in here.
Mayank Aggarwal: And, like this, I'm trying to zoom it in.
Mayank Aggarwal: we provide the config to start the SIP.
Mayank Aggarwal: In… clients, like, and I would just write host slash client here, like… Claude Desktop.
Mayank Aggarwal: Go to SUD.
Mayank Aggarwal: VS Code.
Mayank Aggarwal: We have config, Example.
Mayank Aggarwal: Claude Desktop.
Mayank Aggarwal: Config.
Mayank Aggarwal: dot JSON.
Mayank Aggarwal: or MCP dot… JSON.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where we provide.
Mayank Aggarwal: How to exactly dot…
Mayank Aggarwal: the server. Now, if you will notice, everyone, we was actually also starting the server like this only. So, when my server got started, I ran the same command, which was…
Mayank Aggarwal: If I go on Terminal again from here.
Mayank Aggarwal: When I started my server, everyone, it was also via UV run, fastmcp run, SAP box, fastmcp.py. So I started my server. Claude also did the same. When Claude started, it also started my server, as we saw on the logs, and now Claude can connect with that running server.
Mayank Aggarwal: In that case, yes, every time you start your Cloud, these 5 servers will be getting started up. So, the 5 servers which we see in Cloud, in the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me close this up so that it doesn't confuse us. We have lots of windows. In here, yes, these, all the ones are getting started, everyone. So, read and write, APFI, Kubernetes.
Mayank Aggarwal: demo file system, and SVP box. So, these are all my local servers, which are starting up with these commands. So, Python 3, this exactly is the path for this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Kubernetes, it is a node-based server. APFI, it is also a node-based server, and Read&Write is also a node-based server. So your servers, they can either be created on Node, on Python, via UV, you just have to run the file, that is the whole idea. So you just have to run the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it can be via Docker as well, where they start inside a container. So, in that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where we provide how to exactly start the server.
Mayank Aggarwal: When the host starts, the client… And server gets… Connected.
Mayank Aggarwal: as we make the server run. And this was exactly the reason, everyone, that when the UV path was wrong.
Mayank Aggarwal: I was not able to run my MCP server. And yes, this is actually how, earlier we were facing the issue, and this is the complete, complete steps which I have done right here.
Mayank Aggarwal: So… Make sure that the same That the configuration Has right, path, and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: So this, I guess, is a lot more, practical approach of what all I have quickly shown you. So just to quickly summarize before we close this one.
Mayank Aggarwal: We have two ways in which we can add servers, MCP or in cloud, connectors for hosted and the direct one, configuration file for our own local servers.
Mayank Aggarwal: Connectors is pretty simple, you can see the same in your complete, that as well, which is your,
Mayank Aggarwal: web as well, so if I go on again on Claude Web, everyone, so if I quickly open this Claude web here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cloud.ai. You have the connectors here as well. So, you have these connectors here. But of course, from here, I cannot start my local server, right? So, we will be creating… we will be pushing this server in future to cloud, so that we can even add this server here. But of course, Cloud on the web.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, and this is on light mode, so you don't get confused. Claude on the web cannot connect with my recipe box server.
Mayank Aggarwal: But Claude has a desktop app can, and that is where everyone… I went into the developer. So the reason, everyone, now again, why this is behind Developer. Because, of course, it requires you to change few things up, okay? So it is not available to everyone. It is actually to add and manage MCP servers that we are working on.
Mayank Aggarwal: In the developer side, I showed you that how you can now add and exit, sorry, you can now, work on this
Mayank Aggarwal: Cloud desktop config?
Mayank Aggarwal: where the MCP servers are kind of added. So, we have two one here. I think other it is mentioning or handling itself. So, others are preferences, everyone. And APFI and other it is adding as an extension. But yes, this is how you update the same. You have to make sure that, by whatever command you are running.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can actually also run it via Python 3 as well, not a problem. Just, it should be pointed to the file where my MCP server code is written.
Mayank Aggarwal: I should have all the libraries and everything, so that is the reason Docker way, you can also run it, okay? What do I mean by Docker way? Then it will start up a container, where everything will be present. So, since my machine is having fast MCP, it is having UV.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, with this complete thing, everyone, it is able to start up, and once it starts up the server, then it is able to hit it, and just to…
Mayank Aggarwal: Check the same before we close it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you tell me if… We have excess Or, let me just check…
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you tell me all the recipes?
Mayank Aggarwal: Just… let's just ask this. I think it will be able to hopefully understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: That we have a server for the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: Or else we will specifically point it out, because I guess I have lots and lots of servers connected for the timely, but yeah. So, see, Clare want to use list recipes from recipe box updated. I can allow the same ones. Now it will be doing a tools call, and see, it got the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which is your weeknight pasta, slow roasted chicken, 5-minute salsa. Want the full ingredient for any of these? I can pull them individually.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I go, everyone, back to my, let's say… this server.
Mayank Aggarwal: What exactly was the tools, everyone? Let's see the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: there were, FastipCP1, there were…
Mayank Aggarwal: get recipe, list recipe, and search recipe. So I can search the recipe by tag, let me check.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you search recipes?
Mayank Aggarwal: which I can quickly
Mayank Aggarwal: make. Now, this is where it becomes very, very powerful, everyone. Till now, on the MCP inspector and other places, we were ourselves entering the tags and everything. So, we were actually telling it, but now, because we have the brain, that is your AI, see?
Mayank Aggarwal: It is saying Claude want to use search recipe, and it is having the tag as quick.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me allow the same ones.
Mayank Aggarwal: And see, here are the quick recipes. Veganite pasta, and 5-minute salsa.
Mayank Aggarwal: And that is why, now, you have just created an MCP server, which is directly usable by your, intelligence, which is Claude. If, and yes, we will be doing that, if we make the server available all over the internet, if we host it somewhere on the cloud, then everywhere in this world.
Mayank Aggarwal: just by adding that configuration can use your MCP servers, can use your product with Claude and AI without having any issues. So that is the power of this, everyone. And with that, pretty sure that I hope you understood the two major things which I wanted to explain. That is.
Mayank Aggarwal: global MCP servers, or MCP server, Community.
Mayank Aggarwal: slash connectors.
Mayank Aggarwal: Second, using your own locally hosted MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now… If…
Mayank Aggarwal: You are clear with this, and I pretty hope, because we have actually seen each and everything step by step.
Mayank Aggarwal: you will understand that why. If I go on view and start the chat here, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I go on view and start the chat in here, I can do the same thing because everything is exactly the same. Each and everything in here is exactly, exactly the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can just ask it.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you see it here. So, I've started a new chat session.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can just ask it, do you have excess?
Mayank Aggarwal: 2… recipe, box, updated server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's see the same. I will view terminal.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I will showcase the…
Mayank Aggarwal: outputs, yeah. So, see, everyone, this is where my terminal is running, let me ask it first.
Mayank Aggarwal: Exactly the same thing is happening here. So it is understanding if it is having C.
Mayank Aggarwal: Not directly, but I don't have access to running external server unless it's in your local environment. Okay, I think I will have to start it up, because if I see local…
Mayank Aggarwal: It is having the co-pilot. Let me do a co-pilot.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I see MCP…
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, so let's, see the same in the next part, everyone. We just have to check if… I think we might have to restart the same as VIN.
Mayank Aggarwal: So as to check if we are having this thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can start a new chart here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me open a new chat.
Mayank Aggarwal: Not send this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anyways, let us start it in the next, I think I will have to restart, restart the VS Code so that it does connect with the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because it is having this thing, but yeah, before moving that, the concept will exactly be the same. VS Code has also started the MCP server, as we can see here. And yes, now you can use everything in the same way as well. So each and everything which we want, we can just quickly…
Mayank Aggarwal: Make sure that, exactly in a similar way, we are handling
Mayank Aggarwal: And able to access the tools and everything, because the tools are there for VS Code Intelligence as well. So, yes, with that, now you know that how you can connect to MCP servers which are present all over the internet, via cloud desktop, etc.
Mayank Aggarwal: And how to use your locally hosted MCP server as well. Now, in the next step, next part, let's take it a lot step notch forward, and let's try to work on some real, real-world kind of a project.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where we will be getting MCP servers, have APIs, SQL, and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope this thing is clear, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: We do not have to give the UV path in VS Code every time, or only in desktop config. No, no, Amlan, pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I know that this… might be a little bit, if you have never done it before, see.
Mayank Aggarwal: You see this MCP JSON, which is there in my machine?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, it got created here, see? Studio.
Mayank Aggarwal: In here, I might not have to give the UV path, because it is running inside my this workspace, and in this workspace.
Mayank Aggarwal: it knows what UV is. Like, it normally knows what UV is.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, in the terminal, it has an idea.
Mayank Aggarwal: that…
Mayank Aggarwal: what exactly UV is, so that ways it can find it out. Okay? How to access or use MCP servers from our local client application?
Mayank Aggarwal: I did not get this. We have not created a client ourselves as of now.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? Didn't get this. How is Claude Web, have the recipe box updated, getting updated? Because we have added it only to our Cloud desktop. It is not there in the Cloud Web Hardik.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is Clawed desktop, it is in dark mode.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pay attention, it is Claude desktop only.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, let me have it, maybe this open, so that you can see this. It is Claude Desktop only.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: what exactly are tags in resources? Priya, if you're asking tags in this
Mayank Aggarwal: This is something which we have created as part of our
Mayank Aggarwal: If you're asking this tag, this is just a part of our server, nothing else.
Mayank Aggarwal: I read somewhere that we can connect via connectors only if MCP connectors for that server is created by Claude, not by ourselves. Then that is wrong, Suhani, right? We have done that, just in front of you.
Mayank Aggarwal: How MCP server does decide which tool to call, because we are not using any brain in MCP server side. Nini. So, server doesn't decide.
Mayank Aggarwal: We send… Client sends the request, the tool slash call that how to call and what to call, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope that makes sense. Okay, server doesn't decide. Server 2 is just running, and it says that, hey, tell me what you have to do. I will do that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Sir, can you please show us how we go to localhost? This part is not clear. It didn't show up on any IP to run when we run today. What localhost couple can you clarify?
Mayank Aggarwal: Also, everyone, just one suggestion as well. So, I will show you, like, how I get the potion.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: If possible, for all of you, I'm not sure if you see the same button as well. If possible, ask the follow-up thing here only.
Mayank Aggarwal: So the… when I ask you that, hey, about… And the follow-up question.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ask it by putting this, because else it becomes very difficult that you message something 2 minutes ago, then there are lots of messages, and the message chain is lost, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Sir, can you show me how we go to localhost? This is, again, not clear. How MCP server decided which tool? I think I've answered this. Please share the command to add that MCP in Cloud desktop that I can do. It is there in your code, but otherwise, also, let me do it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Everyone paste it. Which we are checking in browser yesterday. So, that is MCP Inspector. That is a separate tool, which I explained you during the starting as well. So, if you run this.
Mayank Aggarwal: It will start up an inspector in the local host.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, it has started on my 9999, and that is how you can run it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? Can you take the question after the class, just a request? Akshat, so again, I totally agree with you, and even I would want that.
Mayank Aggarwal: But see, what happened is that, for people who have not understood it, if I don't clear out these questions in the 5 minutes, it will be a little bit like they will not be able to relate to it. But yes, what I can do today, which I started, is that…
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me have a 5-minute timer, so that quickly we will have Guest.
Mayank Aggarwal: Questions for this type, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Chetal.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool.
Mayank Aggarwal: Claude Deshmet might replace for ChatGPT, just ask ChatGPT or anything, or otherwise I told you, like, go to any of the config, like, ChatGPT will also have a config, just go there and add these things. The command exact thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope now you're all pretty good with that, like, take a screenshot, add it to that, and all is good. If we have 5 connectors, then how do we define this in config? And if we run all connectors, and all are in the same MCP servers?
Mayank Aggarwal: First.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP server for each connector is separate, like, that is what I have been explaining you. Different client, different MCP server. So…
Mayank Aggarwal: Just like how we have added it here, we will be having it like this. So, client will start up, and we will have this, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: I followed the step, but SP box is not showing in the connector section of Cloud Desktop.
Mayank Aggarwal: It will… show up, study LEO once you have fixed that UV thing as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Have you fixed that UV thing? By doing which UV?
Mayank Aggarwal: So let me write down that command as well, because many of you might not have that. So it will be reaching out to you, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Have you done that? Which UV, and fixed that, StudyL, saved the same and restarted your plot as well?
Mayank Aggarwal: Restarted your Claud event?
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool?
Mayank Aggarwal: How do I make sure that Claude uses MCP for a query, not search? Arun better your tools are decided, or the better you can guide that, hey, use this tool, that is how Claude will do it, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Here, what is host, Client and Server? A host is your cloud, which you are seeing right in front of you.
Mayank Aggarwal: Client will get started as a part of the host only, and server is what is running in here. This is the server which is running.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, the Cloud host starts a client which connects to the server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear, everyone?
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP.json config, you created. You explain it purpose and how you created that. I did not create this, first thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: How many of you use VS Code?
Mayank Aggarwal: I think you will see the VS Code. Just do Command-Shift-P, Click on Add Servers.
Mayank Aggarwal: And once you add the server, everyone, then it will show up and ask you if you have to do it globally or locally, and it file will get created. I did not create this.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is how it gets created normally in VS Code.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, we will not see client, only host and server. Yes, normally, we will not see host here, because it is a part of this, but we will be creating our host in future. Machla, we will use MCP, Fast MCP, and Langchain to create a host specifically in future.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear? If I missed out on any doubt, can you please ask it again, everyone? There were lots of doubts. Also, Mayan, can you ask plot to create MCP JSON initial formatting? Yes, you can very well do that. I can genuinely just go to Cloud and it can create it for me.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me just ask it, Teja, let me start up a new chat.
Mayank Aggarwal: One minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: height.
Mayank Aggarwal: hype.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you provide me MCP.json, which…
Mayank Aggarwal: I can use with the… with, with, with, with cursor.
Mayank Aggarwal: Have the recipe box added here.
Mayank Aggarwal: How do you organize your Mac? I spend every week on Reddit to understand the same, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: If I want to host on MCP server, how can we do it to show this? For the part, that will come in sometime. Can you delete MCP.json and recreate it? What is the purpose of creating MCP.json? MCP.json, which is there, it is just by VS Code to use it.
Mayank Aggarwal: So you can maybe… maybe move away from it if it is confusing, though it should not be. Just like how Claude is having Claude Desktop Config, VS Code is having .MCP just1, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Also, when you ask plot to get MCP.json, Hari hojayka? Quick, everyone, if you, it is saying it doesn't have the recipe box actual connection details, which does make sense, it will not have it.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, if I provide the same everyone like this, pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: See?
Mayank Aggarwal: If I provide it like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: It will be able to run.
Mayank Aggarwal: I get to know that connectors will need more token in Cloud via context management from your cloud course. Yes, yes, that is totally right. Totally, totally right.
Mayank Aggarwal: Hi, man, got to run very fast, we run fast on MCP, this is successful, but now can I add to Claude Desktop? So, Sonu, that is what I told now. Key, go to developer, or just run that command, okay? After that, you will have to fix that UV path thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, go to Developer from here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Settings?
Mayank Aggarwal: Developer?
Mayank Aggarwal: edit config, and fix that UV path. Like, just do which UV and run that. Okay, let me add this C, it has given the same empty one, so you can use this directly.
Mayank Aggarwal: How can we create an authorization, like, only people with the reader role can use the MCP? So, authorization is, again, you can have a key and everything there. So, let me showcase that in the HTTP or future one.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: While running Claude, desktop MCP client comes with desktop app, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Huh.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ideally, what is standard approach of getting MCP server? The way we have created it, that is standard, by using fast MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is a standard thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? Time's up, huh? Mehulp. Salik.
Mayank Aggarwal: extremely sorry, everyone, but just put yourself in other shoes if you are not understanding, and Mayank starts teaching by moving in future. So, you will also be like, Mayank, why are you moving forward without explaining the same, okay? So, just that, I try to be active for everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now everyone, let's move forward, and just before we move on to a little bit advanced use case, I want to show you quickly, if you search for Gmail server, Gmail MCP GitHub.
Mayank Aggarwal: We have seen this server earlier as well, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, if you will notice.
Mayank Aggarwal: We can, I remember, yes. So, if you will notice, everyone, this is actually a NPX-based server, which is a node-based server.
Mayank Aggarwal: which gets started on your local only. So, what happened is that…
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want to start this server, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: what this Gmail client, Gmail MCP server does, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: It's that…
Mayank Aggarwal: it starts up that server on your local, so once you add it into the cloud desktop config, it will again start this server up, and then it will hit from your local… the Gmail APIs or Gmail
Mayank Aggarwal: MCPs and everything. That way, it is just that you are owning up to that. So, a takeaway here, it is not that all the servers of third-party application will be HTTP. Many people have that mistake.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is not the case. If you will notice here, this is a Gmail MCP server, everyone, where you can add it via Node, which is NPX. Now, for people who are not aware about Node or anything, just copy this and ask ChatGPT or Cloud to explain.
Mayank Aggarwal: It can be added via Docker as well, so Docker run, MCP Gmail server, Gmail credentials, and everything. So you give the credentials.json file here, and it will start up a Docker container, so that nothing actually leaves out of that. But it will be on your local. And see, cloud authentication, it is given the complete thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: Similarly, if you search Tavilly MCP GitHub.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because, again, MCP server can be created by anyone. I could have an MCP server created where I'm having Gmail, Tamilion, everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Tableau MCP server, everyone, if we see, pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is the remote MCP server, which we can directly use, so that is the HTTP-based one, everyone. HTTPS-based MCP one.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, if you want, you can have local one as well, so let me quickly check.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is all the remote one.
Mayank Aggarwal: Again, it is showing all the steps, everyone, that how you can have it in PX, MCP remote, HTTP1,
Mayank Aggarwal: And this is exactly what you will add in your VS Code as well. Similarly, if you want to do it locally, so on the HTTP hosted one, every request will go to Table EMCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want to do it locally, everyone, pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: You… Aditya saying that you need to have these things?
Mayank Aggarwal: NPX hyphen Y table MCP latest, but these are the configuration. So this is via node now in a similar manner. NPX via node it will install. Hyphen Y means yes to everything once it gets installed. Tabili, so it will get installed on your local.
Mayank Aggarwal: Similarly, this is NPX.
Mayank Aggarwal: And yeah, I think I can just easily now show you
Mayank Aggarwal: Python 3, I guess there will be some way.
Mayank Aggarwal: this tabbly Python SDK… But again, in a similar fashion, everyone, we have the servers which we can
Mayank Aggarwal: use with Python, 3 pip…
Mayank Aggarwal: Because at the end of the day, we just need the file, which we have to run the code on. Docker, just like I showed you in that. NPX, Node, because we are just starting up the server, and server can be started in any ways, so MCP servers can be getting started like that, and then it gets integrated into your machine. So that is how these things happen.
Mayank Aggarwal: And yes, now you are easily good to just run your server in any of these host slash client, which is VS Code, Cursor, Cloud Desktop. You might just have to change their configuration so as to add them.
Mayank Aggarwal: Otherwise, most of them now supported via connectors very, very easily, because I think it makes a lot of sense to not unnecessarily make people confused with that. But since we have been covering this in so much depth, I want to make sure that you do understand what exactly happens when you are developing your local MCP servers in depth.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, with that, now let's, in the next part, make sure that we move on to the project for sure, and then we will understand that, okay, how we can work on MCP servers and hosting it and everything with a real kind of an application.
Mayank Aggarwal: Why do we want to add remote server to connect via local server?
Mayank Aggarwal: Because then it will run on our machine, and overall.
Mayank Aggarwal: it will be… we will be able to use it directly, right? So, and many of them are having just a local server only, not the remote one.
Mayank Aggarwal: But how Tableau or Gmail will work locally, not able to connect dots. Okay, pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: I have created this server here, Vivint.
Mayank Aggarwal: Recipe box, fast MCP?
Mayank Aggarwal: Can I have a tool here which calls Gmail, and a tool here which calls Tably?
Mayank Aggarwal: Can I have a tool here which calls Gmail API internally? And a tool here which calls Tablei?
Mayank Aggarwal: So I can have search internet, which calls tabily. I can have send email, which calls Gmail.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, can't I run this on my local?
Mayank Aggarwal: I can run this still on my local, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: And they will just connect and hit the HTTP. That is what I was explaining yesterday as well. Okay, don't think local server is just for local. No, no, no, that is wrong. That is where, when you will develop, you will face issues in interview, etc.
Mayank Aggarwal: And otherwise as well. If it is running locally, that doesn't mean it cannot reach out. So Tavilly people are saying that, hey, you take our code, it will start up an MCP server, it will give you the exact tools, you call them up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Whatever minimum load is there, it will be on your machine, and you hit it up, and you get happy.
Mayank Aggarwal: Like, your thing is getting done. Or else, we have the hosted server, just hit that hosted server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Kia?
Mayank Aggarwal: Thanks.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can we hang back for break, for food, please? How can we send email if you're running the code in some Linux server? Well, like, we can now.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just search Chaudh. Can MCP tool call other remote MCP tool? Yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: How is two local approach useful, Mayank? I told you that how STDIO is faster, it is secure, it is overall, very stable as well. So, all those things.
Mayank Aggarwal: Is there any vanilla way? This is the most vanilla way. Nothing after that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool. So, let's have a break, as someone suggested. But let's come back here, Madhlab. Quickly, let's start with the project. This, I thought, will take 20 minutes, but should be fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just… let's own that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, so let us start, everyone, just give me a minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just give me a minute, everyone, okay? So, closing, lots of things…
Mayank Aggarwal: At this point, my machine is genuinely running.
Mayank Aggarwal: on.
Mayank Aggarwal: Not so bad.
Mayank Aggarwal: Who's this?
Mayank Aggarwal: I wish.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can close this as well, not a problem.
Mayank Aggarwal: Presentation.
Mayank Aggarwal: Hardik, okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just 2 minutes, everyone, okay? I'm just pushing in some code.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just facing some issue with this, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: bottom.
Mayank Aggarwal: my MCP had to… exist.
Mayank Aggarwal: Here we go.
Mayank Aggarwal: Konya.
Mayank Aggarwal: When we do RM, it isn't moved.
Mayank Aggarwal: To you.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, time tracker project, everything is there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nope.
Mayank Aggarwal: Everyone, I've pushed the changes into GitHub. Can you check ones, please?
Mayank Aggarwal: I've pushed the changes into GitHub.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I have also made sure that I have pushed up the code files as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: My own 953.
Mayank Aggarwal: have completed MCP, and I will correct the same as well. For the timing, let's try to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is pre-coded, yeah. Time Track Project. This is where you will find lots of things.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: Tell me quickly if you're able to get the theme out, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, it should be showing time tracker. Can you please get quickly do the git, pull, or download the same, so that you also have the access to it?
Mayank Aggarwal: And I've shared my, Cloud Desktop config, I hope that…
Mayank Aggarwal: Like, yeah, I hope that you were not able to hack into my… any machine or something with that, but yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: Got the Rites code. There's no tracking information for the current branch. Please specify which branch you want to get merged for. Oh, there is just one branch, although there is main only, I don't guess we have any other branch.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just… Do this like Class 2026, and you have everything here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Rather, I would highly suggest that you just git push… just do a git pull if you have, get out, if you have ever caught it out, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Sorry, I have stopped this feature.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope each and every one of you is able to see the code and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Each and every one of you is able to see the code.
Mayank Aggarwal: Right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay. So, thankfully, we will be able to do everything from the code now. I will be keeping on pushing it from the…
Mayank Aggarwal: Same base, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let's do it.
Mayank Aggarwal: what are risks involved in MCP? If you are not creating… again, if you are adding any MCP server without checking it, your data can get lost.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is very much similar to how, when you connect to any third-party API server or any third-party application, more or less the risks are same.
Mayank Aggarwal: plus, for simple operations, the cost can be a lot less, so let's discuss around the simple, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: File… which file not found it is showing
Mayank Aggarwal: Instead of having a skill and context surrounding for the project, can we make MCP and multiple tools with same project function and use it in real time? You can, but skills and prompts are different, so we will have to understand the same, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: which project you need to pull. There is a time tag project, this you should be able to see, once you pull it up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Showing page not found. How?
Mayank Aggarwal: Everyone, are you able to access this? People are able to get it, like, can you please check?
Mayank Aggarwal: just…
Mayank Aggarwal: People are able to get it. Why are you not able to pull up even? Can you check? I think all the errors are solved, so I will tell you why the errors were also coming. Many of the files, naming, I think, maybe I… like, it got renamed or something.
Mayank Aggarwal: It was in the… format which Windows does not support, so I'll be able to get that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm not able to get the warm-up project folder.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me check, why is there not warm-up?
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP warm-up.
Mayank Aggarwal: One minute, let me quickly check.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anyways, I will be fixing it, but it should be fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, let's focus on that, everyone. So it is giving me some errors. Nothing added to the commit stage and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will fix it. Should not be a problem, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Hello. Let's begin. Let's focus on this one, actually, time track project. I will fix this up. It is having some issues, maybe with how it is a separate project or something, but we'll fix it up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yep.
Mayank Aggarwal: Viking Vasudevira.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, one minute. Channel.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you provide the UdayMe coupon code? Mehdiqto, like, just give me some time. Teaching page other focus rather to make the project for you, but I will try. Yesterday, I was not able to create it. After that, I did not get the time, so let me do it, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: All the courses also have been updated as well, so let's start with this every one.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great.
Mayank Aggarwal: So… Let's make it ZoomMate.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP… Project.
Mayank Aggarwal: time tracker, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Let us start every month.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, everyone, let us continue our discussion and try to understand few more things in the MCP space, specifically by using a project-assisted learning, where we will be having a project, and we will make sure to understand that how effectively
Mayank Aggarwal: a different concept with respect to making an MCP server on…
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's say cloud, and other things can easily be done.
Mayank Aggarwal: And for the same, what I have done, everyone, I have provided us with this time track project.
Mayank Aggarwal: Inside the same, we are having a notebook, and all the files, along with a README as well, so that we can actually understand each and everything properly. So, real timesheet tool, log billable hours through a browser, or through an AI assistant.
Mayank Aggarwal: And see the exact same data.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, it is having a complete index.html, which is nothing but, if you think about this, your front end for the code, so actually.
Mayank Aggarwal: To see the same, I will just quickly drag it up, everyone, and showcase the same by opening it up.
Mayank Aggarwal: So…
Mayank Aggarwal: If you will see, this is, like, a very basic kind of a project. We can make it a lot more better. In here, you can give the employee name, you can give the project it is working on, the date, how many hours, billable hours you want, and the description. And it will easily be able to load it up, okay? So, this is exactly how the project works.
Mayank Aggarwal: What I will do is, I will use a lot of overall claud and everything to make sure that
Mayank Aggarwal: As we move forward, we are able to make
Mayank Aggarwal: Clawed and everything a little bit.
Mayank Aggarwal: Case to, make our project a little bit much more better.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let's quickly talk about the setup, everyone. What… one more thing which I will do is I will just open the project separately, so that on the left side, we don't see so many things.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, everyone, we just have the project open, and we can have the
Mayank Aggarwal: Claude code on one side as well. If we face any issues with the things which are normally not related to MCP or otherwise, like enhancing the UI and everything, we can just directly use Claude there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Next part, everyone, is that how we are having this notebook IPv. So, it is loading like this. Let me quickly fix it up. So, let me ask a lot for these things. And one more thing to note, everyone, this is how I want all of you to also do the coding in future.
Mayank Aggarwal: Of course, learn what is the issues and everything, but at the same time, do make sure that you are not wasting time on these simple, simple things, like the reason this is not opening up.
Mayank Aggarwal: I know that I will have to download an extension, which is nothing but Jupyter Notebook.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, so this Jupyter, I might have to enable it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me disable it, and then enable it again.
Mayank Aggarwal: Jupyter, I think, should be done. VS Code Jupyter Notebook is a different one. Let's get the official one only, the Jupyter.
Mayank Aggarwal: And just let me search for notebook as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, one more thing here, like, in my case, I am having multiple things which are messed up. I'm using VS Code, internal release.
Mayank Aggarwal: So…
Mayank Aggarwal: Just because it is having some extra limits, etc, but should be fine. Let me try to open it up now.
Mayank Aggarwal: To see if it opens up.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I will have to fix it. Should be fine. So, for the timing, let's…
Mayank Aggarwal: Quickly start it up, and let me show you what all exactly is present here.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you will notice, everyone, there is data.database.py. Now, what this does, okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: It will be making sure that
Mayank Aggarwal: I have created a time track application. In that application, everyone, we or employees can track their time. And for the same, we are using DB, okay? Now, if you have ever actually
Mayank Aggarwal: Done any part, any code with
Mayank Aggarwal: SQL in Python, you would be aware about these things, so I'm getting the connection, everyone. I'm going to create a…
Mayank Aggarwal: Time TrackDB here, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: There is initialized DB, where I will be creating these tables if they are not present. Then, similarly, there we can execute the commands. Okay, we will be adding and filling it up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then, row to dictionary, we will be kind of having the rows cater to a dictionary, listing all the entries.
Mayank Aggarwal: Logging the time, get timesheet, List project.
Mayank Aggarwal: KAP project summary. So, for the timing, I will be using a local DB, but easily, when we will be pushing it to the cloud, easily we can make sure that we are having
Mayank Aggarwal: The DB which is also hosted on cloud, so easily we can find SQL DBs, etc. there as well. Then we have the main.py every month, so in here, if you will notice, so I have the code kind of written, though I will be writing it right in front of us again.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just that, I have given this code initially for all of you, so that you understand
Mayank Aggarwal: properly that what exactly is happening there, like, how exactly we are working on this part. Though, I will make it main, separate, I will define everything right in front of us, so that we are able to understand this step by step.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, yes, for people who are aware, maybe you can skip the part.
Mayank Aggarwal: majorly where we are doing this particular thing, etc. Because otherwise, it's a very simple kind of a code, we are following the MCPs and all these things up, and we are kind of…
Mayank Aggarwal: just using directly the functions which are created. So, if you will see, major heavy lifting is being handled in my database.
Mayank Aggarwal: What I will do, one thing, everyone, is…
Mayank Aggarwal: Or maybe we are fine with the longer code files. You can, if you want, you can just copy these and move it into a separate folder, but I guess that would not be an issue at all, like, we are just using a normal kind of a case, where we are running some SQL commands and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: We have the index.html, which is nothing but the code to load up the front end, which I showcase in here, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? Similarly, we have the style CSS to style this a little bit, and we have the app.js.
Mayank Aggarwal: This tries to make sure that it can hit the DB and everything, because, again, it's difficult to write code which runs directly in the HTML, so it is just going to make sure
Mayank Aggarwal: that it is able to get those elements and just run the command, etc, wherever required. So that is the whole approach of this kind of a project, everyone. Though, as I mentioned, we will be starting the same from scratch.
Mayank Aggarwal: And understanding that, okay, how it kind of happens.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, all in all, this is what the project is, where it's a real kind of a project. Now, normally.
Mayank Aggarwal: You will see that, and we also take that path, where we, of course, in the starting point, understood it by easy examples, like the recipe box, or just by having a very simple add or subtract kind of functions.
Mayank Aggarwal: But yes, I guess moving forward, let's try to make sure that via this project, we are able to understand each and everything, so that in the next part, we will be able to understand key… when we are having a project which is very much close to the real world.
Mayank Aggarwal: how exactly MCP and everything gets integrated there, because we now have understood the lifecycle and architecture, this is where it will become much more practical overall.
Mayank Aggarwal: Everyone, before I move forward, I hope the code and everything is clear.
Mayank Aggarwal: Honestly, I will just ask you to put it all in ChatGPT or Cloud, and you can ask it as well, but I hope you can understand
Mayank Aggarwal: key… how it is pretty straightforward and everything, right? The code and all.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me just quickly fix this up before we move forward.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, what I will do is, I will go to ChatGPT, ChatGPT, paste it.
Mayank Aggarwal: VS Code Insider.
Mayank Aggarwal: Unable to load.
Mayank Aggarwal: Jupiter…
Mayank Aggarwal: Notebook, yeah? Do you two back… YouTube have backend code and MCP code in main.py? Yes, we have both of them.
Mayank Aggarwal: Python and Jupyter, okay, let me go to extension.
Mayank Aggarwal: Jupyter is already installed.
Mayank Aggarwal: Python is already installed.
Mayank Aggarwal: Extension installed in Aggwar are not necessarily rebuilt.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, then right-click open with Jupyter Notebook. If that works, choose Default.
Mayank Aggarwal: the chance. Yeah, that makes sense.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just a bit of a woman, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, I have the PERM kernel as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Fair enough.
Mayank Aggarwal: VS Code Insider normally gives some issues, so should be fine, like…
Mayank Aggarwal: In here, I should have…
Mayank Aggarwal: Simple that we were wise when we were there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Next, I can open it with that as well, but let me try to fix it up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me restart it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, APY content is installed, like…
Mayank Aggarwal: Cluster signaling one, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: All is installed.
Mayank Aggarwal: Skinny… Unable.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pasato, let me help you save the time.
Mayank Aggarwal: Not pasted. Let's go to Jupyter.
Mayank Aggarwal: It does.
Mayank Aggarwal: Try in your browser.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Well, you can open it anywhere, like Gs Collab or anything, but I'm just opening it in here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Go to the tabs. Okay. Channel.
Mayank Aggarwal: Peddwas Cloud and Vasudev will fix. I know, but I don't want to just move in default. I will fix it afterwards. As I mentioned, like, I keep on working on many things, so…
Mayank Aggarwal: It can get messed up in that manner.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pool. Sure enough.
Mayank Aggarwal: I mean, why don't we get Claude T1 Enterprise Plan, and see if anyone else is interested in joining us, sharing the cost? So, no, I think it will be very complex, though honestly, I'm fine with purchasing my own, so that's the case, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me get it here.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now we have a browser here, and we have this here, and we have this here. Cool. So, let's start everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, everyone, let us continue our discussion. Along with the code, we have this timetrack, kind of complete.
Mayank Aggarwal: notebook as well, which help you to explain what exactly is helping and everything. So it kind of explain you, like, the code is written and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: And how it is a little bit more towards the testing side, if you will notice. So, if you are having any issues in understanding, maybe you can just quickly go through the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because many people might have a little bit, problem in understanding it directly if you have not coded a lot, but otherwise, the code is also pretty simple.
Mayank Aggarwal: But that said, yes, please spend the time in understanding the code rather than taking it directly, because that would be helpful in the long run. Now, first, let us, everyone, quickly set up the project. So what I will do is I will open the terminal in here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Inside the terminal, I will run the commands, okay? So the commands, actually, I kind of have given to all of you already.
Mayank Aggarwal: First thing I will do is, I will do UV init, and this thing is required, everyone, because…
Mayank Aggarwal: We will be making sure, and I think it should be inside time track, so I will go inside CD Time Track, clear everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: UV init dot.
Mayank Aggarwal: See? Now, I have initialized the project in here, everyone. I have the Toml file.
Mayank Aggarwal: I have main.py, which anyways I have created, Python version.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I have now initiated a UV, or a virtual environment, or overall a UV project in here.
Mayank Aggarwal: And of course, the benefit is that now UV can do all my handling of packaging and everything, so this is the main file. Plus, when we will be making sure that we make this live on a server.
Mayank Aggarwal: online HTTP-based server. Of course, this is something which will be required. Now, everyone, what I will do, I will quickly just do UV add.
Mayank Aggarwal: Fast MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: Fast API.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, these two are not connected, but they are very compatible with each other. What do I mean by not connected? They are not from the same company, but FastAPI is connected with
Mayank Aggarwal: fast MCP in a manner that very easily you can… if you're having a fast API where all the APIs are present, you can very easily just create a MCP server from that. Like, just generally, that is 4 line of code.
Mayank Aggarwal: And vice versa as well. Fast MCP we have already been seeing, that has been created on top of the MCP official library, and now the same has actually also converged, where the code is very, very similar. So this fast MCP, everyone, if you go on Anthropic.
Mayank Aggarwal: anthropic MCP SDK.
Mayank Aggarwal: And let me just search for Python SDK, because that is what we will understand. Pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: The code and everything will be very, very similar. So, rather than FastMCP, add the Red MCP tool, because they have converged at this point as well, but just to make sure that you understand it, we are using Fast MCP here, okay? Nothing like a problem, it's just something which we are using.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will also install UVicon, because I have a front-end server, so standard.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it is needed as part of your… One minute, let me just… Minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: You'll be gone with this.
Mayank Aggarwal: And see, we have installed all the libraries, everyone. This is easily, easily added here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now I could just easily do UV run fast.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP version, so that I see the version of Fast MCP. This is majorly to check that, yes, inside my folder, I have this thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: The benefit of UV, rather than PIP?
Mayank Aggarwal: easily, it is able to check by a Toml that what exactly is installed and everything. PIP, you have to…
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh…
Mayank Aggarwal: just enable the environment, and then kind of work on the same. So now, everyone, if you will notice, this thing is totally kind of written in front of us.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now let's go to database.py, copy the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: And what I will do is, I will quickly open ChatGPT here.
Mayank Aggarwal: And this is what you have to also do.
Mayank Aggarwal: Paste all the code.
Mayank Aggarwal: Explain the code to me in a very easy, Amanda.
Mayank Aggarwal: Predded in?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, see, think of this as data manager for a time tracking app. Its job is to store things like who worked on which project, on what date, how many hours, what they worked on. And I think our front-end was very, very supportive of this complete thing only.
Mayank Aggarwal: Imports at database location, so I'm importing the same and having a location.
Mayank Aggarwal: DB path?
Mayank Aggarwal: And this is exactly how you have to understand the code for a project. The reason I'm doing this, so that you are connected to the code, rather than just following me blindly. Get connection, the function simply opens a database connection.
Mayank Aggarwal: con.rowfactory SQLiteRow makes database rows easier to access. Without it, a row may look like this. With SQLite3row, you can do row employee name. So see how nicely ChatGPT is explaining the same to you.
Mayank Aggarwal: In MdDb, the function initializes the database, it first connects
Mayank Aggarwal: And then it makes sure that everything is happening here.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, restarting your application won't delete or recreate the table. So, create table if not exists. So, this is the important part in here, everyone. Else, every time the table will get created.
Mayank Aggarwal: This table looks conceptually like this, so this is exactly what we have to focus, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, it is having an ID.
Mayank Aggarwal: An employee name, a project, entry date, hours, and the description on what the person worked upon. And if you think about this.
Mayank Aggarwal: There are many different applications which are even multi-million as well. I remember one of them because I follow its founder.
Mayank Aggarwal: Jaybel is a free time tracking software, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which is, of course, the… Much more advanced version of the same, used by many companies, and…
Mayank Aggarwal: I think every application is having time tracking now, time tracking softwares, if you will notice. So, Clickify… Clockify, I think, yes, is also pretty good.
Mayank Aggarwal: Of course, we are not making at this level, but at the end of the day, we are kind of starting with the same on the very basic one.
Mayank Aggarwal: every time NT gets a unique number automatically, ID integer, primary key, auto-increment. So, although I've written the code.
Mayank Aggarwal: But you have to understand this, that… why it is like this. See data. Code check whether database is empty.
Mayank Aggarwal: How many time entities currently exist? If there are zero, count is equals to zero.
Mayank Aggarwal: It adds up sample data.
Mayank Aggarwal: you already have some test records, then execute many insert all those rows together. So seeding data means that we are just warming up our DB so that it is not empty overall.
Mayank Aggarwal: And then row2Dictionary helper function, SQLite gives you a database row. This function converts it into a normal Python dictionary, so that it can be worked upon inside my function.
Mayank Aggarwal: For example, SQLite wrote this becomes a dictionary.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anyone has any doubt till now?
Mayank Aggarwal: Acha, I really hope that you don't want me to write it light by light.
Mayank Aggarwal: Hello.
Mayank Aggarwal: I really hope. Can you put those website URL in notes? Which way? Website URL?
Mayank Aggarwal: Samitri, that is just a time-tracking software, Madhlam, just do a normal search.
Mayank Aggarwal: For all demands result, we do RohoDictionary. If you have to work on that, that's pretty helpful. So, Samitri, that Jibel, you can just search and save somewhere. Although I don't want to have, I just remember that website, so it should be fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: Is it similar to Jira?
Mayank Aggarwal: Nay. Jira's different.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear, let's move forward, everyone. I think this should be… till now, this should be pretty easy to work on.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great.
Mayank Aggarwal: And, in a similar fashion, everyone, now we have list all entries, which returns every time entry, every entry into the DB.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is giving the example as well. Log time, probably one of the most important functions, define lock time. It adds a new entry to the DB agreement, which would create something like this. Then, of course.
Mayank Aggarwal: We would have the complete way of having to get the timesheet.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm not going inside this, as you have seen, if you just paste it to ChatGPT and ask it, it can explain you the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, in that case, now I think we should be pretty good anyways by understanding the code with the help of ChatGPT.
Mayank Aggarwal: today's world, I would not expect that you are afraid of doing so. Like, genuinely, I would want to do… make sure that you do the same, because many developers in their starting journey
Mayank Aggarwal: They feel that, hey, why am I using internet to work on? Well, that is a wrong understanding, and that feels good for AI as well. Earlier, I also used to be remembering all the codes and everything. Worst approach.
Mayank Aggarwal: just use AI and everything which is present. So, again, in a similar fashion now, everyone, we have all the list project, we have get project summary.
Mayank Aggarwal: website redesign, so… It will be… I'll be taking up a project and grouping it by the employees.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that we can get the summary. So this is the overflow. This is what I actually wanted to get from the same. TypetrackDB, get connections, log time, getTimesheet, Rates Project, and get project summary.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, what you can do, everyone, once we have selected this up, let me clear everything up.
Mayank Aggarwal: now I can do UV run.
Mayank Aggarwal: So we already have the files and everything, okay? UV, run, UV cold.
Mayank Aggarwal: mean… Reno, so that if it's already loaded.
Mayank Aggarwal: It started on 8000. You will see that how the time track DB has been created. You will see that how Yewog has been also created.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me copy this up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Go to my browser.
Mayank Aggarwal: And see?
Mayank Aggarwal: it is actually running up with a complete thing. I can see all the entries.
Mayank Aggarwal: Project summary. Okay, let me just do one thing. Let me say Mayank.
Mayank Aggarwal: Project MCP Mastery.
Mayank Aggarwal: We can have a date here.
Mayank Aggarwal: then ours, let's say, I have spent generally 50 plus hours, so let me say 55.
Mayank Aggarwal: description.
Mayank Aggarwal: Making sure MCP is not something.
Mayank Aggarwal: my student… on my… learners… Will face issue with.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now the same has been logged, everyone, what we can do. If you will see here, see?
Mayank Aggarwal: get, okay, it is saying 404 not found. Have I made any mistake here?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let us do one quick thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: getHTTP1 okay, amp.js. So, seems like the app.js is not fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, I think app.js in the static app.js.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me, in here, use Claude quickly to fix it up. So, this is Claude.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me copy this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me paste it up.
Mayank Aggarwal: But interviews still asked to write the code without AI's help.
Mayank Aggarwal: I don't think that is the case, that you will have to write each and every line normally without AI's help in today's world.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Very sorry to say, but that's what everyone can do, but that AI can play its part. But how and in what manner should we approach the project that thinking or logic and experience you should give to us? Kapil, I totally agree with you.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, again, I think this, when you're learning Agentic AI with me.
Mayank Aggarwal: I am genuinely explaining these things. Believe me.
Mayank Aggarwal: Malam, I would take a stand here that I believe that you should be aware of these things.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is a very basic kind of a code. If I try to explain that, there will be no difference between the one, and generally, I'm still putting in the effort to explain it. If you want that, okay, what is this app.js, what is this index.html?
Mayank Aggarwal: That, honestly, I would expect that you are just running through ChatGPT and understanding for this course specifically.
Mayank Aggarwal: So I hope that makes sense, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Are we gonna do all projects with pre-generated code from AI? Everyone, again, if you think that this is pre-generated code from AI, I'm extremely sorry, this is not the case.
Mayank Aggarwal: malab, then I think you have not done coding. So, Kapil and Deepanshu, how many experience you have?
Mayank Aggarwal: If you feel that I should be explaining this thing, even though I'm explaining not in depth, I will be really honest here. It is not required.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can generally just assume that you know this, and that's the assumption. This is not a pre-generated AI code. I will not be writing this code ever in this class, I'm being brutally honest here, because you will also not be writing it today. You will just ask AI,
Mayank Aggarwal: And you can just copy, paste, and understand it with AI.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: It would be great if you create the file from scratch, rather than dumping from your GitHub.
Mayank Aggarwal: Why would I create these files from scratch? That is what I'm saying.
Mayank Aggarwal: Everyone, there is a… again, this is Agentic 3.0, where our expectation is we want to learn Agentic coding.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? Well, I'm extremely sorry, I normally don't do that, but I would expect that you should know these things up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Generally, this is a very, very basic thing, which you should be aware. It is genuinely not the case. I'm extremely, extremely sorry.
Mayank Aggarwal: But…
Mayank Aggarwal: If you are saying that, Mayank, if you are giving me the… this is a pre-written code, this is not.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is not a pre-written code, I'm extremely, extremely sorry.
Mayank Aggarwal: And if any one of you are facing the issue, please connect with me.
Mayank Aggarwal: spend extra hours, but in the future project as well, I will be giving you the front-end code altogether.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Again, if you are from a different domain, or if you are, let's say, product manager, if you are fresher.
Mayank Aggarwal: Please spend the time, Matlap. Even when I used to teach this before AI, I used to give the code as it is, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool. So let's move forward with this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, if you're saying that, Mayank, no, no, no, create the file and tell me, no, I will say that, hey, please take the screenshot, and ask ChatGPT that what it is, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool. Men just want to know, are we allowed to use AI tools like ChatGPT development project? Yes, it is totally allowed.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Well, if you are saying, Kimah, you create every file altogether in front of me, rather than… it is not AI-generated code, I'm explaining everything right in front of you.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you are saying ki acha yea, this also I have to explain, so extremely sorry. Please spend extra time. That is what I can say. Okay? Shalom.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, I think it has been fixed up, everyone. Let me see if it has been fixed up or not.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me refresh it. Yeah, okay, much better, my bad. So, that was what was setting it up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great. So, now everyone, what I have done, I have fixed this same up, and I was actually hoping that, I was actually also wondering that, why it was the case, so I will update the code.
Mayank Aggarwal: But in this case, if you will notice what we have done, if you refresh, now it is a lot more better. And I was also wondering that why it is having something like that, so we can have the log summary. And now, because the same has been fixed up.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is a lot better in that case. Actually, the app.js file, that was not overall good. It was having some issues. Not able to connect with my DB, and because of that, index.html was also getting
Mayank Aggarwal: some issues. So this was actually the kind of a thing which I kind of got created. So you can see all the entries. Now, if I go on lock time, I can just say, Mayank.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can say project is MCP Mastery.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ours, I can say 55.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's just say… I can have… and description.
Mayank Aggarwal: Lock type, so see?
Mayank Aggarwal: now my time is also locked. So yeah, totally now it makes a lot of sense. And I was wondering that maybe it is because of my VS Code Insider something, but yes. The same has now been kind of very much overall better, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Next code.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool.
Mayank Aggarwal: We can understand it's not an issue, but we have to go through the code again after spending 3-4 hours of class. I feel at least Agent TK-related code we can write in class. Agent-related code, we will be writing in class. I think you have learned Langchain with me, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, did I write any code on Langchain, everyone? Didn't I write each and everything right in front of you?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, extremely sorry, but my Poda Saha you will have to put in the effort, else this will become the data science python, everything. Although that said, to be very honest.
Mayank Aggarwal: I have a 10-hour video of Python, which I will be uploading, and I am recording some Python videos, which I will be talking like that, okay? Yes, why is he telling like this? So, I'm not sure, Deephut again. As a mentor, I have to make sure that everyone is aware of the same, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Chalo, let's move forward with that, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anyone with any Houston law?
Mayank Aggarwal: Kabul, don't worry, I will explain everything. Anyone has any issues till now in what the project does and everything? Is the project part clear? Project part.
Mayank Aggarwal: project part.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope all of you are able to get this UI and everything easily.
Mayank Aggarwal: Each and every one of you are able to get the UI part and everything properly? Yes or no?
Mayank Aggarwal: Do we really need an MCP server for this project? Yes, you will get to know at a time. Don't you feel that if you are having an MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where you can get all these things directly, it will be much better.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where you don't have to log this yourself every time.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just make it, like.
Mayank Aggarwal: Working for a thousand employees, and think that… don't you think that people can make lots of mistakes here?
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope that makes sense.
Mayank Aggarwal: shallow. Let's try to understand the same everyone now.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, everyone, with this thing clear, and in this part, in the last part, we were able to see that how effectively we are having this complete thing working a lot better now.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, what I will want to do is, I will create a file here, so let me name that file
Mayank Aggarwal: mean… to… understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: Not pY.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, pay attention. Here, I will love to first explain you that what exactly and how the things are getting connected, okay? So, first, we will create Form Fast API everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: we will import, your fast API, okay? So I will be actually using Fast API to first create our, complete server, then static files.
Mayank Aggarwal: For people who are, again, not aware, FastAPI is a library which helps you to create API servers. So, we had Flask.
Mayank Aggarwal: Before that, I think we have other… the same for… that same as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, yes, now FastAPI is something which is used a lot. Again, not directly related to FastMCP, but it is compatible with it. In this, if you will notice, everyone, very, very easily you can just create, so you just add the FastAPI, it will get downloaded. So they are also using UVAD.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Just restart it, and… once easily like this, and I feel that this is very, very similar, like.
Mayank Aggarwal: how we have the MCP?
Mayank Aggarwal: And that is the reason many people do get confused between fast API and Fast MCP. But yeah, the whole idea is that this makes our whole thing a lot clearer and easy to use. With that, let's try to focus on the same, and again, I can restart to get this error solved, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because we do know that in our TOML,
Mayank Aggarwal: these APIs and everything are installed, okay? So, quickly, what I will do, everyone, pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: First, I will import database as DB, so this database is nothing but your file, this database file agreement, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: And I'm importing this at DB. Now, there's init db, which I will call, so pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: tb.netb.
Mayank Aggarwal: And… In this initdb event, basically, I am making sure that when I run this file.
Mayank Aggarwal: I am initializing my DB, so I can just write it down here.
Mayank Aggarwal: initialize the database, and seed it with initial data if empty.
Mayank Aggarwal: To understand the same, you can go initial ITP, it gets the connections, creates a table.
Mayank Aggarwal: Fill it with some entry points, which we have seen, actually, if you will notice. So, initially, we are having these entry points every month.
Mayank Aggarwal: And then execute and kind of just closes the connection. So, basically, it is just warming up my DB, nothing else, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, everyone, what I can do is, before we jump onto MCP or anything, let me create app.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it can be fast API application.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can give it a title, so let me see if this works.
Mayank Aggarwal: Title, time track, description, a simple time tracking app with REST and MCP endpoints. Version 1.0.0. I think, yeah, that is all good, everyone, so let me just have it wrapped up. So, this time, I'm having an application created.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, once I have the application created, everyone, what I will do? First, I will create a GET point. So, get…
Mayank Aggarwal: And I will make sure that this is slash API slash entries.
Mayank Aggarwal: And, once I've done that appointment, they've filed API?
Mayank Aggarwal: list… all entries.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I am just listing all the entries.
Mayank Aggarwal: DB list all entries, and if you will notice in here, everyone, in this code.
Mayank Aggarwal: See, there is list all entries, it connects to my DB, and get all the things, and gives the same to me.
Mayank Aggarwal: And actually, without moving forward, first, let's try to make sure that we can run the same. So, what I will do, everyone…
Mayank Aggarwal: is that… let's go back to FastAPI again.
Mayank Aggarwal: past API.
Mayank Aggarwal: And let's see the code.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that you are able to connect that how it happens.
Mayank Aggarwal: app, I've created the app, Fast API, and now I can just run. UVrent FastAPI dev.
Mayank Aggarwal: There should be a command to run it with your,
Mayank Aggarwal: browser with the exact file as well. So what I will do…
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me open Claude in here.
Mayank Aggarwal: How can I run this?
Mayank Aggarwal: with UVCon and FastAPI.
Mayank Aggarwal: By specifying the file name and the code.
Mayank Aggarwal: B9998. So, because I know that 8000 is normally used for it, and 8000 is kind of already
Mayank Aggarwal: used, so… let's see if it will be giving it to me. Okay, I think it has ran the same only.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Your app instance is this?
Mayank Aggarwal: mean to understand, okay, UBO, this one was the command, I guess.
Mayank Aggarwal: UV call made to understand both this.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me try to first check if… Something is running local host.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it was 9998, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: If it was this one…
Mayank Aggarwal: Because I want to show you that Swagger page as well, so everything will be a lot more clear. Yeah, so I think I will have to start it up. Let me close this.
Mayank Aggarwal: And…
Mayank Aggarwal: I can just copy. And one more thing, everyone, I would never want that you also remember the syntax. Even though I have written and created, generally at this point, thousand plus
Mayank Aggarwal: fast API servers, still I don't want to remember the syntax.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, so what I will do, I will copy it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Again, go to ChatGPT.
Mayank Aggarwal: Paste it.
Mayank Aggarwal: And ask the queries. So maybe we can use ChatGPT, because even I find it better. And the reason I'm showing you all this thing, generally, is so that when you get lost, you know how to actually get your way out. So these things, I am not moving out, I have not written the code or anything.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that we actually are able to understand that how
Mayank Aggarwal: you can also use the same. So, I think we are using UV, that makes sense. UVCon directly will not work, so let me copy this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Paste it.
Mayank Aggarwal: No such file or directory.
Mayank Aggarwal: UV run UVCOND.
Mayank Aggarwal: Copy the error. The file sits outside the timecracker folder. Oh, okay, makes sense.
Mayank Aggarwal: Toying my bread, my bread.
Mayank Aggarwal: So it is saying no such file or directory, because we mistakenly created the file outside the folder. So, let me move it here, everyone, so that makes a lot of sense. And that also makes one thing very clear.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which, as you can see, even I'm making the mistake, you are not reading the errors, I'm just directly copy-pasting to Chal GPT. Something which normally I do try not to ever do, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now it will hopefully work, because inside this, we have everything. So, I will explain to you, everyone, what was the problem. Our UV is installed inside this with every library, every
Mayank Aggarwal: requirement, fast MCP and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Outside, the same is not present, so it will never work, okay? So, yes, now we can go on this link every month.
Mayank Aggarwal: And… We have details not found because we generally have not created a simple thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: But the second we add docs in front of it, a very nice Swagger page gets opened up. So this is a Swagger API page.
Mayank Aggarwal: I am not sure that…
Mayank Aggarwal: if… like, I know that why it is called Swagger, because I got exposed to it via Swagger IO for Java, so you can read about it, but I guess this is from where it gets pushed up, because in Goldman Sachs, we used to work and see this Swagger a lot, and now I can try it out.
Mayank Aggarwal: execute.
Mayank Aggarwal: And see, I'm getting all the entries.
Mayank Aggarwal: So in this manner, what I did, everyone, now I will explain. Let me close lots of things in here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me close… one minute, let me close this one. Let me close this. Pay attention. I've just created a very, very simple, fast API server, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: In this FastAPI server, everyone, I have made sure that I just have one entry.
Mayank Aggarwal: I initialize my DB, I create my Fast API server, and then I'm running the Fast API server via the command
Mayank Aggarwal: So, easily, via my command, I'm able to run my FastAPI server, which is this command.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me just quickly try to get this command, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: And…
Mayank Aggarwal: just via this command, I'm able to run my server. I had a one-point API list, all entries. Actually, if I say here, print.
Mayank Aggarwal: API list call it, please return, Hi, how are you?
Mayank Aggarwal: Genuinely, again, it will restart itself, that's a good thing. If I execute it again, everyone pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: it will be high, how are you instead. So just, I'm getting the data and showcase the same, nothing else.
Mayank Aggarwal: And where you are able to see this, everyone, once you run this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then, since I am running it on port 9998, It will be visible on…
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me get the URL for all of you as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: One minute. So… If we go above, yes, just copy this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Paste it here, slash docs.
Mayank Aggarwal: open Swagger page.
Mayank Aggarwal: Port should be.
Mayank Aggarwal: Right. Okay, so this is the host, everyone, and this is the port. So your port should be right. I am starting with port 9998.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because my… normally, they start with 8000 as default, but in my case, 8000 is, I guess, already used, because my application is already running, right? So it will give an error. So that's why I'm just making sure that I am fixing it like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: And if you now focus everyone, just like in this manner, I can define all the other APIs as well. So, very, very similarly.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can just now easily define other APIs, and now it will make a lot of sense, so pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me close this terminal as well, pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: I am having API entries, let me remove this. Let me fix this as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: See?
Mayank Aggarwal: API entries, API projects.
Mayank Aggarwal: API projects project summary. So, for a particular project, this can be… this will be something which will be sent in future to the get project summary as an argument, and API timesheet.
Mayank Aggarwal: Plus.
Mayank Aggarwal: Also, what we are doing, everyone, is that we are making a new entry as well. So, if you want to make a new entry.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is where, actually, we can add a post-call. So, what I will do is, yes, let me…
Mayank Aggarwal: Just make sure that this is post-call.
Mayank Aggarwal: And… Si.
Mayank Aggarwal: all the above things, everyone, I was just getting the same. So let me just, for the time make.
Mayank Aggarwal: command this thing. Now, I have added 4 get points. 1, 2, 3, 4.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, my data, everyone, is easily able to just get with these four entry points. If I go back and refresh the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: See, there are four KPIs.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, to add the data, ideally, I should be using the post call, not the get call. And in here, I can just easily get all the projects as well, everyone see?
Mayank Aggarwal: Write out. Execute.
Mayank Aggarwal: These are all the projects.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP Mastery Website Redesign. And if I want, I could get the summary as well, if I just give… now, see, this get call it expects that I will be getting a value.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, what I will do, I will exactly copy this MCP mastery.
Mayank Aggarwal: And paste this in.
Mayank Aggarwal: And see, I'm able to get the… Complete history, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: 4…
Mayank Aggarwal: putting the data, I will use the post call, rather, and the post kind of a thing. So, for that, everyone, this is the…
Mayank Aggarwal: exact code. It expects a new entry, so I will make a new class.
Mayank Aggarwal: new entry.
Mayank Aggarwal: And… Ideally, what I will do in this, everyone, is that…
Mayank Aggarwal: I will just have employee name, project, entry model, odds, and description.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because these are all the things which I have in here as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: When I log time, employee name, project, date, hours, and description.
Mayank Aggarwal: they will flow down to lock time, and you will notice that how I'm sending the exact entries one by one.
Mayank Aggarwal: And inside this, it will be making a call to the DB, inserting these values, and that is where, again, how your complete MCP server
Mayank Aggarwal: gets overall done, okay? So, we have… Sorry, not MCP server, API server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because this is actually, or majorly, how we will be creating these things up, and how we will be on top of this building tomorrow our own MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Although this was something which, we should have kind of known.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which is kind of understood in a way that, yes, this is how a fast MCP server gets created, but still, I just tried to showcase the step to show that how the base of our application has been set. Because still now in here, MCP is not used. For powering this, this is how we are powering it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Every button, this project summary, this drop-down.
Mayank Aggarwal: It gets filled up by hitting the call in the backend. Log time, it will be hitting the post call.
Mayank Aggarwal: And that is how exactly it happens, everyone. I can showcase this as well quickly, so that there is no doubts or anything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Network, let me clear the… all the calls. Pay attention. Mayan?
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP Mastery?
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me have, let's say 12 hours.
Mayank Aggarwal: Description… Same. When I do lock time, Pay attention.
Mayank Aggarwal: what it did.
Mayank Aggarwal: It actually hit 3 calls.
Mayank Aggarwal: Entries?
Mayank Aggarwal: It is a post-call, everyone, so employee name, request payload.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is complete headers. Now, again, this is how APA normally works. I'm just making sure that you understand it.
Mayank Aggarwal: It then gets all the things back, because, of course, it has to show the updated data, so it got all the things back.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it also makes sure that project is updating as well, so it got all the projects back. Because it might happen that when I'm adding a new entry, I can add a new project. So that's why, when you will go in here, everyone, you will see MCP project as it is. So this is how the whole application is working and connecting and everything is happening.
Mayank Aggarwal: the APIs, the DB, and the front end. Coming to the front end, a simple HTML code to have all the
Mayank Aggarwal: Headers and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: style.css to style my complete application.
Mayank Aggarwal: And app.js kind of handles all of this API call and everything, so document, query selector, and all these things is being handled by my app.json. App.js, sorry. So now let's, in the next part, try to understand that how we will be creating an MCP server or MCP on top of it by using FastMCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: Huh.
Mayank Aggarwal: Going too fast. Rashmi, this was not required, I just did that because many people were asking everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: I… okay, how many of you have no idea what I told, or what all this has done?
Mayank Aggarwal: Well, believe me, this was required, everyone, I'm… I, like, please don't hate me, I'm just being really honest. You know that I'm very patient and everything, just, I'm making it, but don't be like Mayank…
Mayank Aggarwal: You are going fast. Nay, I'm not going fast, this was not required.
Mayank Aggarwal: Generally, I will say this again, this was not required.
Mayank Aggarwal: This was kind of a prerequisite.
Mayank Aggarwal: Bala, this is actually something which you should know.
Mayank Aggarwal: And there are two ways you can take it in life now. You can say that, hey, mentor is not explaining from scratch, he's using AI code, that's the first way you can give me a bad rating. Totally don't… I care about that, honestly, not that I don't care, because I take my teaching very seriously. Second is, you can understand that, okay, if Mayank is saying that this is kind of a prerequisite, and if I don't know this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Maybe I need to work on myself.
Mayank Aggarwal: First one will not get you anywhere, I can assure you that. Second one will generally be something which I will expect from a mature learner.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, if Mayank is saying that, okay, this is required, and why is Mayank going so fast? Well, every code has been given to you. Jat GPT is there, it is an easy code.
Mayank Aggarwal: And still, my MGPD is also there, so yeah. Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool. Can you show a network call again? Yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: But why in the first place we need MCP now? Because a couple… see…
Mayank Aggarwal: The problem is that with AI, we are lazy. If I give you that, hey, KAPIL, you have to now enter this thing up for 10 days. Won't you want that, Mayank? Can't you give me in Slack, yeah, I can just enter that, hey, log in my entry?
Mayank Aggarwal: Rather, or would you like to come here? Think about this.
Mayank Aggarwal: A very, very basic question I have done, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: A very, very basic question I have done.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ki…
Mayank Aggarwal: We would want that AI can help us in that. Like, why do we need AI to send email for us? We can send it ourself as well, right? Why do you want AI to connect with your calendar or anything?
Mayank Aggarwal: We can do that, but… Just, we are using
Mayank Aggarwal: We want that AI… yeah, we are lazy, basically. That's the right answer.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I think that if I'm getting this application, and now if I want people to use my application.
Mayank Aggarwal: One person, you are coming up and saying that, hey, no, no, no, you don't know… you don't need MCP, you can just directly use it like this. I have created a very good UI, it's simple to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: I come up and say that, hey, I've created an MCP, no matter if your team is using Slack, VS Code, Cloud Desktop, even if they remember the same at night.
Mayank Aggarwal: Or otherwise as well, whenever they are working, it will automatically log in their hours. So if the team is working, because I have an MCP, whenever they are working on Cloud desktop, sorry, Cloud Code, they will be able to use the same in the… it will log it itself.
Mayank Aggarwal: surely people will use mine. No one will want to log it itself, log it themselves there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Understood the use case, everyone?
Mayank Aggarwal: Understood the use case.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, Pio, did we design that FastAPIGAT page? Will it be used anywhere in the project? We have not designed it. FastAPI did that for us. We get this with FastAPI to test out our APIs.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, otherwise then I will have to use the curl command or something to get that, right? So FastAPI says that, hey, you are getting your server, let me show you a better manner. Just like MCP inspector, that is FastAPI Inspector, you can call that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear everyone, let's move forward.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let us move forward.
Mayank Aggarwal: Huh, Swagger talks… I've not created anything. But this can't be a real use case of MCP. This is a real use case of MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is generally a real use case for MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear?
Mayank Aggarwal: Explain all API which call which you are making from Swagger.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm not making any API call from Swagger, like, Swagger is just for testing that everything works. So my Swagger is here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, in this, I have all these things. I might have to refresh it so that I see the post as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Is it still running on Amit?
Mayank Aggarwal: HTTP not found, you know, this error.
Mayank Aggarwal: base model is not defined. Have we not defined? A shah. My bad.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where is base model, everyone?
Mayank Aggarwal: Identic?
Mayank Aggarwal: And, yeah, see.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now it is pretty much done.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I refresh it… See? Posting there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, again, it's on me. How can I call this, right? I can call it via this, I can call it via curl, I can call it via internet, I can call it via AI, totally on me. So, Rashmi, to answer your question, just try it out. When you run the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can just check that, okay, you can try it out and run the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: Asad just one question.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, give the answer, and then we will move forward. If I log… if I create an entry from here, everyone, will I see it on my UI?
Mayank Aggarwal: If I make an entry here, will I see it on my UI?
Mayank Aggarwal: If… I will repeat it. If I am making an entry from here, will I see it on UI?
Mayank Aggarwal: For people who are saying no, take my word for it, please revise today. Take care? Let's move forward. I genuinely don't want to spend more time on this. Let's move forward, everyone. So…
Mayank Aggarwal: DB is same, lah, everything will be invisible.
Mayank Aggarwal: You put different port to run app.js made to understand, but the DB is same.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm using the same DMI.
Mayank Aggarwal: DB, database connections, everything is same. It will be visible.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? So, just take this all code, put it to ChatGPT on Mayank GPT, and explain the same. Difference between UVCon and UVC couple, revise the things, ask it in ChatGPT. UVCon and UV are not related, okay? Again, UVCon and UV. Benefits of FastAPI here?
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh.
Mayank Aggarwal: Whenever you will be creating an MCP, it will be on top of an existing application most of the times. So, this is an existing application which I've created.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I just use FastAPI there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear, everyone?
Mayank Aggarwal: UVON is there in the Fast API server, but there are lots of things are there, but yes, so let's move forward, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, everyone, let's move forward, and with the last part, I think it should be very, very much clear that how exactly
Mayank Aggarwal: the… system is already in place. Now, the reason I showed you by creating this is because
Mayank Aggarwal: We will, or we never create an MCP server out of the blue. We normally always try to create an MCP server which is based on an already existing application.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, to think about the same, you can just think it like this, that when I am using Claude.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me go to Claude in here, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: And inside this, if I show you, let's say, the… Calendar server. Google Calendar.
Mayank Aggarwal: All these tools, everyone, are nothing but they are APIs or actions which you can already do, right? So there was already an existing Google Calendar system, like the one which we are having, so we have just done the groundwork here of creating our own system.
Mayank Aggarwal: In a similar manner, if you go on Google Calendar APIs.
Mayank Aggarwal: you will be able to see that how it is having the same kind of an APIs and everything, so resource type and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just that, on top of it, the MCP server was created.
Mayank Aggarwal: In a very similar manner, everyone, we have created the complete system of our time track, so let me close few things up in here, yeah. This is the complete system of our time track, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: And yes, that is where we are now able to… on top of it is where we are able to work upon. So, just to help you quickly revise before we jump on to MCP, everyone, we have tried to make sure
Mayank Aggarwal: First is that there is a complete checklist, which we have followed.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you would have noticed. Now, I'm not connecting it to… once I create the MCP server, everyone, like, it is already created. I will not be connecting it to Cloud Desktop, that we have already discussed in the last part, so you can connect and check the same, so as to make sure that how it happens.
Mayank Aggarwal: We have already seen in the UI that how it moves from
Mayank Aggarwal: rows to a real summary, so we can actually have it grouped by employees, we can ask the question as well, once we will be creating our MCP. Rather, I would want that you actually go and, because the whole code is given to you, you first make sure that you are able to connect it to Cloud desktop overall. That would be very, very helpful.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, everyone, in a similar manner, what we did was, before we move forward, we created the MCP here, so 3 tabs, OneDest API.
Mayank Aggarwal: Get API entries, get API summary, POST API entries.
Mayank Aggarwal: And this, I believe, is a very, very good page diagram to understand. Log time was having some values.
Mayank Aggarwal: Other, we were able to just easily get all entries and everything, right? So, in a similar fashion, now is where everyone… as of now, there was no MCP awareness in this file. This is what we have done. This is actually kind of a groundwork for an already existing application.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, the whole idea becomes that how… now we are having an application.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now let's try to understand, do we want to…
Mayank Aggarwal: create an MCP and Y. And a very good argument which I can give and share of this, everyone, is that how, if we both are creating
Mayank Aggarwal: this application.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I create MCP for this, and I give my clients the overall feature that, hey.
Mayank Aggarwal: you can come and log everything just by mentioning it in Slack, VS Code, or Cloud Code, or rather, I have an MCP which automatically logs when your team is working on a project. So let's say if Mayank is working on a project and using Cloud Code, which is the default tool in your company.
Mayank Aggarwal: This MCP can automatically log the same. So, this improves the requirement of the project 100 times, because even without realizing, the same is getting done, and companies can even integrate it without
Mayank Aggarwal: like, not… I'm not sure if it is ethical or not, but companies can do that without even employees knowing. So, in that case, now let's move forward, everyone, and try to understand how MCP will be added in this, in the next part. Because now we have understood the why part of the scene, that why MCP might be helpful. Until now, what we have done, it is just a complete
Mayank Aggarwal: Set up for this particular kind of a problem.
Mayank Aggarwal: Good.
Mayank Aggarwal: Quick question, Mayank, so Claude can also update the time track without the MCP server. In this use case. Why we need MCP server? Why will Claude… how will Claude make… update the time track without that?
Mayank Aggarwal: How will Claude do that without that? Could you show how to log entry from Slack? We will have to make a server like for that.
Mayank Aggarwal: It can use inbuilt tools, exactly right. But then, let's say, as an example, tomorrow I change something.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, I went here.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I changed something in my code.
Mayank Aggarwal: Will… Claude will try to make a call and it will fail?
Mayank Aggarwal: Again, everyone, see, I can… I think I've explained it multiple times, he… if tomorrow I make some changes here, Claude is having the script and everything which it runs.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, again, it will fail because I changed something in the backend, Claude will try to still fix it up, so multiple problems will happen. MCP solves that all up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Again, Vishwanath's iPhone, why do they need MCP? Consumers Python directly call services via REST services? What if I do a complete overhaul of the system?
Mayank Aggarwal: Then, client will have to also do the overall of their REST API servers.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I have 1 lakh clients, 1,000, let's say, companies, do you think that I… it's good that I ask them that, hey, do the changes, because I have done the same and everything?
Mayank Aggarwal: Make sense?
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, we are going back to why MCP exists. No, no, no. We are understanding key on an exact system why
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP might be needed. Teja?
Mayank Aggarwal: Why we need APIs? Else, how will you connect with the DB if you don't have APIs?
Mayank Aggarwal: No, Claude can load the new changes, and then, again, keep on working like this. Every week, I'm creating a new change. Claude will work on like that. That increases the failure. So, correct me again, you are not wrong. It's just about the ease of usage.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? But do we need APIs for MCP to work? Ideally…
Mayank Aggarwal: No, but normally, as I mentioned.
Mayank Aggarwal: API is something which came up first, and every application is having APIs.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can have a… system which is having APIs? Sorry.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can have a system where MCP is not there, but APIs will surely be there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Balako API toya is, they're required.
Mayank Aggarwal: Don't you think we are wasting toker in this use case, simple use UI to logouts? No.
Mayank Aggarwal: Why we are wasting tokens.
Mayank Aggarwal: Well, I mean, it depends now, again, like, 2K's not a… not a problem, like, I'm fine with… if it increases… if it eases out my work, I'm fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: We are wasting so many tokens in that 80s trend as well, right? So, but I think this is a general use case. I could have made it more…
Mayank Aggarwal: complex, but I think this is still very complex for everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool, everyone, let's move forward, understand the MCP as an event.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let us move forward and understand the MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: So many questions, it's distracting. Niranjan, again, I will reiterate the point. Tomorrow, when you will have a question, and I don't answer it, you will not be able to follow up. So, as a mentor, I have to take care of everyone. Extremely sorry, but I have a timer running on my second screen, 5-7 minutes only I'm taking for questions. And you will notice that while I'm teaching now, I'm not taking any question, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, the dot should get connected. If I, as a mentor, miss out on anything in between, learner dot gets disconnected, and he's not able to follow up.
Mayank Aggarwal: If he doesn't, is convinced CMCP is needed?
Mayank Aggarwal: How will he follow that Venkat MCP? Totasa, let's try to fix it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Extremely sorry again for people who know this, I also know this, but yes. On that note, all the code has been pushed, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: So you can push… pull it from the GitHub.
Mayank Aggarwal: How people need to revise, I've covered everything but Teja.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, everyone, let us move forward and try to create an MCP server on top of this. Now.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ideally, I will be creating it from scratch only, but
Mayank Aggarwal: with MCP API and MCP… Sorry, Fast API and Fast MCP, it is generally very simple. If you just do a simple Google search, for example.
Mayank Aggarwal: Fast API to Fast MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: There is genuinely a one single function, see?
Mayank Aggarwal: So…
Mayank Aggarwal: Generate an MCP server from your fast API? Yeah. Generally, this is this easy, and again, that is how these two applications, sorry, two libraries gets connected, where
Mayank Aggarwal: Although they are not from the same parent company, you can see their documentation as well, that how different they are in terms of how they look. This is from PreFETHU.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, yeah, this is how easily you can create the same, and separate as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: So vice versa is also possible. But for our understanding, I will try to create it from scratch, so now let's see, everyone, what we will have to do. From fast…
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP, I will import Fast MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then, again, ideally, I will have to make sure that in MCPs, we have the tools and the prompts and everything, everyone. So, what I will do is, I will first make sure
Mayank Aggarwal: that I'm creating some tools. So, let me first create MCP equals to time track. So I'm creating an MCP server, something which we have done with Recipe Box as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: At the rate mcp.tool, And… Now I can say def log underscore time, employee name, Pro entry date, So…
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me fix it up till the time I know.
Mayank Aggarwal: And descriptions, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ideally, this is right, because if you think about this.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm getting the employee name, project, Entry date, hours and description.
Mayank Aggarwal: And everyone, I hope no one is saying that, Mayank, why you are not writing it line by line?
Mayank Aggarwal: again, please be very much focused, and this is something which I believe is not required, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: I feel that many people will today say in the feedback, you need to write in every code. Nay itana, you will have to understand ki, we can write it up ourself, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, employee name, project, entry date, hours, description, and we are just calling the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ideally, the benefit is that we can actually have multiple APIs as well here. Now, I am just showing you the vanilla way, which is, I am not using this API to call it, right? I could have generally just called this API directly, but I'm just showing you in a vanilla way, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: And yes, in a similar manner, everyone, I can do MCP.tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: And rather than doing this, maybe what we can do first… let me close this up.
Mayank Aggarwal: And in a very similar manner, let me copy this, go to ChatGPT.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, it is here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Not this one, I guess.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I could just ask, now, how can I start MCP Inspector… on 9997.
Mayank Aggarwal: 4 above.
Mayank Aggarwal: It's in same file.
Mayank Aggarwal: You could have returned the code in a separate file as well, that I think should be not a problem.
Mayank Aggarwal: If name, main, MCP run is there, then start inspector like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: So your two commands can be like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: One important point, MCP should have parenthesis and fast MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: Both MP and FastMCP can live in the same file that I know.
Mayank Aggarwal: I missed out on the parenthesis?
Mayank Aggarwal: Should be fine. What I will do is, I will just quickly write, if… Made?
Mayank Aggarwal: Name?
Mayank Aggarwal: equals…
Mayank Aggarwal: I don't want to run UVCon, actually.
Mayank Aggarwal: I want to run, yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP.tes.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that my server starts.
Mayank Aggarwal: In here, actually, as well, if you will notice everywhere in the main file, which I gave you in the starting, it is mounting it slash MCP as MCP app, okay, and static for the normal one.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP monitors creating and everything, but let's try to keep it simple for the timing. Let me open the server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Our… that is already running.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, we already have the same running, everyone. I can just quickly add the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: command.
Mayank Aggarwal: NPX hyphen my inspector.
Mayank Aggarwal: See?
Mayank Aggarwal: I think the file was not present, okay, I was able to get it, should be fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me close this up, actually. One thing which I would love to have it here…
Mayank Aggarwal: go inside CD Time Track, And then run the command.
Mayank Aggarwal: No matches found. Okay, I copied the different things.
Mayank Aggarwal: port 9997 in town.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, if I show you everyone now, all the dots should get connected. This is an MCP inspector which we have.
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, let me have light mode. Let's connect this.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is connected.
Mayank Aggarwal: Again, it is following the complete architecture which we have understood in so much depth, and I will highly, highly suggest that you should be having this thing now.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me just quickly check MCP tool, this is something which we missed up on, so let me…
Mayank Aggarwal: Quickly close up and… Refresh it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's go to tool, actually. See? There is a tool app, even, which we can easily just fill up, and we can edit it as JSON as well, or like a field. And this is what my, AI will fill it, fill up, and see.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is able to get the client-to-server call for the initialization. Then it tells that, hey, we have initialized.
Mayank Aggarwal: After that, everyone, it is able to see that… how it is just asking for the resources, but there are no resources.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then it is asking for the tools, and there actually is a tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: And when the tool information actually is shared, it is shared properly, the description.
Mayank Aggarwal: And all the input schemas and everything. And what are the required ones as well. And this is how your AI also knows that what it has to send, okay? And along with that, everyone, then it asks for the prompts. Of course, we are not having any prompts as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: And a source templates list, so any template in the resource, if it is there.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now in a similar manner, I think it is very, very easy to understand that how we can
Mayank Aggarwal: Easily now just have
Mayank Aggarwal: all the other tools as well, as well as the prompt as well, everyone. So, just, I will copy the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: In here.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me quickly help you revise this.
Mayank Aggarwal: We wrote the name for log time, now it is getTimesheet, get project summary, list project.
Mayank Aggarwal: And known projects.
Mayank Aggarwal: Of course, if we want, we can combine two or three operations in a single one. We have the prompt as well, generate weekly report, because this is something which AI can use. See? How it is telling properly how we have to generate a weekly report, something which is not easily possible by
Mayank Aggarwal: my, APIs only, okay? So, if I just quickly go and disconnect, And connect it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Go to Tools, we have all the tools. Prompts, we have a prompt.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, it is asking that he give me the employee name, let's say Mayank.
Mayank Aggarwal: And we start, let's say… Now, ideally, we should have a little bit more clarity.
Mayank Aggarwal: That what is this week's start. And you can see that how your prompt can also ask for the
Mayank Aggarwal: arguments, everyone. Because prompts can also be dynamic. It is not that prompts should always be the same, okay? So ideally, I should have explained weak start here, so if I had a description like this, it will be kind of taken away. But let me say that weak start is, something around
Mayank Aggarwal: 20, 09… 2026.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I can get the prompt, see?
Mayank Aggarwal: how nicely it has given this. Of course, now when my AI will run this prompt, all the different, different tools which will be used as a part of this.
Mayank Aggarwal: will be able to give me the complete information, and I will be able to make a much better report. Then my AI figuring out that, okay, this is all the tools and everything which I have to hit.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, with that, we have created an MCP server as well, everyone. And actually, this was all the code which was present in your main.py, but I just made sure that, okay, still we are understanding the same via main to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that you can understand that how it runs right in front of us. So that is the whole case in which now the things get connected, and I have shown you the complete thing as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: And yeah, I think this is how all the learnings which we have done kind of gets connected, because we have created a real project, or a product.
Mayank Aggarwal: On top of that, we already have APIs, which is the case with every
Mayank Aggarwal: real application which we see. Google Calendar already had its API, Gmail already had its API, Slack already had its API.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just on top of that, now I've created a very good MCP server, so that it can be integrated in your application. Now, what I would want all of you is that
Mayank Aggarwal: You should now try to make sure that we are able to use it in your
Mayank Aggarwal: plot desktop, because we have already seen this with the recipe box, and otherwise as well, we know the command UV run fast MCP install plot desktop, then this particular thing, so that you can use it directly and run the same. So in that case, now with this done, everyone, let's, in the next part, try to understand that how
Mayank Aggarwal: Effectively, we can make sure that we have understood the persistence, we have seen the website, how the server works.
Mayank Aggarwal: How exactly we can now make sure to have this particular MCP server hosted on the internet.
Mayank Aggarwal: via the fast MCP cloud. So, if you will notice, let me close this up.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I say UV run, fast, MCP run, Made to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: Made to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: See, it is saying server, time track 4.0.3 is the version, deploy for free on calls andprefect.io. So, ideally, if I could now push it to my, overall server.
Mayank Aggarwal: then it will be very easy for anyone to just access it and work on it, any AI tool for that matter. But yes, in a local sense, it is working, which can be shared by anyone in the company or a department.
Mayank Aggarwal: And hopefully you will be easily able to work it with Cloud Desktop, and then you will get the notice of the… how powerful the scene is.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, in the next part, everyone, now let's move and do the same on the…
Mayank Aggarwal: horizontal Prefect. So this is again what MCP is suggesting.
Mayank Aggarwal: we can use PyPy and other ways as well, but I think the one which FastMCP is suggesting, which is nothing but FastMCP Cloud, is pretty…
Mayank Aggarwal: easier only, so let's try to understand it, and it gets the job done perfectly, and we can easily just connect with our MCP servers. And the best part, it is, I guess, free with… you can have 200 plus… around 200 MCP servers you can have, which I believe is anyways a lot.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, if I got it correct this way, vanilla, we are redefining the parameters and their use, but if we used to take, example, fast MP3, then we don't need to do it and define at the rate MCP high, it will be done like that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great each in mind, loved it. One question, how to add governance and authentication security layer on MCP creation? Similar manner how we have it on top of APIs. Fast MPI also supports the same, so that when you are connecting it, you can actually see each and everything. Clear?
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's move forward, everyone, if all is clear.
Mayank Aggarwal: Priyabra, partially okay. So, Priyabra, I hope you do understand that MCP is also a server, just like our API. So, all the things regarding authentication, MCP also gives us the choices. If you want to have an OAuth authentication.
Mayank Aggarwal: It can… it supports JWT tokens, it supports other ways of authentication as well. Plus, for every call, you can check if that particular person is having the requirement or having the access to the same. Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Tk, I will add the code. But if I showed you, I remember I showed you that in the very first class, so it will be present somewhere in this. In the initial one, it will be present, but TK.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which autocompiler do you use? The normal one in VS Code, this one?
Mayank Aggarwal: With whatever it is, co-pilot free.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm not having any other thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: What code difference is from its main py, right, which you added? I explained you the main.py via main to understand nothing else.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Existing Fast TPS server can be export or use NSP tool, rakesh, for that.
Mayank Aggarwal: you just have to use this command. So, this one which I've showed you, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want to use an existing Fast API server, just use it.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it will be tightly created.
Mayank Aggarwal: Explain line 124 onwards.
Mayank Aggarwal: serve index, I'm just getting the file as for static index HTML, so I can serve it.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is a… normal…
Mayank Aggarwal: on… if you don't give it any path, on a normal path, it is just having this thing. Slash APIs, I can expect this. So when I will run this particular thing, Rashmi.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, let me see how it is running.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, it is running on…
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me see for all of you where the main code is running, everyone. Let me show you the UI.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, my main code is running here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Right? Everyone, am I adding any path in top of it? Am I adding any path on top of it? In front?
Mayank Aggarwal: See, if I do APIs, I can call any APIs as well from here.
Mayank Aggarwal: But if I don't add anything, then I am saying that, hey, if nothing is added.
Mayank Aggarwal: app get, then serve the index. So whatever is the response of this static index.html, staticindex.html, serve this here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Otherwise, I have the API routes created so that they can be used, and they can actually be called via the app.js.
Mayank Aggarwal: And MCP, though, I think is just on top of that, so not a problem. MCP is kind of pretty straightforward. So, my app.js, in this same 8001,
Mayank Aggarwal: without anything, I'm serving the index.html.
Mayank Aggarwal: With the slash API, I'm serving the API endpoints. Like, actually, that is what happens for most of the terms as well, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Have you used Cloud Desktop in this process? If… where? How? I have not used it. I'm asking you to use it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? How do we do caching for storing the static content? Normal caching practices, nothing difficult.
Mayank Aggarwal: When you create Fast MCP upon FastAPI, you don't need to define the tools, etc. Every API just creates a tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: As an AI engineer, should we also need to focus on developing front-end code? Not according to me, like, right now.
Mayank Aggarwal: Any Yual use case of prompt for MCP, I explained that when I was explaining you the prompt key. If you ask it for a weekly summary, that prompt can now help you a much better job, rather than Claude or any other figuring it out.
Mayank Aggarwal: How does Dynamic SQL query work? You just ask your AI to
Mayank Aggarwal: Write the dynamic query on the go, so that you can hit it up.
Mayank Aggarwal: So I can have a endpoint which is…
Mayank Aggarwal: queries QueryDB, and that QueryDB will try to hit the server and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Suhani had answered the question. Yes, all the APIs will be acting as a tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: Mayank, if MCP directly calls the DB to access the data, any reason why we have created the API in this project? As I've explained multiple times, normally we don't do that. Plus, normally, for any project, we create APIs first. It is never MCP first. Gmail APIs were already present.
Mayank Aggarwal: We have all the right authentication and everything kind of done in Gmail APIs.
Mayank Aggarwal: On top of that, it is very easy to create MCP and call the APIs, rather than redoing the work. This is a… again, with a caution, I'm not feeling that this is a simple project, but this is a simple project where I've done the same. But otherwise, it's very easy if I call APIs via my MCPs.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because all the… effort which I have put in defining and mastering my APIs can't be reused in that.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, to answer your question, normally for every software, we have APIs already created, and always created. It will never be the case that APIs are not there. But.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCPs are not always there, so yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: From where project information comes? Which project information?
Mayank Aggarwal: I want this time tracker accessed by other employees of same organization. How it can be done. It will be a development task. Just develop it in a way that you add a login and everything as well, and it will be done.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear?
Mayank Aggarwal: When calling MCP does API get used in our code? No.
Mayank Aggarwal: In our code, we are not using it.
Mayank Aggarwal: How MCP server authenticate client request, make sure request is from genuine Client. We have authentication in MCPs, authentication in MCP as well, no, I've shown this. Please advise everyone MCP authentication.
Mayank Aggarwal: fast MCP, whether it supports all the way authentication happens.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, in AhaP, you will see authentication challenges, token validations, fast MCP as a token verifier, JWT token, which I was saying, remote auth provider, if you want to log into somewhere. OAuth Proxy, OAuth Provider, multi-auth. So, just how you do the same with
Mayank Aggarwal: Past any API, you do it in here as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: App.mount MCP malika is to mount my slash… on the slash MCP, I am mounting my MCP server, so that I can connect it with anything in future.
Mayank Aggarwal: Why have you used vanilla code? You should have used Fast MCP and FastAP instead. Suhani, in which class are you?
Mayank Aggarwal: Everyone, what I've used here, have I used FastAPI and FastMCP?
Mayank Aggarwal: Have I used FastAP and Fast MCP?
Mayank Aggarwal: I have to explain to you as well, Navin I've… properly, I've used it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Suhani, please revise.
Mayank Aggarwal: Vallu… Vanilla code, it is using the same only.
Mayank Aggarwal: Vanilla code, I mean that I'm not using the direct way, I'm just creating it in a… right in front of you, and rather than calling the APIs here, I'm just doing the same part again.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then why are you creating tools?
Mayank Aggarwal: Hagin?
Mayank Aggarwal: Circle back.
Mayank Aggarwal: How will I use this if I don't have any tools?
Mayank Aggarwal: If I am not creating directly.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will have to use and define the tools, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Chalo, cool. Let's move forward, everyone, if all is done, if you are clear with this.
Mayank Aggarwal: But I'm just letting you all of you know, please device. Please, please device.
Mayank Aggarwal: Teca?
Mayank Aggarwal: How did you connect FastTP and Fast MCP? I have not explained. I have not connected them as of now. I have not connected as of now. Let me do that in front of you, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me do that. Let me do that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me do that.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now everyone, let's try to see one very quick thing as well, which is how we can use this thing, rather than me defining everything one by one.
Mayank Aggarwal: And as I mentioned, that how they are very closely connected, I could just…
Mayank Aggarwal: Stop this complete thing. Sorry, comment out this complete thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I could just paste this code. So what I'm doing, I am importing Fast MCP,
Mayank Aggarwal: I am seeing that from Fast MCP
Mayank Aggarwal: dot from FastAPI, and my app is known as…
Mayank Aggarwal: App only, okay? So it is known as app only.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me paste this, and see. All this code which I've written now every month.
Mayank Aggarwal: Generally, this is what it will do. So, if I just stop my MCP server in here, let me stop it.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me stop the scene, clear everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Run it on 9997.
Mayank Aggarwal: See? It has started.
Mayank Aggarwal: And even though now I have not defined any tool, let's see that what all it got.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let me connect it.
Mayank Aggarwal: It has connected everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: See, it has got the tools like this. So basically, I now have all the tools, everyone.
Mayank Aggarwal: which is directly as an API endpoint, nothing else. Although, like, if you will notice, they are not very nicely named and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: But no prompts will be there, of course, and no resources. But, just by writing these four lines.
Mayank Aggarwal: all that…
Mayank Aggarwal: APIs which I have created, I could extract them out into an MCP, and this MCP can then now be used. So, if you focus on this empty one, one minute…
Mayank Aggarwal: So, in here, if you focus.
Mayank Aggarwal: Actually, you can use our same thing like this. So, let me quickly just…
Mayank Aggarwal: get that once we have created the MCP?
Mayank Aggarwal: This is how we will be able to use. So, either you can open the website tab, everyone, to fill in your project summary and everything, or you can just ask ClawDesktop that, hey, lock 3 hours for Arshad, and it will be able to do that for you.
Mayank Aggarwal: But yes, ideally, if you are having extra things like prompts or any extra
Mayank Aggarwal: things which you would want to control, that is where I would love to have
Mayank Aggarwal: myself create the MCP server, and normally, if I tell you, I still love to create my MCP server myself, so because I can give it much more better
Mayank Aggarwal: AI helpful documentation.
Mayank Aggarwal: And one more thing is there, which many of you might not realize, that normally APIs are already created, so to go and change something which is already working, that is, I can add a description here, and it will be kind of taken away.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, still, I would not love to change this thing, because it can fail something. So, Gmail, if I'm in Google.
Mayank Aggarwal: Rather than me changing the already working code in Gmail.
Mayank Aggarwal: I would want to maybe pay… take the pace-taking effort to write the MCP myself like this, so that I can have better names, I can have the better description and everything. Plus, it is also AI-ready as well, like, it is AI supportive, that AI can understand all these things. But yes, that said, there is a way through which you can do this, and now, easily, you can just
Mayank Aggarwal: create this thing properly via this particular thing, via just writing these four lines. Moving forward, everyone, last part of this, before we jump onto creating a client, is to make sure that how
Mayank Aggarwal: We can now push the code to GitHub.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then we can connect it to Horizont, so that it can pull up our code and have that MCP server, and finally, we will have the live URL. So, your project fast MCP app slash MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where I will be able to just quickly check if my MCP is actually working or not.
Mayank Aggarwal: And, as I mentioned, so, horizont MCP,
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, so it is from Prefect only. That does make sense. Even I was wondering that why they are, kind of promoting some other company. So, it is free forever for 2 users, up to 5 deployments, 500 a minute of services.
Mayank Aggarwal: I think this is not… this is the other one. So, for fast MCP, they have provided something else. Perfect horizontal.
Mayank Aggarwal: On this? Yeah, horizont. This one, I guess, is the main one.
Mayank Aggarwal: Every month. So, in this, again, they are just from the same company, just that it is free for one developer, 200 MCP servers, one agent.
Mayank Aggarwal: Log retention is for 1 hour, remote MCP hosting with Git Nadeem or CICD, so that anytime you are changing any code and everything, it connects to cloud code as well. So in the next part, everyone, we will understand
Mayank Aggarwal: properly that how… now that we have understood that how to create a complete project with the help of MCP, how exactly this can be integrated into any application on the internet, so that actually your product can be used by anyone on the world. And that is what MCP makes it very easy, because just by adding the
Mayank Aggarwal: Path of your… Project. You will be able to
Mayank Aggarwal: make it active on any AI, be it Cloud Desktop, Cloud Web, ChatGPT, cursor, anything. So that is where I think it will get a lot more powerful, so let's see the same in the next part.
Mayank Aggarwal: Please call it a day, Kapil. Again, I will call you out here.
Mayank Aggarwal: You have lots of questions, I make sure to clear it, so I will decide that where I will be stopping it, okay? Please make sure that if I'm explaining, focus on that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Once I clear that, then you can have this request. When I'm teaching, please don't disturb on this, because I have an eye on the thing, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Is there any different configuration needed for Cursor or ChatGPT or jami? No, no, it will be same normally, like the one which I showed you there, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Solo. And if for open code, and it will be done. You have lots of patience, great thanks, yeah. Teaching teaches you that. Cool. Arjai, do we want to do this, everyone, or do we want to do this in the next class? After this, just client creation is left, I guess?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, yeah, are you going to show how authorization will work in this project? Hardika will add the authorization.
Mayank Aggarwal: Bala, I can easily add the authorization. Now I will tell you what are the steps, everyone. We will post it to GitHub. We will create an account on GitHub, like, for people who are not having… they will connect the same to GitHub. GitHub will get connected to Horizen.
Mayank Aggarwal: And then we will have this. But I hope that now it is a lot clearer to everyone, like, this project should clear everything, everyone. Like, generally, this is very much in-depth.
Mayank Aggarwal: And honestly, I did not think that I will be doing these things line by line after giving you the code, but still, I've done that, so I hope you appreciate that, and…
Mayank Aggarwal: revise the same. In the next class now, what I will do every one then, and again, please revise everyone I want to, I plan to close MCP today, but generally I took an hour to explain these things.
Mayank Aggarwal: I don't have any concern with this, but if I'm putting in the ask to explain, but you are not revising, then that's a wasted effort for me.
Mayank Aggarwal: And hundreds of people would know this thing already. So, for people who are asking this, if you're not revising, that's a little bit bad as a complete community. Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Horizen, I will explain again, okay? Not a problem. Hello.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ha, cool, Ty, let's call it a day then.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me… Stop the share.
Mayank Aggarwal: And just quickly…
Mayank Aggarwal: And just one feedback, many people are not revising the classes. I will generally love if you are revising it properly. Teja? Let me give the same everyone more.
Mayank Aggarwal: Those tools raise participant hands.
Mayank Aggarwal: I disabled it because it is problematic. Actually, polls and quizzes there also as well, everyone. So yeah, do show your love on the poll. I hope you like the in-depth explanation, and this is a real-world project, everyone, right? So this is very much close to how you will be working on the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? Udaymi Gopal, let me provide you the next class, or I will post it in your craft link or something. So, do show your love on the…
Mayank Aggarwal: Pose, everyone. I'm also tired now. Devesh basic explanation is quite a little bit difficult, but diga. I hope you understand it. Now, please revise it. Highly suggested to revise the scheme.
Mayank Aggarwal: And yes, please don't hate me, because Mayank
Mayank Aggarwal: I know already this, why are you teaching this? Mayank… I don't know any of this, please teach this. So, that is something which I would want.
Mayank Aggarwal: But yeah, let's see how it points out.
Mayank Aggarwal: Journal.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, people can raise hand and I can ask questions. dipika, Bala, Basavannah, and Anshuli.
dipika vijapur: Yeah, hi Mayank, good morning. Hi, dipika. I really loved your explanation. I just got a little lost in the last part, where we connected our application which we created to the MCP. Can you please just go through that once? Did we use the Fast API, or did we use the tool? Because this is the actual use case in my application, which my senior built, and I'm very keen on understanding how we did this one.
Mayank Aggarwal: First thing, I hope you do understand the project overall, like, how we are having a time tracker which is having APIs.
dipika vijapur: Yeah, yeah, yeah. APIs, I'm good, because I already work on Java APIs.
Mayank Aggarwal: Java, you can use Swagger API.
dipika vijapur: Yeah, yeah, everything is relatable. Only part is how we connected this API to MCP, and what was the two ways? Why did we use at the tool instead of direct API endpoint? Something like that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me explain, yeah, yeah. See, when you use Adlerate tool, it just picks up your APIs and transforms that to tools, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: So it just picks up your APIs, whatever APIs you have created.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it just say that, hey, this is the tool which we are creating. So you have a lot less control if you think about this, right? Because on top of this.
Mayank Aggarwal: We genuinely are not having
Mayank Aggarwal: What if you want to, in a tool, use two APIs, not a single one? What if you want to make sure that you are having, more information about a particular
Mayank Aggarwal: tool, or let's say the argument which it is asking. So that's why I showed you by creating this. And plus, otherwise as well, because people were facing issues connecting the dots, and we have created earlier in the recipe box like this. So I created it with this.
Mayank Aggarwal: But ideally, inside this, I can call the APIs if required as well. So inside this, I can call the APIs. But how it is connecting, if you do this, all the APIs get converted to
Mayank Aggarwal: tools. In here, too, you have the complete control. You can define the prompts and everything as well.
dipika vijapur: Okay, now, in my use case, I already have a certain APIs which are already deployed in production, okay? Now, by using MCP server, MCP architecture, we want to expose those APIs to other consumers within the company. In that time, what do we use? This direct 4-line code, or at the right tool part?
Mayank Aggarwal: I will suggest this one.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can call your APIs from inside this, so that it is still like that, but I will highly suggest you use this one, because I would not want that you are changing these things, adding the description or anything into your code, any of the default values you are changing, because your APIs can be used at multiple places, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, any change which you do, that can have a breaking consequences. So, as an experienced developer, I will say that use this one, where you are using and having this kind of a proper… and then remove this, just call the API here directly. But I will be using this one, not the other way.
dipika vijapur: So, you mean either a tool is nothing but a wrapper on the API, where you have more control on the attributes, default values, or anything?
Mayank Aggarwal: No, no, no, no, no, no, I did not mean that.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm seeing that… When you create with this.
Mayank Aggarwal: It just does your work in the backend, where it takes up this one thing, and then it kind of wraps these APIs at the right MCP tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: But in here, so, we are defining it ourselves. So this MCP tool, it is not a wrapper on top of API, it is a proper function via which we control the creator tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: When we are doing this, then is where it wraps the APIs inside MCP tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: But otherwise, we control and RK and everything.
dipika vijapur: Okay, so when we say this add the right MCP tool, in this only we'll be handing authentication and everything if we need, if we are writing it as a tool, or that's a different part again.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now again, it depends. Do you want to do an authentication at each tool level or at an MCP server level? Normally, it will be at a server level, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: So you will authenticate the person at a server level, and authentication steps are very much similar, like how we have in
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, so how we have in the APIs? So you have the token validation, token verifier, OAuth.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, it's on you. Ideally, you would want that you can easily just,
Mayank Aggarwal: authenticate the person, and then in tools, you check if the person is having the
Mayank Aggarwal: ability to call… to call that particular API or not. Sorry, to call that particular tool or not.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is how we do it, right? You first let the person in with API, and then you say that, hey, you are not allowed to call this tool. So once you have done this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Auth, you can check that which, kind of permission the person is having.
Mayank Aggarwal: And after that authentication, then you can check, let me see if the person is allowed to have a tool or something. So authentication is just like how it works in APIs.
dipika vijapur: Okay, yeah, thank you. So, next question is, now, for example, in my use case, I have two sets of APIs. One is a GraphQL API, and one is a normal REST API, okay? One is for read part, and one is write. So, those are two different set of applications itself.
dipika vijapur: but we are using one MCP server to first connect to GraphQL and fetch the data, and then the same MCP server to connect to my other ingest, as in, like, to persist the data kind of thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: you're using.
dipika vijapur: Yes, yes, REST APIs. So, in that case, we have only one MCP server. I mean, when we have multiple combinations of API endpoints to be called, we do it at the tool level. How do we do this kind of integration?
Mayank Aggarwal: It's fine if you're doing it with a single MCP server.
dipika vijapur: It can be done, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: It is not a problem, yes, yes, yes, it is not at all a problem. I can have an MCP server which is having 5 of my most used functions across applications. See, the whole goal of MCP is to make sure that AI can connect with your application and do the work.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nothing else. So if you are very nicely handling it, not floating it.
Mayank Aggarwal: you are fine with that. Rather, create your tools in such a manner that they call multiple APIs inside them only, rather than creating…
dipika vijapur: doing that.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, Raghave, and everyone, this is for all of you, don't ever think that the tools are one-to-one with APIs. No, that is not the case. That happens most of the time, but that is not a requirement. Your tool can have multiple API calls as well. Not at all an issue.
dipika vijapur: Okay, yeah, thank you, Mayank. Actually, that will help me go look at my project in a better.
Mayank Aggarwal: Well, now I think you will be able to discuss and even create it a lot better, so I would highly suggest that with this knowledge you have.
Mayank Aggarwal: now revise it and ask Claude or chat GPT, this is what I'll know, this is what I want to do, and it will be able to explain you in a much better manner.
dipika vijapur: Yeah, and I totally agree, these are real-time projects itself, Mayank, because I can correlate what you're saying to my application.
Mayank Aggarwal: I also created with the same mindset key. That is how we normally work. We have an application already, we have APIs, now we create MCP on top of it.
dipika vijapur: Yes, that's what we are doing right now.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, that's the idea.
dipika vijapur: Thank you. Thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool.
Bala k: Hi, ma'am.
Mayank Aggarwal: Bala, yes.
Bala k: Yeah, thanks for all your explanation, just I'm trying to understand, like, I know if my… correct me if I am wrong, maybe I am missing something. So, I know we are building a project, and I'm trying to correlate with the Docker where, how the…
Bala k: this is the deployment of the some steps? Some, like, we have given it, like, a UV RAM kind of thing in the cloud desktop, so is it something like Docker steps we are going to provide in the real-time world? Like, when we are…
Mayank Aggarwal: What do you want? Like, see, what is the use of Docker according to you?
Bala k: So, I'm a Java developer, like, I'm creating a built-in Kubernetes when we are deploying to the cloud.
Bala k: So, at that time, so…
Mayank Aggarwal: So I can just have this complete application inside a Docker container, and then I can use it. So once the Docker container will unwrap, it will give me the API server, it will give me the MCP server as well, and the same will get carried on to Kubernetes and other businesses as well.
Bala k: Here, just trying to ask, so, how, like, do we really use Docker in this kind of.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, yes, we do that, we do that. We have, I think, many MCP servers, we are having the Docker way as well, so if I see…
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's say Tablei again, Tablei Docker MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: We will have the Docker image of MCP so that we can use it. It provides integration with Table Search and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because Docker, the volume is to make sure that it can package everything, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, in that case, we have Docker and everything, like, if you will see here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Local instantiation. This is the official documentation of Tablei, connecting the clients. So, it is giving via NPX.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: And…
Mayank Aggarwal: It is… see, it is giving via NPX, and I think it will be having the Docker one as well, let me search.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, Docker is just to make sure that all… everything is properly
Mayank Aggarwal: Containerized, so that when it works, we don't face any error.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, in that case, we can easily just
Mayank Aggarwal: Even Docker is a complete application, or just our MCP server, so that when the person will be running it, it starts up like a Docker Docker container, and person can just connect with it, and we are making sure that
Mayank Aggarwal: our container is separated out so that we don't face any issues. So that is where Docker will be used, and that all understanding kind of gets done here as well.
Bala k: Okay. The way I came into my mind is, like, we are going to deploy to the cloud, so that…
Mayank Aggarwal: So in the cloud, Madham, as of now.
Mayank Aggarwal: In this, we are not using Docker. In the project, we are having Docker.
Mayank Aggarwal: In the project, we will be having the complete application dockized, so that internally they can connect with MCP server and everything, but yes, that is the case.
Bala k: Okay. Thanks, Meg. Thanks for a lot of explanation. Thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great. Bala Apoor Basav
Mayank Aggarwal: Balaj.
Bala k: Bala is there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anshul, Basavannah, Murthy Debanjan, Harishid.
Anshul: Amen.
Anshul: MR.
Mayank Aggarwal: potentially, yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is your own image.
Anshul: Okay, am I audible now? Because…
Mayank Aggarwal: You're audible, you're audible.
Anshul: Okay, great, thank you. Thank you for the session, Lenk. I come from a local, community, okay? So, even then it was…
Anshul: Pretty good.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, then you will have to revise things, because…
Mayank Aggarwal: Many things which we will be doing in the future that will be based on Agentic side, so please spend the time in Devizer.
Anshul: Yes, yes, I'll do that.
Anshul: Just one question, man. In this time tracker project,
Anshul: We have created multiple files like app.js, style.css, index.html.
Anshul: And, these files refer to different layers of application development, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: use for front-end side, but yes, they are, like, it is a full-stack application, having a front-end and a backend.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, that is why I've created that.
Anshul: So can you just, it's a silly question, but can you just give me a high-level
Anshul: Understanding of the different layers of the stack, probably in the craft screen.
Anshul: That what is happening at.
Mayank Aggarwal: Stick with me.
Anshul: I'm revising, I can collect in the bedroom.
Mayank Aggarwal: When you create an application, normally there is two parts to it. Backend,
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me get it like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: content.
Mayank Aggarwal: Similarly, we have backend.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, backend is everything which handles your DB, your operations, and everything, which is, like, the major part of a project.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: For example, when you open google.com, right? This is the front end, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Which you see.
Mayank Aggarwal: Front-end, on the front. But when I search something here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Of course, in the backend, it will be going through millions of pages and then giving me the result. See how quick it is? Going through millions of pages for here.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, backend handles all that thing, backend then returns to Google, like, generally I can show you that as well, if you see quickly.
Mayank Aggarwal: Developer tools, inspect.
Mayank Aggarwal: Network? Network?
Mayank Aggarwal: Clearing everything. See, the second I click NBA, And hit up all.
Mayank Aggarwal: When I click on this scene, how many calls are getting made, because it's trying to find something.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, actually, see, I searched… this is a call which we made.
Mayank Aggarwal: I search… NBA, query was NBA, and it was going, and the backend responded with so many information.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now it is a rollover front-end to show this properly, because if Google shows you results like this, no one will use it, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Generally, it has given you a complete HTML, doc type HTML, as a response, which is to be used.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, in a similar fashion, in our application, we are having a front-end, which is nothing but this.
Mayank Aggarwal: And we are having a backend which is running. So very, very small kind of a thing in our case, not Google kind of a level, but yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, what you have to understand is that
Mayank Aggarwal: For my backend, information or anything can come from anywhere. Front-end is where I'm handling it via HTML, CSS, this app.js, because frontend will have to do this
Mayank Aggarwal: calling of the APIs and everything, right? So, front-end calls, APIs, and everything, that is done via app.js, so async function.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you're from no code, what I will do is just put up all these three codes, give all the code which I've given you in a zip to ChatGPT, and ask you to explain to you.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, this is what, in a very, very high sense, is happening, nothing else. So, back-end, I have the API so that I can interact with DP and everything. Front-end just shows me the result. Front-end doesn't care key how things are happening. Front-end just shows me the result, the way I'm giving it up.
Anshul: Yeah, thank you for it. I'll just run these files in ChatGPD and try to.
Mayank Aggarwal: Abho, that would be much better, although if you still face error, let me know. But on that note, I will still suggest that don't waste a lot of your time on this. Just understand that, there is a front-end and back-end.
Mayank Aggarwal: And majorly, in this course, we will be working on backend, because AI developer majorly will be back-end side, and front-end, thankfully, AI is getting a lot coded, so we can write it ourselves. And anyways, to be very honest, I'm not a… I don't like front-end work, so even if I have to write this code from scratch, I will not be able to write it up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because I don't like Venkat, okay?
Anshul: Okay, so if the backend… if the backend concepts are clear, then front-end can be created. That's not a big thing, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Normally, companies don't expect key… mother, they hire full check in here, but if you understand the concept of front-end small little bit, that's fine.
Mayank Aggarwal: It's not that…
Mayank Aggarwal: you will be asking to write each and everything and from every part. Though, that said, dependent on your experience, like, if you're in college now, that might be expected, but overall.
Mayank Aggarwal: it's not…
Mayank Aggarwal: It's like, you should know the complete cycle, that, hey, front-end gets connected, backend will send this data, this will be getting, like, how… so that is more than enough.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because if you have to now master front-end and backend, it will be a 6-7 months thing again, web development course or something.
Anshul: No, no, I won't master because I'm working in the industry from the last 13, 14 years.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that is not required. Yeah, yeah, that is more.
Anshul: I went to… business consulting and all, right? But I just want to understand the entire…
Anshul: architecture, so that if I'm in a meeting room with the relevant stakeholders and clients, I can explain everything at high level, you know?
Mayank Aggarwal: So this is more than what is required at a high level, at your 30, 40 years of experience. We will create these things up. Now, in… tomorrow, like, in the next class, we will create… add an agent as well as a client, so that whatever MCP we are creating, we can ourselves use it with agents, rather than… and I think we will use Langchain there.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that rather than Cloud Desktop, we are able to work it out and everything. So yeah, that is something which we will be creating.
Anshul: So, just 2 more minutes, and sorry to everyone.
Anshul: So, since I'm into SAP, so most of the enterprise data.
Anshul: are in the SAP system, if you talk about sales, finance, purchase.
Anshul: everything is in the database. So I have access to those databases.
Anshul: I have now understanding of how these AI systems work, thanks to you.
Anshul: Now we are trying to connect everything.
Anshul: And SAP has its own products, so you must have heard about SAP JUL and all, you know.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, Julia, yeah.
Anshul: Machil… the concept remains the same. It's exactly what you're teaching.
Mayank Aggarwal: Exactly same.
Anshul: Lapped it up in their product, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, yes, yes. So, someone understood concept in this much depth.
Mayank Aggarwal: And then they were able to create it, something which I'm trying with all of you guys.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, exactly how.
Anshul: Yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: you can now know MCPs in depth, and how the tools and everything works.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because otherwise, I could have just started with today's class directly to explain MCP, but yes, that much understanding, because now people are having, they were able to create a SAP,
Mayank Aggarwal: They would have also have MCP which connects with their JUS agent, etc, or they can ask… provide you, because I don't think they will give you the rate access outside, because that's a data problem, security problem, but yeah.
Anshul: Yeah, thank you, ma'am.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope that is clear.
Anshul: Excuse me.
Mayank Aggarwal: Mail me if anything else is there, I will be happy to help, not about.
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: Yeah, hi, man.
Mayank Aggarwal: One minute. Ms. Vendor?
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, can you hear me?
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: Going by the queue, everyone. Yeah. Yes, Ms.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, thanks, thanks for the explanation. I come from the web designing background.
Basavanna Olekar: So I got the whole concept.
Mayank Aggarwal: For you today.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, thanks, thanks again for that. Now, see, when we do any kind of a communication, it is a unidirectional. But here in MCP, in the last or last but last class.
Basavanna Olekar: You clearly explained it's a bidirectional. For example, when, yes.
Basavanna Olekar: When you host, and like, you know, a post call is made, there is no get call, or again, there is no post call from the other side to dump the data, right?
Basavanna Olekar: So, here, one question is, If a call is made.
Basavanna Olekar: say, for a specific tool, of a MCP server, whatever I'm hosted, not in a internet, but I'm telling about an internet, okay?
Basavanna Olekar: like, Google API. As it is a bidirectional, when the call is made, I can do the authentication.
Basavanna Olekar: Okay.
Basavanna Olekar: I can do the authentication. Oh, MCP code?
Mayank Aggarwal: Connect… no, no, no, no, again, just to connect you up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Authentication happens when you pull up your MCP initially.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, once it is authenticated, then you can use it.
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah, so that way I'm securing there. But once the authentication is made, it is not a unidirectional, it's a bidirectional, so is there any further
Basavanna Olekar: concerns I should have with respect to security because of the bidirectional communication, unlimited.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nope.
Basavanna Olekar: No, no, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: As a protocol, MCP kind of handles it, plus the bidirection communication is majorly… the server tells you that how much it has done a particular work.
Mayank Aggarwal: Or if you want to use your AI. So, just as an example.
Mayank Aggarwal: Client is having the access to AI, right?
Basavanna Olekar: Yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: server is not having that. MCP server doesn't have any access to it, so if…
Mayank Aggarwal: ever want to use AI, that is where it can ask client to do the same for you. So, in that case, just if you're connecting with the right MCP server, it should not be a problem. So, I will…
Mayank Aggarwal: Take that up that, okay, if you're connecting with a…
Mayank Aggarwal: Verified MCP servers is not a problem.
Mayank Aggarwal: But that is then true for everything, with respect to the… Complete, complete.
Mayank Aggarwal: case.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is what happens. So, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: You just want to make sure that you connect with the right servers.
Basavanna Olekar: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Basavanna Olekar: Thanks, thanks a lot.
Basavanna Olekar: That is it from my side.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, great. Harshit?
Harshit Goyal: Yeah, I will ask in the end, Mayank, actually, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Is it related to Bare?
Harshit Goyal: Sorry?
Mayank Aggarwal: Is it related to career?
Harshit Goyal: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, okay, just… you have to wait a little bit. Arshad is done. Basavana is done. People who have talked to, please have your hands down. Debanjan?
Murthy AI-ML: I'm a routine here.
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: So…
Mayank Aggarwal: First we'll go with the engine, going back to…
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: Yeah, hi. So I have a request, so for this, for today's class, will you be, sharing the chat box, transcript, please?
Mayank Aggarwal: I will have to ask the person, I don't upload the recordings or the transcript.
Mayank Aggarwal: your chatbot?
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: I'm in.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will have chatbot.
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: Chatbox.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, yeah, chats, I understood the message which you were sending to me.
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: Yeah, so if you shared those, I think it will be beneficial,
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me ask. Let me ask if we do get that, so what should we find?
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: I mean, you can, copy those, to your front. And, why specifically I'm asking is, like,
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: For, last two weeks, well, I cannot attend your classes, so I was running around with all the things.
Mayank Aggarwal: Mhmh.
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: So I'm still going through, so if you can, share today's chat and…
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: I think it will be beneficial for… to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will try, but honestly, we avoid that, because many questions are there, or many things are there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which are…
Mayank Aggarwal: I will, I will try, like, let me ask if I can mask it or something, but yeah.
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: Yeah, I mean, I'll be going through this class, and side-by-side effect, and see that it will be…
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, let me ask the person if it can be done, but otherwise, to be very honest, I try to read out the question loud, which are relevant.
Mayank Aggarwal: And normally, I'm not teaching in the Pomodoro way, like, I teach for 10-15 minutes, and then I take the question.
Mayank Aggarwal: So anyways, to be very honest, I try that you don't miss out on anything. But still, I will ask the person if he can share the same.
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: Yeah, Liz.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Debanjan Mani_Laptop: Absolutely.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you, Murthy.
Murthy AI-ML: Hi, Mayank. My question is in the database.py file. Can you open that? So, I see that you call the explicit, queries, where, create the database and extract some queries, right? So, if I wanted to call something else which is not part of this, database.py file, so how that we can retrieve it?
Mayank Aggarwal: you can call it, right? If you want to call on the dynamic calling, basically.
Murthy AI-ML: Right, let's say you are inserting some records here, but I wanted to insert from the tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: So you will create a tool, create a function here first, where you will take, so let's say dev.
Mayank Aggarwal: execute.
Mayank Aggarwal: query, something like this, okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, getting connected, executing whatever query you are giving, and closing the connection, okay? And you just return the rows and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, in your this part, You can create a tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ada is MCP… Dude.
Mayank Aggarwal: And we can make short diff.
Mayank Aggarwal: execute.
Mayank Aggarwal: griddy… too dynamically.
Mayank Aggarwal: And you can have something like this. So, when your AI will be using this, it will be sending the query and the parameters.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I would just also make sure that excess… the… it is source… or schema.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, that you know the… Tables, etc.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now I can define at the rate MCP.asource.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, this, thanks to the AI thing, yeah, this tells you.
Mayank Aggarwal: So now it… your AI will be able to understand that, okay, this is the exact table which is there, and it can execute the query.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because Claude and Adais are smart enough. Though, just one thing to note here.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will now have to love to have some cartels, because I don't want that it deletes anything. So that's why, though it is pretty easy, like, now your AI will tell you that, hey, this is the query which I want to execute.
Mayank Aggarwal: It will execute the query.
Mayank Aggarwal: And, yeah, you can get your work done, but then you should not be able to delete or change multiple things, so that is something which I will correct.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay, so I can create, I can retrieve, but to update something, we can enable god rails, that I understood. So…
Mayank Aggarwal: And Aditya, I think, should be better with cartels.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay, so if you wanted to create a new table, does it still allow here?
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, here everything is allowed as of now, but we are not closing anything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Any…
Mayank Aggarwal: query which you give, I just directly execute it. I'm not stopping anywhere, just totally on you. I'm just executing the query.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay, understood. So, I see there are close to 5 columns here, but I wanted to retrieve only employee name and the project. So, how does it manage that, only retrieve the only 2 columns? My query is not enough.
Mayank Aggarwal: Sweetie.
Murthy AI-ML: Mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: You know?
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, it will be query, so if you ask your cloud when it is connected or not.
Mayank Aggarwal: on any, on any AI client.
Mayank Aggarwal: That, hey, please get me this. So it will just do select employee name and project from this time entries table.
Mayank Aggarwal: And you can have any other thing as well, so it can do that.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay.
Murthy AI-ML: So every time we need to…
Mayank Aggarwal: But your AI should be smart, like, it should not be the case that you are using any small LLM model which is of 200 MP and you are asking it.
Murthy AI-ML: Is it… is it something like Text2SQL, the query what you wrote here?
Murthy AI-ML: Text2SQL is similar, or does it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh.
Mayank Aggarwal: Mother, you can take it as Text2SQL. You were just telling that, hey.
Mayank Aggarwal: I just wanted to guess. That text or request gets converted to MC… to a SQL, and then SQL is getting executed. Nothing else.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay.
Murthy AI-ML: So, in this complete project, right, what is client and what is server Mayank?
Mayank Aggarwal: what is client and what is server? As of now, there is just a server, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: We have not created any client or anything. So, again, there are multiple facets to it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Multiple facets. With respect to MCP, I can tell you.
Mayank Aggarwal: We have just created an MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah. If you start up the MCP inspector, then that becomes the client.
Mayank Aggarwal: And, if you connect it to Cloud Desktop, which I expect that you all will do, I'm not doing that, because that's pretty simple now, then Claude Desktop will be the host and client, so Cloud Desktop will be the host, it will start up a client, which will get connected to the server.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay.
Murthy AI-ML: So, in this server, can I have multiple databases? I see one is SQL here, so likewise, can I have multiple Cosmo, or Mongo, or those things also?
Mayank Aggarwal: Totally on you, totally on you, how you want to connect it.
Murthy AI-ML: Don't have any limit, you mean?
Mayank Aggarwal: It's a normal quote.
Murthy AI-ML: Oh.
Mayank Aggarwal: I would not like to see it as, in this server, can I…
Mayank Aggarwal: I would like to see it as, can this server do multiple operations on DP? Because I don't create MCP servers and everything. I would like to ask it… this question is more relevant for an application.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can I have an application where we are having multiple DBs? That's the right question.
Mayank Aggarwal: You normally don't try to create
Mayank Aggarwal: application with MCP directly. You create MC application first, and then on top of it, you create MCPs.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay, understood.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is clear. Oh, sorry.
Murthy AI-ML: Yeah, sure.
Murthy AI-ML: So, I see you opened the log file, so how it is generated? I mean, can you open the log file again?
Murthy AI-ML: Somewhere you open the log, in between Vallu execution.
Mayank Aggarwal: From Claude?
Murthy AI-ML: No, I think from your project code.
Mayank Aggarwal: I must have opened multiple logs file, let me see…
Mayank Aggarwal: Ecto, we get the logs in the terminal directly, if you see.
Murthy AI-ML: and so…
Mayank Aggarwal: Here, we get all the terminals, logs, key, who is connecting, and whatever. This…
Murthy AI-ML: Yeah, not internal, somewhere you have opened the manual log file. Not sure, I didn't follow that.
Mayank Aggarwal: One minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: See, I can tell you where all the logs and everything is present.
Mayank Aggarwal: One minute, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: So…
Mayank Aggarwal: Claude, all the logs file, you can ask Claude directly, it is present here as well. Let me show you the settings.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you go on Developer, You can see the logs from here.
Mayank Aggarwal: recipe box updated, we can see the logs from here. So, are you talking about this one?
Murthy AI-ML: Yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: So this, I just connected this thing, new logs.
Mayank Aggarwal: from Clare Desktop.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay, these are the cloud logs, right? Not the project log.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is logs from Cloud, like, cloud desktop application.
Mayank Aggarwal: So it is kind of trying to do everything. Server started and connected successfully, shutting down server. Light closed, server closed. Using MCP server, Command UV, and it is starting all these things up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then it started a fast MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then it must have tried to somewhere get the tools list and prompt list.
Mayank Aggarwal: the source list, then it got all these things up. So earlier it used to show you the MCP as well, JSON, sorry, JSON RCP, but now it is not showing that. So this is the… this is the locks for the clot.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, everything has its logs, right? It is totally on you at what you want to see. So, this is the logs for the clock.
Murthy AI-ML: If you wanted to see the log, how my project is working, so, where you can see that?
Mayank Aggarwal: Which project?
Murthy AI-ML: I mean, the one, you have executed.
Mayank Aggarwal: The time tracker there?
Murthy AI-ML: on the VS Code.
Mayank Aggarwal: Time track, what?
Murthy AI-ML: Yes, yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: We will have to create a log file here, but we will already have to create a proper logging file.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, that would have everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, I can showcase, like, do that right in front of you right now, actually.
Murthy AI-ML: for…
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you please create a log file?
Mayank Aggarwal: and a proper logging functionality, so that anything which happens into my time tracker, I'm able to record with that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thanks to AI, this is very simple, though I would still expect that error handling and everything, we are aware.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now it will create a log file for my application, so any API hit, anything which happens.
Mayank Aggarwal: But there will be lots of changes, actually. So I should not do it. But yes, it will read all the files, and it will give you that how…
Mayank Aggarwal: everything can be logged there, so it will create a logger, and that logger will then be used. So that is how we will be
Mayank Aggarwal: Maintaining the logs for our application.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm not doing it because it will add unnecessary multiple changes at every point. So every call, it will try to add a log file, log change, and everything. So, but, yeah, that is possible.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay. Is it STD or HTTP Mayank, or this complete part? Time Tracker?
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you.
Murthy AI-ML: Sorry, easily.
Mayank Aggarwal: I think it do the lock file, not the lock file, but I hope it will be right, because in the future, it takes…
Mayank Aggarwal: happens into my time tracker, I'm able to record that. Proper login, Arti. It should not be logged. Murthy, I hope it is clear.
Murthy AI-ML: Yes, ma'am, it is clear now. And last question, sorry.
Mayank Aggarwal: audible.
Murthy AI-ML: Can you hear me now?
Mayank Aggarwal: Nini mic was on, and I tried to give the input, yeah.
Murthy AI-ML: Okay, so last question. So, I see this is completely into SDDO, right? Not HTTP.
Mayank Aggarwal: As of now, it is HTTIO, this is a local server.
Murthy AI-ML: Right, okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can I check it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Here.
Mayank Aggarwal: But we will be creating an HTTP server as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: remote service.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is STDIO. So, what we can do, it's very easy. If I just add the host here and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: I can just make it start with an HTTPS VIN, rather…
Mayank Aggarwal: So I will showcase that, actually.
Mayank Aggarwal: In the future class.
Mayank Aggarwal: Right now, it's SDIO, but we can easily just… so, see, by default, when we do this with TPL, it starts off as a STDIO, but we can give it a…
Mayank Aggarwal: basically address as well, then it will start as HTTP.
Murthy AI-ML: Understood. Thank you, Mayank.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you. Great.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool, okay, so Ramakrishna Yashwanth… Sudhl?
Ramakrishna P: Hi man.
Mayank Aggarwal: Who please have hands down. Hi.
Ramakrishna P: Can you… can you hear me?
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, yes, you're on the one.
Ramakrishna P: Yeah, Mayank, when we ran this MCP.run, right, so our tool definition, somehow it get converted to JSON RPC2 schema, right? So, where can I see that, and then the LLM call, where it is going?
Mayank Aggarwal: LLM, though, we have not included as of now.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want to see… Again, let me reiterate. When we run… when we run an MCP inspector.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, when we have created this, as of now, when it runs, just MCP server get starts, okay?
Ramakrishna P: Great.
Mayank Aggarwal: No, nothing, no.
Mayank Aggarwal: tool and a thing is happening, MCP server just is starting.
Ramakrishna P: Good night.
Mayank Aggarwal: when I run MCP inspector, on the other hand, then we have a client now here, so this is a client.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which gets connected. And see?
Ramakrishna P: Great, great.
Mayank Aggarwal: where it is with all that complication in JSON, RPC, and everything which I told you and taught you about.
Mayank Aggarwal: Properly, it is doing all the functionalities.
Ramakrishna P: Right, right, for our current APIs and tools, what we have within the time tracker, still do we need to bring up one more thing, or in the SDI mode, how can we bring this? It looks like it's in HTTP, right?
Ramakrishna P: Interesting.
Mayank Aggarwal: Studio.
Ramakrishna P: Yesterday. So, for our thing, how can we bring it up again? One more report, and then same…
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, I didn't get the question. What do you want to make it again?
Ramakrishna P: Currently, we have our time tracker project and the tools we expose it, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, yes, he is.
Ramakrishna P: So for that, the runtime-generated JSON schema, where can we see?
Ramakrishna P: again, we need to come this kind of MCP inspector here, right?
Ramakrishna P: Or it… in this itself, it will show.
Mayank Aggarwal: Maybe, again, so the logging happens… we can do the logging at a server end as well, but normally the logging happens with the clients connecting, clients maintain the logs.
Mayank Aggarwal: For example, here, MCP inspector is maintaining the logs. You just want to see the logs, right? This is just on RPC 2.0 or something else.
Ramakrishna P: Yeah, runtime generated, for our tools, current time tracker APIs, right, the tools, whatever we expose. For that, the runtime-generated JSON RPC wanted to see how it is going there.
Mayank Aggarwal: What do you mean by runtime-generated GS1 RPC?
Ramakrishna P: this response, or the request, I mean, we are giving prompt or something, right, to get some response, correct?
Mayank Aggarwal: No, no, no, no, no, again, see.
Mayank Aggarwal: I told you, when you connect your client and server without even using the same
Mayank Aggarwal: Initially, only it hits the phone calls. So this is all the runtime when only. I'm not asked any response, or I'm not asking anything.
Ramakrishna P: No, no, no, for our calls, for our calls, if you go to the time tracker, let's say, go to the time tracker one, let's say one tool we can see, one API call, which is internal calling, right? You will see get time over, get somebody, right? So, if I call this one, somehow, just come down, yeah, let's take one, new entry, or whatever it is, huh?
Mayank Aggarwal: API or MCPI or tooth?
Ramakrishna P: tool, tool, but this API internally will be called by tool only, right? That MCP tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, yes.
Ramakrishna P: Right? Now, this schema generated, not this database schema I'm referring, for our request schema, whatever we are hitting it, that somehow gets serialized and then converted to JSON RPC2.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that will depend on how we are, like, which client we are using to call it, right? For example, if I am calling this one, as an example, I'm just showing you, let me clear everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: See, client calls the server, right?
Ramakrishna P: Great.
Mayank Aggarwal: So now, this is a client which I will be calling with…
Mayank Aggarwal: And see, there is a… there is a… Logs now?
Mayank Aggarwal: If you're using Claude, then it will have a clock somewhere else.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, client maintains these logs when you're hitting it up. So, it made a tool slash call, it gave the name of the tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: And if any argument or anything is required, that is how it is able to work on these things. So this is how you can see the logs. Client, when you use client.
Mayank Aggarwal: Client maintains these logs, right?
Ramakrishna P: Right, right.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I call the tool, and I'm having the API and this, I'm able to see it here.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I think…
Ramakrishna P: I'm asking for our current, thing, my…
Mayank Aggarwal: What is that current thing? I'm not able to understand.
Ramakrishna P: This Time Tracker project.
Mayank Aggarwal: project, yeah, so this is the tools for the time tracker project only.
Ramakrishna P: There we could see different names, right? The, new entry ad, get method at post method 30, get API list projects, list API.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where is the budgets are.
Ramakrishna P: Yeah, yeah.
Ramakrishna P: API?
Mayank Aggarwal: list project, API project get. So, I think it is adding API in the starting.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is maintaining this. So, this naming will not be directly compatible, it is just, Fast MCP must have kind of made a naming convention that first add API in the starting, because it's an API.
Ramakrishna P: Pop me, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: And then timesheet API, timesheet.
Ramakrishna P: That's what I'm just trying to compare both, it is not matching, so how it is generating impact.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is a name, we can ask it.
Ramakrishna P: Okay, that's okay, that's okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Initially, let us fix it up soon.
Ramakrishna P: This is the JSON RPC2 one, that's okay. I wanted to get clarity on that.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me paste it. Let me paste it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me paste the world code, actually.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you tell me how, when I'm directly creating the tools, from my APIs.
Mayank Aggarwal: the naming convention overall works, and how fast MCP defines the names.
Ramakrishna P: And the RPC, how it converts to the… JSON RPC2 compatible schema.
Mayank Aggarwal: Please, schema and everything is compatible. It is all good, it is not a problem.
Ramakrishna P: Yeah, but AbhiT is creating with our request, that's what I just wanted to connect.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, I'm still not able to understand. See, we are having the MCPs here.
Ramakrishna P: Alright, hold on.
Mayank Aggarwal: from this MCP… sorry, we are having the API here.
Ramakrishna P: Right, right.
Mayank Aggarwal: From these APIs, we create tools.
Ramakrishna P: Tools, right.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Ramakrishna P: Late.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, we can call the tool. When the tools will be called by our client, we will be able to get the RPC request. If you are saying that, okay, Gaurav, that RPC, how that gets converted
Mayank Aggarwal: Excellent.
Ramakrishna P: That's what, again, that serialized and deserialize, nobody is happening internally, and then…
Mayank Aggarwal: So, let's ask this again only here. So, see, it is… this UGM created up. Let me ask you in follow-up question.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now my MCP when I connect it with a client, it works in a JSON RPC
Mayank Aggarwal: But… The same request will be sent as a… Complete.
Mayank Aggarwal: Overall, API request, because I'm directly converting the same into a tool.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you explain me how that happens as VIN?
Ramakrishna P: And if we give it to the agent or LLM, how it will work in that case? How can you feed it to the…
Mayank Aggarwal: I will normally explain you, like, see, when we are sending this JSON RPC, let's say, let's use this one.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me just fill some Prometries.
Mayank Aggarwal: 0-1, 0-1.
Mayank Aggarwal: Whatever. See, when I execute this tool, it got executed.
Mayank Aggarwal: We are sending these Argument, the structured content, right?
Ramakrishna P: It's in the back.
Mayank Aggarwal: Second, it will be taking the structured content and sending that to my, that directly, to the APIs. So, that way, Fast MCP will be handling this thing. Where this structured content, it takes in as an argument, because these are the arguments, and it is aware of the same
Mayank Aggarwal: Because FastMCP has created this complete thing for me, right? So it is aware, and it will be sending the same as well. So we can edit the same as JSON as well, and otherwise.
Mayank Aggarwal: And I think this is what it will suggest. But there are two different protocols involved. Your MCP client talks to MCP server using RPC 2.0, that's where you created the server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Fast MCP knows that an MCP tool such like list project correspond to fast API rules such as this. So the flow is, MCP client gives the JSON RPC
Mayank Aggarwal: maps MCP tool to the OpenAI or Fast API route?
Mayank Aggarwal: Fast EP endpoint gets hit, goes to the database.py result, fast MCP converts the result into the MCP response, and we finally get the response like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yep.
Ramakrishna P: Good.
Mayank Aggarwal: I hope this was the question, right?
Ramakrishna P: And one more question here is, when we call that MCP.run, so how that loop is getting executed? That is where the difference between normal versus the CA loop run, right, for the MCP
Ramakrishna P: In the 65 line, MCP.run. That's where our, lifecycle gets triggered and then initialized and all that.
Yashwanth Panji: Starting in MCP server, that's all okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: an MCP server, if you run this file directly.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, what this means, name, main, -
Ramakrishna P: Yeah, easily.
Mayank Aggarwal: to me.
Ramakrishna P: Yeah, if that is recommended.
Mayank Aggarwal: hitting this file, then MCP will start, MCP server will start.
Yashwanth Panji: Oh my goodness.
Ramakrishna P: The life cycle, how it will be.
Ramakrishna P: That one time?
Mayank Aggarwal: Glasses.
Ramakrishna P: The loop will get executed, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Which loop?
Ramakrishna P: The MCP lifecycle loop will get initialized and then run, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Any, any MCP lifecycle loop gets executed when you connect it with a client. This here-only server will start.
Ramakrishna P: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: server will start. When the client will connect to that server.
Ramakrishna P: Huh.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is where that loop will start of lifecycle. And it's not a loop, actually, like, that's a wrong statement, it's not a loop.
Mayank Aggarwal: It's three steps. Initialization, operation, then shutdown.
Ramakrishna P: Okay, so MCP.run will not go through that initialization and, that.
Mayank Aggarwal: No, it will just start the server, it will just start the server. If I do… Python CD.
Mayank Aggarwal: CD time track.
Mayank Aggarwal: And if I do Python… 3… Sweet.
Mayank Aggarwal: to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nobody named FastPBHR.
Ramakrishna P: That's okay, that's okay, my young boy.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm gonna end with you.
Ramakrishna P: I got that one. Just wanted to client side, how it is, how we are calling that line, I forgot, actually.
Ramakrishna P: In the client side, when we are initializing.
Ramakrishna P: Instead of MCP.run, we might have our… Fast ends up being…
Yashwanth Panji: my question and leave. You know, I just have some two, three questions, okay? I cannot wait, huh?
Yashwanth Panji: Yep.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, Sean, can you just wait a little bit? I will just close it, like, you can go.
Yashwanth Panji: No, no, I mean, it is getting extended. I mean, I've been waiting from last.
Mayank Aggarwal: I totally understand. XTV, sorry, for the same. Arabisa, just wait a minute. Yes, yes, you can ask your questions.
Yashwanth Panji: just see, like, now today, what I understood is, you know, just earlier with the API concept, first API, you know, concept, we used to just do with the methodical and procedure, we have to get to, just to get to the API to execute. Now, with the MCP, with the human language, we are able to get our jobs done. Am I right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Majorly, that is the role of MCPS.
Yashwanth Panji: That is done. That is, our LLM will convert our natural language into this API-specific routing, and get the jobs done for us, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: I will not say that it's one-to-one API routing, but yes, literally it's do something on the product.
Yashwanth Panji: That's what, see, like, now LLM will query the MCP server, get the tools, and invoke the API, get the response, and convert it into your job in a natural language. That is the use of our MCP server now, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: More or less, yes, yeah.
Yashwanth Panji: Yeah, okay, so second thing is, like, Kumar is, like, you know, the, you know, the tool, what you told is, like, you know, to get the icons right immediately, so you told the tool name, I forgot it, can you just repeat me one more time?
Mayank Aggarwal: 16?
Yashwanth Panji: No, no, whenever you try to set the icon right in, whether it is a customer, RAVET.
Mayank Aggarwal: I think it's in Mac only, and it is connected… after that, it is connected to Google Calendar. Let's keep the question related to this concept only,
Yashwanth Panji: Yeah, yeah, okay, okay. Next, yeah, one more receipt, like, now in my company, my ANSI, like, what they're doing is in MCP server, they're having, you know, sub-agents, okay? Sub-agents are mapped to the tools.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Yashwanth Panji: Subway agents are mapped to the tools, and they know, like, and the tools will get the… there is MCP client, and which will connect to the main, QA agent, and the QA agent will have Subway agent, and the Subway agent will have the map to the tools.
Yashwanth Panji: And the, you know, there is a job getting work done, so can we have… can we be able to show, you know, how we, you know, agent-to-sub agent communication happens via tools?
Yashwanth Panji: Can we do the…
Mayank Aggarwal: discussing that. Agent to sub-agent communication doesn't happen via tools.
Yashwanth Panji: No, no.
Mayank Aggarwal: You are suggesting is that there is an agent.
Mayank Aggarwal: Beneath that agent, we are having sub-agents, and each sub-agent is having access to some specific tools.
Yashwanth Panji: Tools, yes, correctly.
Mayank Aggarwal: That we will cover in multi-agent architecture, and we will cover it in Langchain.
Yashwanth Panji: No, we are covering, right? That one?
Mayank Aggarwal: Langchain… it is a Langchain concept, it's not an MCP concept.
Yashwanth Panji: Oh, okay, okay, okay. Fine, then, I'm done, Mike. Thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great. Sargyback to Ramakrishna.
Ramakrishna P: Yes, oh my god.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, see, I will quickly help you. I think this question is clear, right?
Ramakrishna P: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: So now, when you start your MCP server, and when a client attached to it, then client do that call, the process. The client is the one which initializes this call, not the server.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, in here, for example, my MCP inspector is the client.
Mayank Aggarwal: And it is doing all these steps, right in front of us, so when I avoid it, when I connect to this, this is where my steps begin, because client make these calls up.
Mayank Aggarwal: When I do MCP run, it is where just the server is starting up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, on this server, I can have client getting connected. So, from a single server, multiple client can get connected.
Mayank Aggarwal: So I hope that is fine, right? Because the server is running.
Mayank Aggarwal: Each client will always connect to one server, but one server can host or have multiple clients connected to it, just like how it happened with HTTP as well, right?
Ramakrishna P: -
Mayank Aggarwal: So that is why, when this MCP run happens, nothing is happening, just my server is starting up, and then once the server starts up as well, for example, if we quickly just do one thing here…
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me quickly do UVCD time track.
Mayank Aggarwal: UV run, fast, MCP run.
Mayank Aggarwal: One minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: Way to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: So now it will just start my MCP server, see? Starting MCP server with transport STDIO,
Mayank Aggarwal: now anyone can connect to this directly, or they can start their own, but only server has started as of now. No, nothing is happening.
Ramakrishna P: Now, when we run our client, this server, as a sub-process, it will get started, as it is in a STDI mode.
Mayank Aggarwal: A client will start up a…
Mayank Aggarwal: server in itself. So if I do it here, you will still not see the logs here. This client is starting as a sub-process, this inside it.
Ramakrishna P: Yeah, yeah, client, started, Saraviz is a process, attach it to it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes.
Ramakrishna P: Right? So, that's where we, in our fast MCP client, we are, writing, and then the client. The session.
Ramakrishna P: We have written, correct? SDAM.
Alok: When we are…
Ramakrishna P: Not here. Yesterday, we connected separate client, we have written in the Zoom, right?
Ramakrishna P: Fast MCP client test.
Mayank Aggarwal: I don't think I've shown Fast MCP client as well.
Ramakrishna P: We changed that quote, and then we brought it up, right, in the inspect mode. Client, this is how we are today. I mean…
Ramakrishna P: Which Rasti did I work to land?
Mayank Aggarwal: Which way?
Ramakrishna P: A warm-up, warm-up project? I think warm-up project, or first MCP server?
Ramakrishna P: Yesterday, you shared one link to access with 999 or 49 ports, the client.
Mayank Aggarwal: You have to give me the filing, I mean, multiple files we work on.
Ramakrishna P: Mmm…
Mayank Aggarwal: Cannot do like that.
Mayank Aggarwal: This was what we were working on yesterday.
Ramakrishna P: a recipe… Some client, you pinged.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just take the time, tell me which file is it, let me move on to other questions we buy.
Mayank Aggarwal: Any other question?
Ramakrishna P: Nuh- I'm gonna do.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, you can tell me the file, I'm still keeping you, and let's see that.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you're saying this, okay, I think Venki has given me the code. If you're saying this one, right, client, quote, something like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Which I ran. I think it will be obed, one minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: What are you saying this one, Ka?
Ramakrishna P: In spec mode, you started…
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I started the…
Ramakrishna P: I'm Eshwarzene.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is the inspector, same inspector, which I gave you the one, right?
Ramakrishna P: Okay, but here also we started with MCP.run only, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: This is… no, no, no, this I'm starting the MCP inspector client, and it starts the MCP server inside it, this MCP server.
Ramakrishna P: But if we see that 42 line, it's MCP.run only, we are keeping it, Mayank then.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nito, this run can be here done? Like, what is your concern with this MCP not run? I'm not kidding.
Ramakrishna P: what you are saying is MCP.runny generally will start the MCP server, right? Boot-up process. Now, when it comes to the client, client will not do that MCP.run.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nadeem again.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, let me clear it. See, I understood.
Mayank Aggarwal: In this phase, because I'm using the inspector, it is not that two servers will start up. With this line, I'm telling Python 3, this is where the same thing is present.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, it will just start up as a subprocess of this FCP inspector.
Mayank Aggarwal: Clear?
Mayank Aggarwal: Just, this MCP inspector will start off, it will not care about this MCP run and start the same. No. I'm just telling my inspector that, hey.
Mayank Aggarwal: you start this python3 recipe box fastmcp.py, you run this command, and there is a server here.
Ramakrishna P: Okay, okay, okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: It will start that as a subset.
Ramakrishna P: Both will be in communication. Intercommunication is happening between these two.
Mayank Aggarwal: We are having a publication like this.
Mayank Aggarwal: In here as well, when I do this connect, it'll run this thing inside. It'll run this thing. So I think I closed the seam, so it is now showing the error, but yeah.
Ramakrishna P: That's okay, that's okay, yeah, okay, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: I closed the kitchen.
Ramakrishna P: Yeah, okay, man, thanks.
Mayank Aggarwal: One minute, who is the next one? Alok?
Alok: Yes, can you hear me?
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, it's Arunaball.
Alok: How can this time application be accessed within the same organization?
Mayank Aggarwal: Same organization as it?
Alok: means, suppose I have deployed this service, and…
Alok: Another colleague of mine want to access it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just deploy it on a link which is shable. So, as of now, it is on my local host.
Mayank Aggarwal: I would have it running and share it with a link.
Mayank Aggarwal: Or maybe on a server like Vercel or Netlify, if you want to do it for free.
Mayank Aggarwal: And then anyone can access it.
Alok: But if by chance that servers are not allowed in the organization.
Mayank Aggarwal: Mmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then you cannot do it. If you cannot load up your own server, then you cannot do it.
Mayank Aggarwal: of NCROC, if you are aware of that tunneling concept.
Mayank Aggarwal: Sorry, you were asking, Anju?
Alok: Oh, Can't we put it as a MCP server or something like that? I'm not aware of, so…
Mayank Aggarwal: No, no, you want to give the application access, whereas I want to access this application, I don't care about MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: Where does the MCP come? And I just want to access the application. MCP comes after what?
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want to give the access to MC application, you will be able to host it first.
Alok: So hosting needs to be done by? Or can you just ping the name of the servers which you're talking about?
Mayank Aggarwal: Actually, hosting is… can be done by multiple ways, like, iTunn is working on my machine.
Mayank Aggarwal: Currently, you can do it on Vercel, Netlify, these are websites which can run your code and host it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Or else, you can have a machine, like, any VPC machine on hosting, or on AWS or GCP, so your application can be hosted in
Mayank Aggarwal: Unlimited ways, I will say. So that depends on what your company allows, and otherwise what you are comfortable in.
Mayank Aggarwal: And then you will be getting a link, and you can access that link easily.
Alok: Server is required to deploy this application.
Mayank Aggarwal: RBS, because… Then, if my machine stops as of now, then how will you access it?
Alok: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pursuit?
Alok: Yes, and last question is, whatever you have taught till now?
Alok: Will that be helpful to find the jobs outside India also, even though I'm working for.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, yes, yes. So, like, Raghan, to be honest, outside India, they focus a lot more on the conceptual part, in my understanding.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, if you tell them that, hey, I've created MCP and I've done that in this level.
Mayank Aggarwal: I believe that even 95%, 97% of the people would not have done that. Concepts are exactly the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, anything which I'm teaching that holds good across the world, hopefully, as of now.
Alok: Thank you so much.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: Saranya next to you, are you?
Saranya Thangaraj: Hi, Mayank.
Mayank Aggarwal: Right.
Saranya Thangaraj: Mayank, I am completely from data engineering background, so… So today, before adding that MCP dot tool, or that, FastMP MCP, so that is a pure, you know, web-based.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cheers.
Saranya Thangaraj: Right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Till here it is pure… no, not here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Unlimited.
Mayank Aggarwal: Time track, would you? Time track?
Mayank Aggarwal: I mean, to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: Bill… Here, it is a pure, pure, normal application, nothing to do with MCP or anything.
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay, so when I'm running this, like, you know, fast API, URL in the… some, Chrome, so when I ask question, so based on that, that, .ap.get will re… redirect, okay, user is asking this employee's, timesheet, this, and, no, API project summary, all those things.
Saranya Thangaraj: And then this will help to connect to DB, and we'll get the information in the front-end screen, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Excuse me.
Saranya Thangaraj: we add this, you know, MCP, what is exactly happening? I'm unable to visual that part.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, see, I will make it visualized to you. Let's say that someone wants to now use your application, okay?
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: I was saying that, hey, you can come to this and use my application, not a problem.
Saranya Thangaraj: Mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: That person says that, hey, that is all fine, but I don't want to use it like this. I want to connect it with my tools. Like, I use… my people use Claude a lot.
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you connect it with Claude so that it happens automatically, or I can just mention that, hey, I am… please lock some time for Mayank?
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you do that? First, let's tell me the answer. Can you do that without MCP normally without MCP.
Saranya Thangaraj: No. I need to manually type it.
Mayank Aggarwal: So let me make it a little bit clear. You can do that without MCP, otherwise then you will have to create
Mayank Aggarwal: These scripts and everything, which can be called.
Mayank Aggarwal: And those things will make the changes in your DB and everything from API… from AI.
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: But then that becomes a problem. Today, I have this four… four or five functions. What if I make them, let's say, more enhanced, 10 to 15, I make these changes. For example, today I'm not asking anything here. Maybe I'm asking for any list project, I'm asking the department here tomorrow, just as an example.
Saranya Thangaraj: Mhmh, mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nope!
Mayank Aggarwal: If I do a change here, you will also have to make sure that you do the change right now in your… at your end, okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Or keep on updating the same thing again and again.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that your script doesn't fail, else your script will fail the moment you have not updated or anything.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now to make sure, and the very good example of this is, let's say, Gmail, okay?
Saranya Thangaraj: Mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: or Slack, or any other calendar management.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, now, rather than…
Mayank Aggarwal: me saying that, hey, I will maintain all these things up and define the tools.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will create an MCP server, that is what every company has done now. They are saying that, okay, you want to use our tool, be no buddies, we will give you our MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, you don't have to worry, just tell in a simple language what has to be done, our MCP server will get called and give you the answer. For example, to do the web search, either I could write a complete script.
Mayank Aggarwal: Or I could just directly, right, hit this MCP server, and it will get me the result. Anything which happens, it can be updated as well, so I can refresh the tool list, so that it gets updated if anything new by any chance is added.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, that improves my adaptability with
Mayank Aggarwal: AI tools a lot. So that is where MCP is needed.
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, in a similar manner, let's just equal real tool, let's say Jibal as an example.
Mayank Aggarwal: Inside this, if they tomorrow say that, hey, we have integrated everything with AI, so you just add an MCP and anything which you want to do the selfie capture, or anything for that matter, like, whatever you want to check and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: It can be done directly via AI, you don't have to fill it manually, you don't have to fill 10 rows manually or do anything.
Mayank Aggarwal: all these dashboards and everything. So, of course, the usability will increase.
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that is the reason MCP is required. As a very good example, this table is used a lot in the AI space.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because they are very quick on making changes and making it relevant with the AI agents and everything.
Saranya Thangaraj: No care.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because if they don't provide a server, then… like, just as an example, if they don't provide the Stavly server.
Mayank Aggarwal: then I will be very, very less chances that I will be using this.
Saranya Thangaraj: Mhmh,
Mayank Aggarwal: Because then I will have to write the script, and then I will have to make sure that that gets… don't get failed and everything. Similarly, Google… if Google doesn't provide this, then people will not use it. So that is the reason we create MCPs, for the ease of usage and entry point into our application first.
Mayank Aggarwal: Second, now because everyone is using AI, we want to make sure that our apps are compatible with it.
Mayank Aggarwal: As an example, you can easily now connect your application between multiple systems. For example, your AI application can be connected to Gmail, Calendar, and your time track, okay?
Saranya Thangaraj: Mhmhm.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anshul MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: All of this is possible without MCP as well. MCP just makes it a lot more easier.
Saranya Thangaraj: So, you mean to say that, we have used, FastAPI to, no, to get all the logic. Now, instead of, at that FastAPI, we are using Fast MCP, so that I can integrate those tools with any of my, AI application.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, majorly, yes. Just one thing, I have not created fast APIs with it, that matter. Fast API and application, I've created otherwise. Like, otherwise, also, my application would be…
Mayank Aggarwal: Expected and used across multiple places.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just that I've added a layer of fast MCP, or MCP, I would not say fast MCP, just that I've added a layer of MCP on top of it, so as to make it much more easily accessible by the tools and everything.
Saranya Thangaraj: So, suppose if I'm not using that, fast APA, what will the impact? Anyway.
Mayank Aggarwal: It doesn't matter, I don't care about API.
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: You will have to check key where all your application is being used. For example, if you're having a front-end or anything.
Saranya Thangaraj: Mhkaya.
Mayank Aggarwal: As a user, end user, I don't care. If you're giving me the MCP, and if you're giving me the tools.
Mayank Aggarwal: you have to handle that for how you're executing it. I don't care.
Saranya Thangaraj: In this application, without that Fasty API also, using a MCP, I can… I can do, I can enter the user, you know, like, I can log…
Saranya Thangaraj: Oh.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can do that, but then, unless you will have cost associated, because you will have AI, you will need to have AI here, you will have to… because MCP is not the right protocol for that.
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: API is the right protocol of that. Like, if you are from a data engineering background, every tool, every application is having APIs, right?
Saranya Thangaraj: Yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because normally we connect with the application using API only, we don't connect with MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP comes into picture when you want to integrate AI. So, a simple application.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will not be making MCP calls here.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will not be making MCP calls here. That would be worst system decision or design.
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: API will be used here, and normally, because we are having APIs in every application, we try to extend that by creating MCP servers on top of that. That's the understanding.
Saranya Thangaraj: I don't care.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will not say that, okay, if you're not having APIs, then we use MCP directly, no.
Mayank Aggarwal: That's the wrong approach. We should not do that.
Saranya Thangaraj: I don't care.
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay, Mayank, I'll go through this, VIN.
Mayank Aggarwal: How many exp… how much experience do you have in data engineering?
Saranya Thangaraj: I have a total of 6 years of experience here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Think I just… I think I'm gonna ask one data engineer, no worries, just send me a CV, I will drive…
Mayank Aggarwal: opening is still there. But otherwise, also revise these things a little bit more, because at 60 of the experience, I would expect a little bit more in-depth knowledge about APIs and everything.
Saranya Thangaraj: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: This just will be fine, okay?
Saranya Thangaraj: Sure, sure, yeah. Thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: Abhiraj?
Abhiraj Singh: Yes. Hi, Mayank.
Mayank Aggarwal: Hi.
Abhiraj Singh: Today's class has been, I mean, a bit complicated for me, like, I'll need to revise a bit more of…
Mayank Aggarwal: I totally expected to be…
Abhiraj Singh: I'm doing the fast API. So, one thing I want to know is there was a point where you gave a prompt, and we got the list of tools in sequence in which they would get called, that you showed in MCP Inspector, I think.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is it.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is the prompt.
Abhiraj Singh: We have not connected it to LLM.
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, so that is the, like, first we will be connecting it, like, that is what I expect that you will be doing it with Cloud Desktop.
Mayank Aggarwal: But after making it live on the server.
Abhiraj Singh: Mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then I will be coding MCP client as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: And then I will be using LLM as well. So all the things which we are, as of now, assuming with Cloud Dextron, we will be coding everything and then connecting it and everything.
Abhiraj Singh: Okay, so this will be doing next week.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, I planned to do it today, but I actually took a little bit of time because people were facing issues with understanding this code.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, yes, now we will do it next week. So creating it
Mayank Aggarwal: Live will be taking 15 minutes on an HTTPS, on a server.
Mayank Aggarwal: After that, we will just write a code to create an MCP client and NLM as well. So that host, client, and server, we will be owning all the three things.
Abhiraj Singh: Also, using MCP Inspector, we can also see, like, in what sequence our tools are being called, and what parameters are being passed.
Mayank Aggarwal: We can do that, but MCP Inspector, then I cannot use inside my application. So my idea will be that in the next class, I will be creating a streamlined kind of an application, as an example, where we can, just like how Claude, you just tell Claude to send an email or something, we can do the same thing, nothing else.
Abhiraj Singh: Alright, alright, thank you, Meng, thank you so much.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then all the dots will get connected more nicely. But before that, revision will be required, connecting it to Cloud desktop, if you do it, I think that will be required.
Abhiraj Singh: Absolutely. So, Langchain has been a bit easier for me to understand. The MCP has been a bit trickier for me. I have not.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is not the case. Honestly, honestly, Langchain will become complex as well. The reason is that I have gone a lot in depth of Langchain and MCP both, but Langchain till now, we were doing it in a very sequential manner.
Abhiraj Singh: Right.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, when I do the project, then you will find this thing, because in MCP, now we have understood everything, now we are covering and everything together.
Abhiraj Singh: Mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: Same thing will happen in Langchain. As of now, you have covered Langchain independently.
Abhiraj Singh: Right.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP, by the nature of how it is defined, it is based on using on top of something, which I kind of show you today.
Abhiraj Singh: Mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that is why you are finding it complex, because normally what happens as learners, when two, three things get to us, that is where we find the complexity. Same thing will happen in Langchain once we do MCP and once we do multi-agent and multiple projects, but hopefully you will be able to surely get that, not a problem.
Abhiraj Singh: Alright, definitely, your teaching style is wonderful.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you.
Abhiraj Singh: Thank you.
Abhiraj Singh: Oh, okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great. Hartik, you're next.
Hardik Vora: Hey, Mayank.
Mayank Aggarwal: Right.
Hardik Vora: Thanks, appreciated in detail explanation. My couple of things. So, FastAP I've used earlier, I mean, just through AI and all. So, basic concept, I got a proper understanding when you explained in Fast MCP. I mean, same logic.
Hardik Vora: Same implementation logic, right? So I can relate that. So Swagger is, I mean, just wanted to understand, slash docs, I was not able to see your address bar at that point of time when you were explaining, because it was hidden, I believe.
Hardik Vora: That's why I was asking that time.
Hardik Vora: that fast API, if we execute, via that… this… so Slack docs, if you do Slack Docs, it will directly give us a Swagger,
Mayank Aggarwal: FastAPI, when you create your server using FastAPI, it creates a sign-in page as well for you.
Hardik Vora: So, it's by default, we don't need to do anything, just slide talks, and you will be able to understand.
Mayank Aggarwal: Well, that's the nature of fast API, like, how it makes it easier for you.
Hardik Vora: Okay, that I had not worked on, so I was not aware. And you…
Mayank Aggarwal: Swagger, like, it's a very simple one. I think Redoc, alternate API docs, there is Redock as well, which they have included.
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: or something like this. Malhan, these are our very, basic kind of a thing. In the APA world, we kind of use it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Best I can do is I'm recording these things up, so I will provide all of you with the recording as well, like, that is something which…
Hardik Vora: Yeah, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: one of you.
Hardik Vora: be helpful, I mean.
Mayank Aggarwal: There, I'm recording these things from scratch, so let's see how many of you will be taking advantage of that. Kyoki, ideally, if you're joining this course, I expect these things are available.
Hardik Vora: and development tools, I mean, API calls and all, fetch, etc.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is the same thing. You use Postman and you are simply having… Correct, correct, correct. …th thing, not a problem at all. You can hit it via Postman as well, not a problem.
Hardik Vora: So that I'll go through it in Spanish.
Mayank Aggarwal: curl, Postman, Swagger, Redoc, anything you want to do it, there are hundreds of applications for documentation on API.
Mayank Aggarwal: Chaga is just one of the most common ones, so yeah.
Hardik Vora: Okay. So, I mean, very important question, Mayank, if you can just go to the code. So, I understood what you were explaining. One second.
Hardik Vora: Just a second, just a sec.
Mayank Aggarwal: Meanwhile, Zach, can you ask your dog?
Zackariya Yoosuf: Hi. Yeah, as far as, as I understood, you know, from the cloud desktop, it will be connected to this, MCP, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: You will have to read that command which I gave you for today.
Zackariya Yoosuf: Yeah, yeah. So, it will automatically insert the, time, right? Time logs.
Mayank Aggarwal: if you… Corrected properly, then it will do that.
Zackariya Yoosuf: Okay, so my question is, in that case, how it will select the project? Project will be multiple projects.
Mayank Aggarwal: We will have to tell, it will either ask if there is a convert… there is a problem, or then again, you can create a resource where we have the projects created.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, we can have the list of projects via the same. We can have a resource where we are making sure that you are just entering the exact project.
Mayank Aggarwal: As it can enter anything out of order.
Zackariya Yoosuf: Okay. Anyway, okay, so, it will not be 100% automation, but,
Mayank Aggarwal: It will be 100%, it can be. If you give it to the resource, AI is that smarter and do not make that mistake.
Zackariya Yoosuf: Oh, okay, okay. Yeah, okay. My second question is, is MCP, can we connect this MCP to, any other… now we connect it here with Python, right?
Zackariya Yoosuf: the front end. So, can we connect this with, VB, app? Any app?
Mayank Aggarwal: which supports MCP, you get connected to that.
Zackariya Yoosuf: Okay, because it's a new technology, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: normally now, any application, like, any… all the IDs and everything, they support… they have support for MCPs.
Mayank Aggarwal: For the local learning one, you will have to follow the approach which I showed you in CloudTextalk, where you have to edit the config.
Zackariya Yoosuf: Hmm,
Mayank Aggarwal: are the…
Mayank Aggarwal: Remote one, we will make it remote in the next class now, but we will make it active on the link, so that you can see the same.
Zackariya Yoosuf: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? Actually, I got the idea for connecting with you yesterday, let me give you a time tracker, because you told me, Naki, you are in the HR space and something like that.
Zackariya Yoosuf: Yeah, yeah, yeah, so I was thinking how I can make use of this thing.
Mayank Aggarwal: That's why I thought, okay, this is a really good use case, but actually, this happens. Earlier, I had built a recipe box kind of a thing, but I thought that, no, no, let me then move away from the basic one, and create something which is genuinely helpful in the real use case.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anything else?
Hardik Vora: Yeah.
Zackariya Yoosuf: Yeah, thank you, no, no, thank you.
Hardik Vora: Yeah, should I continue?
Mayank Aggarwal: Nick, can you just check in with me?
Karthik: Hello?
Mayank Aggarwal: One return to Hardik area.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'll take a little quick, yeah.
Hardik Vora: Sure, sure, Mike. Just, can you just go to the code, today's code?
Hardik Vora: So, you mentioned that, I mean, at MCP.tool, once we create, right, it is more, hands-on of our, holding it, I mean, the changing of the code. So, just as an example, you mentioned.
Hardik Vora: In that, if you want department, right? So here, I can implement in that way, so that I can.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes.
Hardik Vora: we can… I can implement, and I have all the, details in my hand, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Exactly.
Hardik Vora: Correct. So, suppose we don't write in this way, and as you mentioned, that there is only 4 steps which you have, I mean, commented, and Vince, you have done for Fast MCP to FastAPI, right? Yeah. Here. So here, the only disadvantage is, I will have to manually, tweak in my APIs.
Hardik Vora: Of handling those things, and then it might fail to all the people using it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, so…
Hardik Vora: That is the.
Mayank Aggarwal: What I meant by that is, actually, you can add in top of that, like, if you, like, right now, if I do this.
Mayank Aggarwal: This one is right now having, I think, 5 things. Okay, let me…
Mayank Aggarwal: Because, see, it is taking all the APIs.
Mayank Aggarwal: But I can add now on top of that as well, but it's not that key, just 4 will be taken, and you can now add on top of that as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Verma…
Hardik Vora: No, that is the additional one, Mayank, that I understood, that we can add…
Mayank Aggarwal: to the next part, what I mentioned was that
Mayank Aggarwal: As an experienced or a good developer, we don't… Touch things which are working.
Hardik Vora: Hmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: So if you want to have a resource kind of a thing, rather than me going and changing it in here, which this API might be used by maybe hundreds of people, or any application, I would not do that. Rather, I will make… want to make sure that I can create an MCP and take that hold on.
Mayank Aggarwal: So I'm… I was just suggesting that, and that is true for everything. If you have to create another application which uses APIs from this.
Mayank Aggarwal: Normally, you will not change a lot of things in here, because that can break things.
Hardik Vora: Hmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: That's a normal… that's… see, that's… it isn't nothing right or wrong with it. That's an experience-based, suggestion, which… that, hey, don't change anything which is working. Rather, create on top of it, and that is where, rather than
Mayank Aggarwal: calling it like this, maybe I will call the tool directly, so I can…
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, sorry, I can call the API directly here.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that my APIs are not changing, and I'm able to get the best of the both worlds.
Hardik Vora: Correct. And Mike, only one understanding, just scroll down, you mentioned someone asked you on the DB part, right? You created the two, two new things. Just scroll down.
Mayank Aggarwal: You just, yeah.
Hardik Vora: This one, this one, yeah, yeah. So, what is the purpose of this? I mean, I didn't.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want to have any, like, see, as of now, you are limited with the things which you can do, right?
Hardik Vora: Hmm?
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want to execute any query on DP, like, because you are having AI,
Mayank Aggarwal: You want to just change anything in the DB, you don't care about
Mayank Aggarwal: the one which are already given. So, in here, I'm not giving you the option of
Mayank Aggarwal: writing or running anything. It is exactly done, just I'm taking the arguments from you.
Mayank Aggarwal: But if you want to have a control where you want… you can run… you want to run anything on the DB, then this kind of things are required. So, Dex to SQL kind of an agent-only scale.
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Hardik Vora: Okay, and one final question, Mayank, you always show in the connectors, right, where there are a couple of options, need approval, read and write access and all. So, how can that type of implementation.
Mayank Aggarwal: middleware and HITM.
Hardik Vora: Oh, okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Materparent HD, you know, that is all… There's just nothing.
Hardik Vora: In the… in the MCP part.
Mayank Aggarwal: maybe mother, that is being done by host. So when you use Langchain.
Mayank Aggarwal: middleware and HITF, and you can do it.
Hardik Vora: No, no, so… Okay? In this… Server which you have created.
Mayank Aggarwal: In the MCP server, yes.
Hardik Vora: Correct. So we have that connectors, and suppose this, we create MCP server, and we push it in our, existing connectors, which we will do, right? Which we have done, right? That receipt updated in the MCP server, in the cloud desktop. So there, if I want such kind… yeah, yeah, this, this, that screen, needs approval screen.
Mayank Aggarwal: SCB, what is this?
Hardik Vora: So there, we… we have not, created in a way that, read-write access needs approval.
Mayank Aggarwal: Naik load has created.
Hardik Vora: This week, can we handle…
Mayank Aggarwal: Do that.
Hardik Vora: Okay, okay, okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: This is not a MCP feature, this is a host feature, or client feature.
Hardik Vora: Do you have?
Mayank Aggarwal: not KJs Insider, but maybe Claude is having the middle wares and the everything in between.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that it can ask you these things.
Hardik Vora: Can we tweak this, in our codebase? Because it has automatically asked here, right? If you select the.
Mayank Aggarwal: I don't think that's the right approach. I would have… see…
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP will not have HIT. MCP, why would you have a human group in MCP?
Hardik Vora: So that's a…
Mayank Aggarwal: Wrong approach.
Hardik Vora: Hmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: That's the wrong approach. Even if we can do it, even if we can raise an event and that event asks you the thing.
Hardik Vora: Mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: You see, ideally in AI, obviously, in programming, it is about how, not about if. You can do everything.
Hardik Vora: Hmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: But I would not want to raise an event hall here.
Mayank Aggarwal: and say that, hey, work on this. So that's not a good decision design.
Mayank Aggarwal: Is that a discussion?
Hardik Vora: It is not in, hmm…
Mayank Aggarwal: No, that's not a right way. When I'm hitting this call, I hit up an event here, and that event asks me to.
Hardik Vora: No, I was just trying to understand how Claude has implemented that.
Mayank Aggarwal: A lot is much better with, middleware and everything.
Hardik Vora: Okay, okay, got it, got it. Thanks, thanks, man.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Yeah, hi, thank Debrahi said.
Mayank Aggarwal: One minute, so… Just… Karthik, you're next.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me go by the complete…
Karthik: My question is… my question is about my career. Anshul whether it's the union or CSV
Karthik: Yeah, sure, yeah, I'll just wait.
Mayank Aggarwal: Debrajudihi.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Yeah, so, one question is, in Google Cloud, if I have to, deploy first API, right, we always probably use, Cloud Run. So, if the MCP, if I… if I convert it to, through the first MCP, probably, should I deploy in the Agent Engine, or somewhere?
Mayank Aggarwal: not be an agent engine, I think. You can just… you just need a normal server, so cloud and everything can be used.
Mayank Aggarwal: just search, GCP MCP servers, is there anything which is supported?
Mayank Aggarwal: Not this, like, sorry.
Mayank Aggarwal: host a MCP server.
Mayank Aggarwal: on GCP? Are they providing something out of the box? So, yeah, there is Cloud Run, which you can now use. Not Agent Engine. Agent Engine is where Agent Runs.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay, so Cloud Run or GK would be the best choice.
Mayank Aggarwal: Well, Cloud Run or any GK will have anything now which is having resources, any normal machine.
Mayank Aggarwal: Anything which you want on that product.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: And, second thing in the production-grade project, suppose, I have an agent build with Langdrop or Langchain, and I want to connect MCP tools, and that is actually the first MCP-based
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: MCP, which is probably hosted in Cloud Run. So, in this…
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you repeat? Can you repeat, Sony?
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: So, probably, I have one MCP server hosted in Cloud Run, and that is using the first MCP, and there are certain tools and Art Defined, for example. And now I want that, tools to be called from an agent, which is probably in GK, built with, Langraph.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: So, in this, because both are into two different environments, two different services, there might be an authentication process required, right? So, every time… right? So, how… is that Google that manages it, or is it something that…
Mayank Aggarwal: You see that normally when you will connect two services.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is how you will enter the authentication. MCP doesn't care.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay, so normally we do, like, we have the Google inbuilt APIs that we are calling, right? So, in the backend, maybe there are X509…
Mayank Aggarwal: How many in… exactly the way you will be having the same authenticated via… Google, normally.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is how you will do it, because that connection doesn't care what is running, like Google, GKE, or Cloud Run, they doesn't care. First, they need to be connected.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that has nothing to do with what is running inside it.
Mayank Aggarwal: First you fix that, then we can have that MCP is it now having some other authentication?
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Boom.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCV will not take the first, just to give you a little bit clarity.
Mayank Aggarwal: First, it is important that you are able to connect to me. Now, what you ask, or what I give the answer, that doesn't matter. First, this connection is important. In a similar manner, it doesn't matter what is running in Cloud or not GKE, you have to first make sure that they are able to connect either via some request, some authentication running on the same user account. So that is how it happens.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay, okay.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay, and the last question is, for example, as I'm making the MCP customized, from the dueling section, can I call the LLM? Maybe I have some deployment… You can.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: But, is it the best approach? No.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: No, definitely not. MCP is meant for that, yeah, just a moment.
Mayank Aggarwal: It is majorly the action part of why…
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Without token. Something without token, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Plus, one more thing, MCP can use the client's LNM?
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Oh.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? That is where the two-way complication… I will try to recreate that it's a little difficult.
Mayank Aggarwal: But MCP can use the client… client's,
Mayank Aggarwal: thing, so that should be helpful. Let me just check if I quickly asked. Fast MCP server use AI from client.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, we piedanikhi.
Mayank Aggarwal: Throughout feature, Yahira LM sampling. This was actually the feature, so sampling.
Mayank Aggarwal: context injection and everything. So, this is some type of a code. So, ask client AI, you can give the problem. So, this is a better way of doing it. Let me showcase that, and let me try to see that how can I integrate this as well in the next class. So, here, your client is saying to the… sorry, your server is saying to the MCP
Mayank Aggarwal: Can you… can I please use your AI?
Mayank Aggarwal: So, it will take a prompt, like, send this prompt.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pretty advanced thing.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay, yap prompt ingestion ho, hai.
Mayank Aggarwal: Server is saying to client ki Muja AI use Kantar.
Mayank Aggarwal: to chemicals at Tom Aka. So, this concept is known as sampling.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Okay, okay.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: MCP toolkulk kartana async Yoos hota, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Yoos, you think?
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Correct. So it is… it is because we want… we don't want to put a dependency, some kind of.
Mayank Aggarwal: Async, I will explain you from our use case, because I do plan to make our code also async when I deploy it.
Mayank Aggarwal: See, if you're not doing async, let's say that I am executing this query, okay? And it is taking 5 minutes, just as an example.
Mayank Aggarwal: It will wait, it will not have any other requests coming in till then.
Mayank Aggarwal: An initial.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: No, is that?
Mayank Aggarwal: it up.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Asing nahi dala toh connection lose hojay, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Naid dalat po… Jo agar amna execute karar. If something takes 2 minutes.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Hmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: you have 5 requests, they will take 10 minutes total to execute. Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, Paralytica.
Mayank Aggarwal: first waited, everyone else will have to wait before the execution comes. So that is why async is used normally.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Go to key.
Mayank Aggarwal: When I create my server and example, I give you all the access.
Mayank Aggarwal: You should note that if someone is hitting it, I'm waiting for the work to finish, and then I'm allowing anyone else to do it, so that is the reason.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Tick, tick, tick. Soldiers.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yep.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Thank you so much, thanks, thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: So for that matter, even async and Python can hold my basic concepts, I will be creating videos, very much in-depth, and I will be sharing that.
Mayank Aggarwal: I plan to do that this month, but let's see. Thankfully, for the last 2-3 months, my plans are not my plans. Life is taking a good role, so yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: I have to go home and all these things, yeah.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: out of the box hai. Aphe 80K kuppar jo videos bana deka, actually, my follow, but A2K, A2A kupar thhoda akut specific.
Mayank Aggarwal: Tomaro.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Bye, okay. Thank you so much. Thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: A2A, I will be teaching after ADK only, okay? It's from Google only, so it will be… Gotcha.
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Thank you so much.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great, great, great. This was Debrajyoti, right?
Debajyoti Mukhopadhyay: Yes, yes.
Mayank Aggarwal: Great. Panda, you are next.
Mayank Aggarwal: Pradeep.
Mayank Aggarwal: Karthik?
Prerana Dhoke: Yes, ma'am. Hello? Okay, Priy.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can ask quickly.
Prerana Dhoke: Yeah, so, I was… I just want to ask that, if I have a web… server.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Prerana Dhoke: And I have, created a MCP, using, from, Fast API. So…
Mayank Aggarwal: Sanjay, okay?
Prerana Dhoke: Yeah, I have just googled it, and I found that we can run
Prerana Dhoke: Both at same server port.
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, we are doing it here, actually. See?
Prerana Dhoke: No, no, but,
Prerana Dhoke: This will have a client put 9999, but can… can I make a direct API call?
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, that's accurate.
Mayank Aggarwal: Time clock means Yaha Pay, we are having… Yeah. …the localhost 8,000 for the website.
Mayank Aggarwal: Slash MCP is my MCP endpoint. It is a 3-label HTTP endpoint.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, on the same server, we have both the Gates running on the same link.
Prerana Dhoke: So, where we have used streamable HTTP? Because…
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm not showing you this.
Prerana Dhoke: Go bun.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'm not showing you what level.
Prerana Dhoke: Okay, good.
Mayank Aggarwal: I showed you the STDIO one.
Mayank Aggarwal: Tomorrow, when we will make it live, that is where I will explain kand what this is.
Mayank Aggarwal: In here, if you will go…
Prerana Dhoke: means both API call will be…
Prerana Dhoke: accessible as well as MCP call.
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, mother, it is a server, it doesn't care whether it doesn't care, like, has a problem at all. Server should be able to handle the load. Smeho, we can have it that way.
Prerana Dhoke: Okay, because I, I searched online, so it says that, MCP.streamable is a typical app we have to use for same…
Mayank Aggarwal: We have done that. We have done that.
Prerana Dhoke: And, and, and then mount, MCP app.
Mayank Aggarwal: Huh.
Prerana Dhoke: We have done that. Okay, we have done that. Okay, okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Beautiful.
Prerana Dhoke: Okay, that's… I need to confirm. Thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, what I've done is, ki, I'm saying ki mhich, whatever app I'm running, which is my normal application.
Mayank Aggarwal: FastAVUSMCP mount, please mount this.
Prerana Dhoke: Okay, means both will work, API and Opacity also.
Mayank Aggarwal: That's the right way of deploying it, actually, whether we will not have two servers or something. AG server, we will have everything deployed.
Prerana Dhoke: Yes.
Prerana Dhoke: Okay, sure. Go ahead, thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: Beautiful.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'll take…
Karthik: I'm Angela.
Mayank Aggarwal: Bye.
Karthik: Vasudevira, thank you so much for all this, deepening up. Thank you.
Karthik: Naika, it's about my career, the right interview is to complete, or is it? Career you will have to wait.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because people before you are also waiting.
Karthik: Yeah, yeah, same thing, yeah, yeah, I'm happy to… yeah. Okay. Yeah, you should.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, one minute.
Mayank Aggarwal: For all other people.
Mayank Aggarwal: So I think Alok, Harshit, and Karthik, you are waiting for that. Deephuti, I think you are done, so please have your hands down.
Mayank Aggarwal: Hardik and Vasudev, I think we're not connected, so last people, I'm just permuting now.
Vasudev N: Not blaring.
Vasudev N: optimum losses here.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, that's a bit.
Vasudev N: Mayanka, just last, one question, that, I saw you created, Kubernetes local MCP server. Can you just show that, Python file? I'm just curious to know…
Mayank Aggarwal: it is not from, it is not updated, honestly, I'm not even aware. I think I must have been doing something. So, in the developer, there is Kubernetes MCP server.
Vasudev N: Yes. It is running up.
Mayank Aggarwal: Honestly, I'm not sure how it is running, to be very honest. I must have done it after 2-3 months, I will kill it agar.
Vasudev N: Do you have this Python file in your local.
Mayank Aggarwal: it is starting from Cloud extensions, so I'm doing it via extension.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, I think… so, Harshit is running, actually, so…
Vasudev N: Oh, go, go, go.
Mayank Aggarwal: Extension part, you can also add multiple things.
Vasudev N: Because even, the moment when I saw, I asked your Mayank GPT to create this kind of file for me also.
Mayank Aggarwal: It will be not that. You will not be getting Python file, they provide you. It is not that if you have to start a local server, they provide you.
Vasudev N: Exactly, but we can also customize our tools, right? Instead of depending on the… You can, you can, but…
Mayank Aggarwal: What you should do then is you should work on their provided code. For example, this APFI is also an extension.
Vasudev N: Mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: And this is where, kind of, MCP newer version has moved, so it is a little bit like that. But you don't say that, okay, let me write the content, you just use theirs only.
Vasudev N: Okay, okay, okay. Because, the moment when I saw, since now, it's very clear about TDIO and,
Vasudev N: this streammable HTTP, because STDO is something which we want to use local MCPs, for that we can use that. So I'm thinking that if we can able to customize these kind of tools also for our purpose, instead of using direct Kubernetes MCPs, that's the reason I saw… I was asking.
Vasudev N: It's fine, Mayank, I got.
Mayank Aggarwal: Also, what I will then suggest is that have installed the Kubernetes MCP, then on top of that, you try to make your own Machla.
Vasudev N: But again, the problem is… yeah, the problem is we cannot use… we have to use the API key.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nini, so that is what I'm saying, the abstraction-based thing to where the authentication and everything is taken care of.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just search Cloud, it will be able to tell you, okay, how you can change, like, how you can add and remove tools based on that.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, that ways you will be able to use the authentication and still use the tools. So, will be possible, I guess.
Vasudev N: Okay, okay. Okay, Mayanka, that's all for myself. Thank you. Thank you so much.
Alok: Yeah, hello.
Mayank Aggarwal: Here's a loop.
Alok: Swagger, the way you are using, Swagger, can you…
Mayank Aggarwal: Have you used Swagger earlier, or any MCP… any API event?
Alok: I have used, but you explained more than what I know.
Alok: That's what I said.
Mayank Aggarwal: I have not even touched on Swagger Club. Normally, when you create Skira?
Alok: Yes, you will see the swagger, and then you file the request and get the response.
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, that is okay.
Alok: Yeah, can you just, in 2 minutes, can you explain what the Swagger and how the three things are related?
Mayank Aggarwal: See, when we have an MCP server hosted.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you are having an EPS server, right?
Alok: Huh?
Mayank Aggarwal: That API server can now be hit with Postman.
Mayank Aggarwal: It can be hit with curl request, it can be hit by anyone. Swagger is just a UI which we get to hit the same. So that is where, again, you are seeing,
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah. You are seeing Swagger here, so it just… the thing, it just shows you all the APIs which you have along with their endpoint, what they want and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: Just that.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want, you can do the same thing with Postman as well, with a simple curl command.
Mayank Aggarwal: Swagger is just, like, a documentation for API in a simple manner, nothing else.
Alok: Okay, and suppose this application which you have created locally.
Alok: That…
Alok: I think if I want to deploy it onto the MCP server so that it can be created as MCP and can be accessed by MCP client, then there is no point in installing this application into any GCP cloud, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: In GCP, why would we do that? Like, it depends. If our server, we feel that our server will be used or not.
Mayank Aggarwal: and we use a lot of compute, then we can go for any cloud run or anything. Yeah. So it will depend. If your company's using GCP only, then I will deploy it to GCP, but otherwise, not a use as such.
Alok: Exactly. So, oh, then it will be very… suppose I have an application which is required to create… use by only 15, right? 15 don't be limited. So I will create this, and then I will deploy it on through the MCP server, and give a client to the… those folks who are using any VS Code or cloud code.
Alok: Oh, sorry, in, GitHub…
Mayank Aggarwal: Joe will create a server and tell them however they want to use it, doesn't matter, you don't care about that, no.
Alok: Okay, server, and then they need to add that extra client in VS Code GitHub Copilot. Is it possible?
Mayank Aggarwal: anywhere they want, totally on them. You don't care about that, no.
Alok: Okay, but I have to teach them how to…
Mayank Aggarwal: Manini, if you are specifically asking, then yes, you have to create a server, and you then tell them that, hey, if you're using MCP on VS Code, just add it, like, VS Code gives you these options. If it's an HTTP-based one.
Mayank Aggarwal: then… You can give them link.
Mayank Aggarwal: If it's a local one, then also you can give the same.
Mayank Aggarwal: So…
Mayank Aggarwal: Seems like they support the local host as well, so just give them the link, and then they can use it in VS Code and GitHub Copilot, or anywhere.
Alok: Okay, second. Okay, now suppose whatever the application I have created, that fetches the application, that fetches the data from GCP Cloud.
Alok: And it is able to access… my application is able to access the data, because my user ID is there.
Mayank Aggarwal: Then you will need to have… make sure that either you are whitelisting the server IP address.
Mayank Aggarwal: Or somehow connecting it if it is not on GCP. Inside the GCP, I think it will be pretty straightforward then.
Alok: Okay, now suppose I have deployed this application, and in GCP, okay, and I have… in GCP, there is a separate namespace, and that namespace is trying to
Alok: Huh.
Alok: access that.
Alok: application. Now, that application
Alok: which is there in the GCP. There are two applications. One is my application, which is trying to access another application.
Alok: And another application is accessible via our HTTPS URL.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Alok: Now, that HTTPS URL can be used in Postman to query the application and get the result.
Alok: Right? Now, if another application, which is my application, is trying.
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, excellent.
Alok: This is the previous application.
Alok: which is accessible via HTTPS application, then how it can access without.
Mayank Aggarwal: Reddy portal, not confusing, sorry.
Alok: Yeah, yeah, sorry. Okay, so there are two applications. One is API, via which I will query and I will get the response. This is application A. Application B is the application which
Alok: which is trying to access application A, but accessible… application A is accessible via only HTTPS. So, is there any way by which application A must be having another
Alok: a URL which can be used in order to create, call it within GCP by application B.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ideally, there should be.
Mayank Aggarwal: You should be having an HTTP link
Mayank Aggarwal: the API-hosted link, so that application B can call that up.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you want to directly call the HTTP request. Otherwise, how will the connection get done, right?
Alok: Okay, and if I…
Alok: query, I use that VS Code, and I just query in the GitHub Copilot to give me that HTTP link via which it can be called.
Alok: It can…
Mayank Aggarwal: Naik that will get a Popallam or not to that.
Alok: then how I'll come to know what is that link URL with the help of which…
Mayank Aggarwal: person who has created it.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you're using someone's application, they will give you the link or something.
Alok: Ideally, it should be… there should be Veera out here, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Oh, they should provide it, nothing, nowhere else. If I've created an application, I want you to access it.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will give you the link, no? I will tell you, look, Naik, this is the.
Alok: Generally, yes. Generally, people create in such a way that it should be accessible outside GCP via HTTPS, and within GCP via HTTP, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: HTTP and HTTPS, yeah, yeah, that's so fine, because within HTTP, you don't need to have the secure connection, that is already checked.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that ways, it's all fine. That phase, of course, it's not a problem.
Alok: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, so that's a security kind of a thing. Normally, we can have HTTPS and everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: See, all the protocols and security thing which you are aware about, same thing kind of gets to the MCP and everything as well, because they are just connections, nothing else.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Alok: Thank you.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, Harshit, let's get back to you.
Mayank Aggarwal: And let's do it really quick.
Mayank Aggarwal: Push it.
Harshit Goyal: Yeah, thanks for, man.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, extremely sorry for the wait.
Harshit Goyal: No problem, no problem, I understand that, yeah. So, Mayanka, so just, just let me give you some background about me, and then we'll discuss. So, I have around 15 plus years of experience, and since last 10 years working with the data applications,
Harshit Goyal: Apache Spark, Databricks, and stuff. And now I'm moved to the data platforms, creating the applications, which is data… data application, basically, from the platform, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Harshit Goyal: And so, what do you think, like, after this? Because I… now I got good understanding of Langchain and MCP as well. What should be the target job for me, if I ask you?
Mayank Aggarwal: You have 15 years of experience, you are already having the… complete…
Mayank Aggarwal: Understanding about data engineering, and hopefully then a lot more in depth.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will then suggest that you should be targeting an architect kind of a role at any position, in either some startup or in some company.
Mayank Aggarwal: Provided you are very good in designing, and to be very honest, AI is just a part of your work, or part of your building.
Mayank Aggarwal: not the complete thing, because right now as well, most companies suffer by creating good systems rather than integrating AI to it. Integrating AI is not that difficult. So, target job for you should be somewhere at an architect or at the tech lead level, if it's a very big company.
Mayank Aggarwal: If it's Amazon, etc, then you can be at an EM level.
Mayank Aggarwal: That's the best job for you. In there, 70-80% of your
Mayank Aggarwal: Capability will be tested on the work which you have already done.
Mayank Aggarwal: not a lot on your AI understanding, not on this course as well, because in the 15 years, if you have built scalable systems, something which solves the actual problem and the problem solving, that is what company will pay you for, not the key, Ashish person knows AI in-depth, or even MCP in depth. That's a very, very big plus point, though. If you can explain MCP in this level.
Mayank Aggarwal: to anyone, they will know that, yeah, yeah, this person knows, and that's a very, very big plus point, rather than you just saying that, hey, this is an MCP. If you understand and explain them that, hey, I can tell you the complete MCP architecture, that will kind of showcase to them, ki, this person, he is serious, he knows the things.
Mayank Aggarwal: In a similar manner, he will be understanding other things, and he will be able to make much better systems than a normal person.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that is… that's a much better job for you. Like, that's very, very big for you, but yeah, role is architect level.
Harshit Goyal: Yeah, so for that, our role, I need to understand the SDL and SDL as well, right? High-level design and low-level.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, yes, that's, like, the most important thing. Balaksi, for 15 years of experience, based on my ex… multiple talking with multiple people.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I give you a problem.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay, Harshit, I want to make sure that I solve this problem via tech. You should be able to design each and everything around it. If I even say that, Harshit, it should be manageable by, let's say, millions of requests per day.
Mayank Aggarwal: Caching, scaling, auto-scaling, downscaling, you should be able to do all that things up.
Harshit Goyal: Right. So, one… one couple of favors needed from your side, if you can give… give her, like, any recording or any UdayMe course.
Mayank Aggarwal: I am already… I plan to pick that up. Actually, I plan to pick that up with one of my friends, but right now, he and me both are busy, so that is at least pushed to the next month, because my August was not very health-friendly. So, once I start doing that, then I will be happy to share it.
Mayank Aggarwal: And yeah, I do plan to cover AI system design in that, because I personally love designing a lot, like, I genuinely love AI system… system design a lot. So that way, I will be, hopefully, able to
Mayank Aggarwal: Created a much better thing, yeah.
Harshit Goyal: One more question. So, if I'm trying to get a job outside India.
Harshit Goyal: Is this the same pattern I should follow, or… Yes. There may be some kind of a tweak?
Mayank Aggarwal: No, no, almost the same. Just… honestly.
Mayank Aggarwal: read about the interviews and how they happen outside India, rather than just
Mayank Aggarwal: Kind of trying to, shoot in the dark.
Mayank Aggarwal: That would be also much better.
Harshit Goyal: Do you have any references, we talk about, also, Aditya, if you can refer?
Mayank Aggarwal: Not really, like, I… my understanding comes, thankfully, from multiple things which I have built, and because I keep on doing that. Best thing which I have found is Claude and everything, so they are pretty good with explaining everything.
Harshit Goyal: Okay. Yeah.
Harshit Goyal: Okay, yeah, thanks, thanks, ma'am. Thank you. One more question I have, so…
Harshit Goyal: this MCP inspector, right, that we have created. So, in MCP, if we have started simultaneously two different inspectors.
Harshit Goyal: with the different ports, right? It will be started on my local.
Harshit Goyal: How this RPC call works? It will work, like, how this RPC call works, or initialization happened works. It will be on the individual level, right? Like, two different MCP inspectors, their own session, their own RPC call, their own questions, and everything, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Mcp Inspector can have multiple clients, so right now we are starting with a single one. If we would have different 2-3 servers, we could have
Mayank Aggarwal: done that.
Harshit Goyal: And in case the same server, using the different command line that you've given with the client port equals to 900 or 9000, whatever it is, we can start multiple, right? And then it will have its own.
Mayank Aggarwal: And you can store multiple MCP inspectors, so that they can connect with different servers and everything, not a problem.
Harshit Goyal: Oops.
Harshit Goyal: Yeah, thanks, Meg.
Mayank Aggarwal: Karthik or Hardik, whoever was first, I forgot, but let's move in the sequence only.
Hardik Patel: Yeah, I…
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, Hardik.
Hardik Patel: Yeah, so, Mayank, I only… I have only two questions.
Hardik Patel: Initially, apne jo, recipe box already aapka ek MCP server tha, thicket, aur hamne ekusar server bhne hai, same name se ha. Toho automatically underscore update le tay nam ya, se huh? apne diatap.
Mayank Aggarwal: Take a minute. Krishna recipe box meh.
Hardik Patel: Jayap logo nih config file mein malabh vaan selod desktop app seh hum logo na configure gya, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: Huh?
Hardik Patel: Hamara local, local MCP server, correct?
Mayank Aggarwal: Huh.
Hardik Patel: So, Aka already, previously aapne, suppose malap basically duplication of name hota hai, Sarwarka, to automatically wo update karte lei letter.
Mayank Aggarwal: Duplication should be avoided. No problem Naik. I think it will take a later one in the file.
Mayank Aggarwal: config, and then I've not tried it out. I mean, when a recipe box updated, I'm like the other, because recipe box, I tried out
Mayank Aggarwal: Madhuri… no, I may avoid krna chee? Because it just does a one-line change, so why to do that? I think that it will take the latest one in the fight. Sidharak hai.
Mayank Aggarwal: So it will take the latest one, uske dia mein kushni ganda config page aake hai.
Mayank Aggarwal: which I showed you, IK shared in my fight with you yesterday, no? Kant kar sakti hain.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's have a recipe box with two names, and do Alok phases, and let's check if Parikh. To pallod hay last parod hai.
Mayank Aggarwal: Most probably.
Mayank Aggarwal: fast MCP1, fast MCP2. Yeah, see the afloat Sushhop.
Hardik Patel: Basically, ya, yaya patch leg.
Mayank Aggarwal: Well, that's the debugging way.
Hardik Patel: Correct, correct. Ye shutdown wala jo kali tin amok toh kustuk hain, Mehukho chees samaljne ai, actually. Agar amok streaming HTTP use karthe hain, toho usmeh toh directly amok shutdown kar sekte hain. Bala bhapnek browser gloss kya ya.
Mayank Aggarwal: normally we are just closing it. Browser ogeh application ogeh. Normally as well. Bhar client normally karte, toh, stream email HTTP may just close the connection.
Hardik Patel: Correct. Langin utape kaman karna Bharthai, correct? From the client side to, server side.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, what happens is that is internally hota na hai. Toh, internally, saurav input bant kartheek hai.
Mayank Aggarwal: OS level commands unto ya.
Hardik Patel: Gotcha.
Mayank Aggarwal: kartheek Bolge khek mehodamuk kar signal. Agar baichan neu doto firamikkil kartek hai.
Mayank Aggarwal: Panda.
Hardik Patel: Okay, okay. malap use case.
Mayank Aggarwal: kart ya.
Hardik Patel: Huh?
Mayank Aggarwal: Toh connection kum meh churung kanya, meh ko, ideally ha bandh saare connections bant karke.
Hardik Patel: Correct.
Mayank Aggarwal: Jayapag gaapi MCP inspector open kiapko close kari kanap band kar kyo. Nito. Taset toyo jya yadne bant gi alignho connection khau abhibbi.
Mayank Aggarwal: MCP Kulakarhijih mehi connected a kyukh bejani
Mayank Aggarwal: Of course, no timeout saur died on Hojay ba. Thinka.
Mayank Aggarwal: Again, scaling my shivas, toh, timeout k saps.
Hardik Patel: Gotcha. Toh agar agar humblogo, Yuske lia mei humblogo na lika hua vot, toh easily ho jyata hai, malik timeout ka.
Mayank Aggarwal: Bhartha, ideally, there are things which are said directly. Shut down the abhne architecture, like, cycle me a Jat hai.
Mayank Aggarwal: I think abhih chauh no stateless kart obi kafi CHI. Honestly menus ko pada hai abhor thuda abhin se panda bat, the way I can explain you the way I do normally.
Mayank Aggarwal: features,
Mayank Aggarwal: architecture level pay, but to answer it, yes.
Hardik Patel: That's idle, idle wave over here.
Mayank Aggarwal: If I showcase to you, right, just to showcase this, yapirankarrah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Little detail? Yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Hmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is, I'm closing it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Si.
Mayank Aggarwal: Client transport Clare times clothes. Osne karam, malik bandi, okay? me Bandar klei.
Hardik Patel: Gotcha.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is how it happens. Normal example is ka, Tomar acha. Whenever you close the windows, your Mac, your laptop.
Mayank Aggarwal: Toh koshish kartek yung sari applications gracefully shut down karte, malabank karte.
Hardik Patel: Correct.
Hardik Patel: Deacon.
Mayank Aggarwal: kanh state kioskisko.
Mayank Aggarwal: And now, twist me.
Mayank Aggarwal: Bandu.
Mayank Aggarwal: KAP ako request huti.
Mayank Aggarwal: Apoor request pathar aiki bhai, das request kanne ke, apne to request di, request to challenge Ari hai, apne beja ni ki me bando chuka toho wa saur response. So, multiple benefits of this. Madhur, that's a very one-on-one kind of a system designing thing.
Hardik Patel: low level ekdam chhoty level.
Mayank Aggarwal: Like, I normally ask the person. Lakhti hai.
Mayank Aggarwal: or abhka diese Lakhtapandogi ha. Jayapod kart ya, tokyawi ka. These things can pop up, or hotah kayi ki, what I have seen is.
Mayank Aggarwal: ki system design ko ki na kumar details, toh agar bisseho gedabhoge ki ai baki jag bi Yusu rahulp. Exampe gela mehi ako laptop example, right? Kya bant kart. Toh se mehi cheesy Yusuf, hi toh, system design at a very bigger point, converge, kya chauh cha system, follow pall li the ha.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, EFI, the author system.
Hardik Patel: Pop.
Mayank Aggarwal: Abh aapkar lohya bolo gaj mehdha ha MCP suya. Sari Reyhai kanothya toh, fidhi sa help karthe interview kaya kani mein.
Hardik Patel: Yusk mala Bhsamnya Alok ko patajko lo lip chhijihi pataya.
Mayank Aggarwal: Agarne Bola MCPAT karte hain. What do you know? Banda Bol rak ye chai know how to connect with MCP 202 MCP Bala… he will… the second person has a much more better chances of getting selected.
Mayank Aggarwal: He said I have the complete lifecycle architecture and how to create the servers and everything. I've done this. So this is how you control the interview. The more you know, the luck gets low and the chances becomes high.
Hardik Patel: MC bikar prompt jo hai, prompt resource.
Hardik Patel: Yuska use case mehi aapko chat mein prota, lekin meho abhne Ansar biya chalu chalu mehdiya. Lakhin meho sa detail mehij.
Mayank Aggarwal: usageo. Example litin, ki Apko sam Ritesh, yup Nayak exampleites, jam me najih venaya.
Mayank Aggarwal: Both basic example hai, but some other guys say. Let's say ki aapko weekly report banan ya.
Hardik Patel: Hmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: Let me get the information weekly and everything, jobhi chai.
Mayank Aggarwal: Teja kol ka kan.
Hardik Patel: Hmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: Teja?
Mayank Aggarwal: Let's say aapko play manager po ya, kiskoi formal email bhinda, aapko example, kay lia.
Hardik Patel: Huh.
Hardik Patel: Huh?
Mayank Aggarwal: But at the same time, agar aap mehi MCP rub kar river agar mein aapko ek prompt det.
Mayank Aggarwal: I see common request INR.
Mayank Aggarwal: Toh, rather than Jadhav abhang nanikiya proper flow follow window.
Hardik Patel: Gotcha.
Mayank Aggarwal: You can.
Hardik Patel: predefined prompt, Jessa.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Agar aap ganjith report karukhot ya gerega wo ye follow karyga.
Mayank Aggarwal: However, you follow Bagga results will be much more uniform.
Hardik Patel: Similar kind of ayagar.
Hardik Patel: We're emailing it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Exactly. Toh, ye baab jhad cha benefit, kna aapko example kilaga Muj patai, ki plot, Google Calendar mein Bandai yay postte hai ki can you tell me about my day, about my week?
Hardik Patel: Huh.
Mayank Aggarwal: uniformity agina.
Hardik Patel: Correct, correct, correct.
Mayank Aggarwal: that won't doing Summit.
Hardik Patel: use case kaya hai.
Mayank Aggarwal: It's like a skill. Skil agar prod mein samjya ho health furo.
Hardik Patel: Yeah, yeah, thanks.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you.
Hardik Patel: Thanks, man. I mean, Abhoh Deep Meh Jayo, actually. Is Leah…
Mayank Aggarwal: kana job lagi. Aka meh auna dipika nahi.
Hardik Patel: That's why it me dip… mehi question a RA, actually.
Mayank Aggarwal: So I'm happy, malabai, I really hope no one is hating me for that.
Hardik Patel: Not normal.
Mayank Aggarwal: I don't see anyone who would have been this complete batches across batches. I don't know kisi Nayak mein MCP people are like, MCP mehdi kart ni aka shah.
Hardik Patel: kabine, kabine is…
Hardik Patel: Yeah, I agree.
Mayank Aggarwal: interview abjap kum control kar bhati ho, aurap ko interview control kar ganache Japapatao. Agar bhakis bin abhinati bhos taba interview ki. Correct. MCP bhot important topic hai, Ragh, MCP, these are the basic core topics, Japkap bhai pathology.
Hardik Patel: Correct.
Mayank Aggarwal: And 97.8% lower path, yeah, Matlam. They would just be like, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Hardik Patel: especially, MCP Server Create Connect Lab Could be.
Mayank Aggarwal: Ninito ish lian tokarap joty auraghav k hunke requirement me MCP. Auraghav abhi sam jahati the honee.
Hardik Patel: Hmm.
Mayank Aggarwal: Nikita.
Hardik Patel: Correct.
Mayank Aggarwal: So, yeah, he was understanding the same for Langchain as well.
Mayank Aggarwal: not be a problem. So, yeah, let's trend the time and market it up.
Hardik Patel: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you. Thank you. Karthik, your last one?
Karthik: I meant.
Mayank Aggarwal: Right.
Karthik: Yeah, my… it's about my career.
Karthik: I just use the bathroom desk for my experience. I have 17 years of experience.
Mayank Aggarwal: Kantar, your voice is getting a little bit echoed, so not clear.
Karthik: Tokenam.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes.
Karthik: Yeah.
Karthik: I have 17 years of experience, and currently… 17 years.
Mayank Aggarwal: 17, okay? 17.
Karthik: Yeah, I wouldn't…
Karthik: And, I'm a senior consultant, and working like a business analyst. However, I'm, like, a technical business analyst. I worked as a data analyst for a long time. I'm working… I'm working on data for a very, very long time, and
Karthik: Even though I'm, like, my day-to-day work is not having any involvement of data since machine learning at all. I learned machine learning data science, and I created numerous projects. Even I launched my products also.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Karthik: So, after learning this Langchain and the MCP and all those things, what is the role I can target for, and
Karthik: Do I need to create any of my own products, or AI Agentic products, in order to show the product?
Mayank Aggarwal: won't.
Karthik: Okay.
Karthik: Okay, so what's the…
Mayank Aggarwal: The idea is that the duel ended.
Mayank Aggarwal: See, first is if you're in a company that helps.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay? Overall.
Karthik: Okay?
Mayank Aggarwal: your approach is key, your product is much more helpful now. Like, let's say if you have created a project, if you create an MCP.
Mayank Aggarwal: and you tell your clients, Kieri, now you can use my product directly via AI and MCP, they will be much more happier.
Karthik: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: So that's our biggest takeaway. The main aim is to make sure that the project gets… product gets used properly.
Mayank Aggarwal: That is the main aim.
Mayank Aggarwal: Now, to create that in a much better manner with all the authorization and everything, because, see.
Mayank Aggarwal: Creating a basic MCP server just gets you karteka even created.
Mayank Aggarwal: The one which will actually run in the production will be the one which will be in very much depth, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: So now that I have demystified so many things for you, you will be able to understand those analogies and stuff, so that it will be very helpful.
Karthik: Okay, and from the… assuming that I'm just getting into interview, like, engineering and all, yeah, I… if they just… just look at my profile, like, probably it's not having, like.
Karthik: as a day-to-day work, I might be having a lot of things, like, I'm just connecting with the business people and all, but personally, I would be having a lot of knowledge on data and data. So, I can just project myself, that I do have the knowledge of this one. In order to show that not only I just created a lot of projects and products in my GitH.
Mayank Aggarwal: I will say that best approach of to have a project on your resume which can showcase these things.
Karthik: Mhmh.
Mayank Aggarwal: Because that is where it will get popped up. The projects are the best way. Otherwise, everyone says that they know MCP, RAG, AI, everything.
Mayank Aggarwal: If you don't find anyone who says that today, I don't know AI. So, yeah.
Karthik: When you say project, even I can just create my own project, and they just upload it in my Gita, and they can just show it to me.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, yeah, GitHub, and ideally, that would be better if I had 17 years of experience, that project is not a personal one, but something which you have helped a client.
Karthik: Yeah, because I do have some ideas on creating the projects and products for my client also, and I'm just trying to create the architecture and everything too. So, if it is okay, I can just share that diagram also with yourself.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yeah, I just shared on my Gmail, on my account, and I will have a look on that.
Karthik: Yeah, sure. And, is there any opportunities, if you come across, would you be able to share it with me? I'm actually…
Mayank Aggarwal: 17 years of experience, I don't… I'm not getting a lot. Normally, the opportunities I'm getting is around 2 to 3 to 6 to 7, because…
Mayank Aggarwal: As I mentioned earlier, I normally connect with startups or small-based companies, so that is where their pay range kind of handles. So, yeah.
Karthik: Okay.
Karthik: Okay, fine, yeah.
Mayank Aggarwal: Okay.
Karthik: Yeah, that's all from my India. Thank you so much, Mike.
Mayank Aggarwal: Thank you.
Karthik: And I can share the diagram with you via email.
Mayank Aggarwal: I'll just unmute.
Karthik: Mailed to Mankur already, yeah, I can share it.
Mayank Aggarwal: Yes, Hardik. Let's keep it quick.
Hardik Vora: Hey, Mike, yeah, yeah, thanks, thanks. Mike, only a couple of questions only. You have recently heard on this, security concerns more on the models recently, right?
Mayank Aggarwal: bumping.
Hardik Vora: So, I'm just thinking around Mani… I mean, what should… With a final roadmap.
Mayank Aggarwal: Four.
Hardik Vora: But after learning this AI and all.
Mayank Aggarwal: Create projects, give interviews, nothing else.
Hardik Vora: Okay.
Mayank Aggarwal: Create projects, give interviews, and if you are working on your own product or something, integrate all the learnings into that, nothing else.
Hardik Vora: Yeah, all product will work routinely.
Mayank Aggarwal: Bakr will be having observability, security, and all these things pop up as well, so hopefully we will use up there.
Hardik Vora: Tiki, take it. Look, thanks, man.
Mayank Aggarwal: Good.
Mayank Aggarwal: Cool everyone, thanks a lot. Please revise, because I don't want to stretch MCP beyond the Saturday's class, next Saturday's class, but yeah, let's then get back. I request you to please revise properly.
Mayank Aggarwal: But otherwise, I think you are learning MCP in very much depth, so that is genuinely a very plus point for all of you. So with that, let's meet in the next class. Thank you.